<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<arpg>
<part>
  <title>Game Manual</title>
<chapter>
  <title>Core Rules</title>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <text><Apathy/> is a paper &amp; pencil role-playing game.
    <Apathy/><squo/>s authors have played a great many RPGs including D&amp;D, Heroes
  Unlimited, GURPS, Shadowrun, TMMNT, various White Wolf games
  (Vampire, etc.), Deadlands, and a few others.  While these games are
  all fun, we felt that each game had various shortcomings that could
  be improved upon.  Enter <Apathy/>.  <Apathy/> is designed to be a
  very flexible role-playing system.  <Apathy/> can handle classic
  games with knights and dragons, as well as modern-day, Cyberpunk,
  superhero, or futuristic scenarios.  It excels at fantasy games that
  blend all genres.</text>
    <text><Apathy/> is recommended for advanced role-players (or at
  least for experienced DM/GM/Storytellers).  This is because the
  <Apathy/> system is designed for a unique mix of speed and realism
  rather than carefully <dquo>balanced</dquo> rules.  The <Apathy/>
  rules make it very easy to make unbalanced (<dquo>min-maxed</dquo>)
  or tweaked characters.  <Apathy/> is likewise not appropriate for
  <dquo>rules lawyers</dquo> or excessively anal GMs and
  players.</text>
    <text><Apathy/> was created around several core features.  These
  are what make <Apathy/> a unique game system:</text>
    <itemized-list>
      <item>
        <text><Apathy/> has no fixed character classes, such as
    <dquo>fighter</dquo> or <dquo>wizard</dquo>, etc.  Players can
    pick and choose every detail of their character, rather than being
    forced into set classes.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text><Apathy/> contains rules for all manner of technological
    and supernatural powers, weapons, items, and skills for characters
    to use.  These range from archaic concepts like martial arts and
    swords, through ultra-modern concepts such as cybernetics and
    mecha<mdash/>and the supernatural abilities of magic and psionics.
    These different elements can be used simultaneously without any
    one being excessively powerful.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text>There are no discrete <dquo>levels</dquo> for character
    advancement.  Characters develop and grow constantly, rather than
    infrequent, sudden, increases common to level-based games.  There
    is a distinct and obvious increase in <dquo>power</dquo> as
    characters grow.  This gives players the feeling that their
    characters are constantly improving as the game continues.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text>The game rules are purposely devoid of <dquo>fluff</dquo>
    rules.  Time-consuming (and therefore not fun) look-up tables and
    thick books of rules are nowhere to be found.  <Apathy/> is
    designed to be fast to play.  Most of the <dquo>tables</dquo> in
    the <Apathy/> manuals are just to explain things to the players
    and aren<squo/>t used during play.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text>While <Apathy/> is devoid of many <dquo>clutter
    rules</dquo>, it does have an emphasis on realism.  <Apathy/><squo/>s
    combat system is an excellent compromise between speed and
    realism.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text>In any game of <Apathy/>, the CHARACTERS are the heroes!</text>
      </item>
    </itemized-list>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Basic Terms</title>
    <description-list>
      <item>
        <description>Action</description>
        <text>An <action /> is the most basic unit of time during combat.
  It is roughly equal to one second of time.  Most characters will
  have three <action plural="yes" /> per turn, though certain things can increase or
  decrease this number.  Note that as long as a character is
  unconscious, he or she always has at least one <action /> per turn.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description><base-armor /></description>
        <text> A character<squo/>s natural resistance to bodily harm of
  unusual varieties.  You can think of this as <dquo>toughness</dquo> (not to
  be confused with the skill of the same name).  A character<squo/>s base
  armor reduces the damage they suffer from U (undefined) damage.
  <base-armor /> does not protect against any other form of damage,
  such as P, S, C, or D. Note, that if a character suffers any U
  damage, no matter how high their <base-armor /> might be, they
  always loose at least 1 HP.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>C</description>
        <text> An abbreviation for <crushing />.  When used in
  conjunction with a weapon, it indicates that the weapon in question
  deals <crushing /> type damage.  When used in conjunction with armor, it
  indicates how much <crushing /> damage the armor will defend against.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>CP</description>
        <text> Character Points.  These are points you use to
  <dquo>purchase</dquo> skills, equipment, etc. for your character.  CP can
  also be used to increase attributes according to a special table.
  See the section on character creation.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>Character</description>
        <text> A persona within the game world that is adopted by a
  player.  The player sees through the character<squo/>s eyes, controls the
  character<squo/>s <action plural="yes" />, and speaks through the character<squo/>s mouth.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>D</description>
        <text> An abbreviation for <direct-damage />.  D damage is applied
  directly against the target<squo/>s HP.  Armor, including <base-armor />,
  cannot protect against D damage.  Fortunately, D damage
  sources are few and far between.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description><game-master /></description>
        <text> A person who is in the game that is not a player.
  The <game-master /> controls the game world that the players inhabit.
  He/she controls everything that is not the players.  This includes
  other people (sometimes called non-player characters), monsters,
  natural events, etc.  This is usually abbreviated as <dquo>GM</dquo>.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>HP</description>
        <text> Abbreviation for <hit-points />.  <hit-points /> are used to
  represent a character<squo/>s health.  If a character gets injured, their
  HP decreases.  If a character reaches 0 HP, they fall unconscious.
  If a character reaches -X HP, where X is equal to their maximum HP,
  they are dead.  Note that if a character is below 0 HP, they will
  loose 1 HP per turn (1 HP per 3 seconds when not in combat) due to
  bleeding, unless they are given medical attention.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>HTH</description>
        <text>
see Hand-to-Hand </text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>Hand-to-Hand</description>
        <text> Hand-to-hand is a special type of combat.  It
  takes place when the combatants use no weapons of any kind.  Thus,
  in hand-to-hand combat, only punches, kicks, and similar attacks
  will take place.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description><luck-points /></description>
        <text> Usually, this is short for <luck-points />.  <luck-points /> are
  accumulated during gameplay, and players redeem them for combat
  bonuses, or for saving their character<squo/>s butt if things get rough.
  This is used to help un<luck-points />y die rolls from screwing over players.
  All major character in the game, including significant NPCs,
  villains, etc. will have <luck-points />.  The GM is responsible for
  distributing <luck-points />.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>MA</description>
        <text> Abbreviation for Martial Arts.  It is sometimes used to
  refer to the Martial Arts skill.  See the Martial Arts section for
  more information.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>MP</description>
        <text> Magic Points, also called Mana.  Magic points measure how
  much magic a character can use in a certain amount of time.  Each
  time magic is used (a spell is cast, or the character makes a rune)
  MP are consumed.  If a character has no MP, they cannot use any
  magic until the MP replenish.  MP replenish naturally over time.
  See the Magic section for details.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>Melee</description>
        <text> Melee is a special type of combat.  Melee combat takes
  place when there are no projectile (launched, thrown, shot,
  etc.) weapons or attacks of any kind.  Melee combat includes things
  like hand-to-hand fighting, or using weapons like swords, clubs,
  etc.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>Missile</description>
        <text> A missile weapon is one that flies through the air in
  some manner.  Throwing knives, slings, thrown stones, spears, and
  arrows are examples of missile weapons.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>Non-Player Character</description>
        <text> A person controlled by the <game-master /> who
  interacts with the players.  A non-player character is anyone in the
  game world not controlled by a player.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>NPC</description>
        <text> See Non Player Character.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>P</description>
        <text> An abbreviation for Piercing.  When used in conjunction with
  a weapon, it indicates that the weapon in question deals piercing
  type damage.  When used in conjunction with armor, it indicates how
  much piercing damage the armor will defend against.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>PC</description>
        <text> Power Cells.  This is a measurement of energy or power for
  things like mecha, vehicles, robots, and power armor.  Power,
  measured in PC, is produced by things like engines and is consumed
  by movement systems and weapons, etc.  PC can also mean <dquo>player
  character</dquo>.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>Player</description>
        <text> An actual person, like the authors of this manual<ndash/>or
  you<ndash/>who controls a character in the game world.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>Round</description>
        <text> A <dquo>round</dquo> is the most general unit of time during
  combat.  Any sequence of combat is broken down into one or more
  rounds.  During each round, each combatant gets to take one turn.  A
  round is over whenever all combatants have taken a turn (or are
  unable to for some reason).</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>S</description>
        <text> An abbreviation for <slashing />.  When used in conjunction with
  a weapon, it indicates that the weapon in question deals <slashing />
  type damage.  When used in conjunction with armor, it indicates how
  much <slashing /> damage the armor will defend against.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description><size /></description>
        <text> A representation of the approximate <size /> of objects such
  as people, mecha, etc.  Humans are <size /> level 2.  Each <size /> level is
  approximately double the height and weight of the <size /> below it.
  So, <size /> 2 covers things up to about 7<squo/> tall.  <size /> 3, therefore, is
  about 14<squo/> tall.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>Turn</description>
        <text> A turn is a unit of time during combat.  Each round of
  combat is broken down into one turn per combatant.  During each
  player<squo/>s turn, they get to do whatever they want.  A turn is roughly
  equal to three seconds of time.  Each turn is subdivided into
  <action plural="yes" />.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <description>U</description>
        <text> An abbreviation for undefined damage.  Undefined damage is a
  special type of damage that cannot be prevented by normal armor.  It
  is usually caused by supernatural powers, magic, high tech weapons,
  and similar unusual sources.  Normal (P/S/C) armor cannot
  protect against U damage.  With very few exceptions, the ONLY thing
  that can protect a character from U damage is his or her <base-armor />.
  Note, that if a character suffers any U damage, no matter how high
  their <base-armor /> might be, they ALWAYS loose 1 HP.</text>
      </item>
    </description-list>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Game World</title>
    <text><Apathy/>, like most role-playing games, can be thought of like a play
or a movie.  The players are like the actors; their characters are the
heroes and heroines of the story.  Like a movie, a game can take place
in any number of settings.  The GM is like the director, and decides
the intricacies of the game world.</text>
    <text>The GM should talk with the players and decide upon what kind of game
world they would like to use.  The GM can then finalize the details of
that world, and should tell the players about it before the players
make their characters and the game starts.</text>
    <text>Some things to think about when creating the game world are the following:</text>
    <numbered-list>
      <item>
        <text>Time Period:  Medieval?  Modern-day?  Futuristic?</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text> Location:  on Earth?  A different planet?  A particular city, perhaps?</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text> Level of technology</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text> Allowed game subsections: Magic?  Psionics?  Supernatural Powers? etc.</text>
      </item>
    </numbered-list>
    <text>The <Apathy/> system contains sections for many different types of
games and many different historical settings.  The GM should decide
which ones to allow for each game.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Creating a Character</title>
    <text>The first step in playing <Apathy/> is determining your character
concept.  Talk to the GM and your fellow players for ideas about the
game setting and what kind of character you might want to play.  Your
imagination is the only real limit as to what your character can be.
Perhaps you want to play a heroic knight that fights for honor and
puts monsters to the sword?  Or maybe you<squo/>d rather play a cunning and
seductive thief with a hidden agenda.  You could be a young mecha
pilot<mdash/>inexperienced, but eager to fight for his cause.  Your
character is a hero in the game.  You should take this opportunity to
have fun and do things you can<squo/>t do in real life.</text>
    <image src='/Monsters/Buer.png'/>
    <text>If you are having trouble thinking up a character concept, you might
want to look to books, movies, or even historical precedent as to what
kind of character you want to play.  You could be a space mercenary
like Han Solo from Star Wars, or maybe a secret agent like James
Bond<mdash/>or perhaps an old-west gunslinger.</text>
    <text>Once you have an idea so to what kind of character you want to play,
it<squo/>s time to develop that idea.  Think about what your character looks
like.  How old are they?  How do they dress?  What kinds of
possessions do they have?  What do they do for a living?  What was
their past?  How would they react in a fight?  What would they do if
they were suddenly given a lot of money?  What are their fears?  Their
hopes?  Their goals?</text>
    <text>Now you should have a good understanding of your character<squo/>s
appearance, personality, skills, etc.  What you need to do next is
represent that idea in the <Apathy/> system rules.  Grab a character
sheet, and follow along.</text>
    <section>
      <title>Character Basics</title>
      <text>The first part of describing your character is very simple.  Decide
what your character<squo/>s basic description is like.  Are they male or
female?  How tall?  What do they weigh?  Fill in age, sex, height,
weight, eyes color, and hair color/style on the upper right portion of
your character sheet.  Decide on your character<squo/>s name, and fill that
in too.  There is also a spot on the character sheet for your
name.  Now you can move on to the details of your character.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Attributes</title>
      <text><Apathy/> models characters by means of a core attribute system.
These attributes are numbers that describe the most basic
characteristics of any given character.  They are:</text>
      <figure>
        <table>
          <head>
            <cell width='.5in'>Abbr.</cell>
            <cell width='1in'>Name</cell>
            <cell width='2.5in'>Definition</cell>
          </head>
          <row>
            <cell>STR</cell>
            <cell>Strength</cell>
            <cell>raw physical strength,  muscle power</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>DEX</cell>
            <cell>Dexterity</cell>
            <cell>quickness, coordination, fine motor control, balance</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>BLD</cell>
            <cell>Build</cell>
            <cell>the toughness and durability of your body, stamina, <dquo>guts</dquo></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>INT</cell>
            <cell>Intelligence</cell>
            <cell>computational power of the mind, ability to grasp complex problems</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>KNO</cell>
            <cell>Knowledge</cell>
            <cell>experience and background knowledge, common sense, etc.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>WIL</cell>
            <cell>Willpower</cell>
            <cell>strength of the mind, ability to `stick it out<squo/> when things get tough</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>CHA</cell>
            <cell>Charisma</cell>
            <cell>friendliness, dealing with people, etc.</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <caption>Basic Terms</caption>
      </figure>
      <note>Throughout this document the attributes will usually be
  mentioned using the three-letter abbreviation instead of the full
  name.</note>
      <text>The first three attributes (STR, DEX, and BLD) are considered Physical
Attributes.  The second three attributes (INT, WIS, and WIL) are
Mental Attributes.  The seventh, CHA, is a little of both, but is
generally considered to be a Mental Attribute.</text>
      <text>Attributes are rated on a scale.  1 is the lowest possible attribute
score.  There is no top end on the scale, though an attribute of 20 is
the peak of human ability.  A human character can never have an
attribute higher than 20 without some supernatural effect (super
power, magic, cybernetics, etc).</text>
      <text>When creating a character, the GM allows you a certain number of
attribute points.  Attribute Points are used to purchase the attribute
values you want your character to have. A normal human has
  about 40 attribute points.  An above average human would have about
  105<ndash/>140 attribute points.  We recommend that 120 Attribute Points
  be assigned to starting characters<mdash/>after all, player characters
  are supposed to be heroic<mdash/>though the GM has the final word.</text>
      <text>The cost of an attribute is computed like a skill with Rank 1 (see the
skill section later on). However, the final value for the attribute
(for a Human) is increased by 8; that is, if you buy 5 levels of STR
(for 15 AP), then the final value of the STR is <math>5 + 8 = 13</math>.</text>
      <note>In most cases no player may have an attribute below 8.
  Attributes below 8 are considered handicapped and/or disabled, and
  such a character would probably not be adventuring!</note>
      <note>If the
  GM deems it OK, then you may reduce an attribute below 8, but you
  get NO benefits (you wouldn<squo/>t get points in another attribute for
  example).  Why would you do this?  Simple, it<squo/>s in your character
  concept.  Would a 6-year-old child have an 8 STR?  Not likely.</note>
      <text>When recording your attributes on the character sheet, record the number of
Attribute Points you spent on that attribute, this will help you when you wish
to increase them later.</text>
      <note>No attribute can be above a 20 for a natural human.  A 20 is
  considered the peak of human ability.  11 or so is average.  Below 8
  is considered handicapped for an adult human.  Note that certain
  things can increase attributes above 20, such as supernatural
  powers, magic, cybernetics, etc.</note>
      <text>Character Points (see next section) can be used to purchase Attribute Points
for increasing your attributes later on.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Sub-Attributes</title>
      <text>There are a number of <dquo>sub-attributes</dquo> that rely on your attributes to
determine their value.  The names, description, and method for determining
their value are listed below.</text>
      <figure>
        <table>
          <head>
            <cell width='1in'>Abbr.</cell>
            <cell width='3in'>Definition</cell>
            <cell width='1.5in'>Computation</cell>
          </head>
          <row>
            <cell>Lift</cell>
            <cell>This determines how much weight the character can lift in pounds, in a <dquo>good</dquo> situation, such as a weighted barbell or a trunk with handles.</cell>
            <cell>
              <math><frac><top>STR*STR*BLD</top><bot>10</bot></frac>+STR</math>
            </cell>
            <cell>Carry</cell>
            <cell>This is the amount of weight the character can carry about his/her person for a reasonable length of time.</cell>
            <cell>
              <math>
                <frac>
                  <top>Lift</top>
                  <bot>2</bot>
                </frac>
              </math>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Encumbrance
            </cell>
            <cell>This represents how much gear the character can wear before encountering adverse effects due to the weight and impaired mobility.</cell>
            <cell>
              <math>
                <frac>
                  <top>BLD+DEX+STR</top>
                  <bot>6</bot>
                </frac>
              </math>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Base Armor</cell>
            <cell>Determines how resilient the character is to <dquo>odd</dquo> damage, such as lightning and fire.</cell>
            <cell>
              <math>
                <frac>
                  <top>BLD+WIL</top>
                  <bot>6</bot>
                </frac>
              </math>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Movement</cell>
            <cell>How fast the character is in <dquo>squares per move-equivalent <action /> </dquo></cell>
            <cell>
              <math>
                <frac>
                  <top>2*STR+DEX</top>
                  <bot>15</bot>
                </frac>
              </math>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Perception</cell>
            <cell>How well the character can notice things around him.  Used just like an attribute check.</cell>
            <cell>
              <math>
                <frac>
                  <top>DEX+2*KNO+INT</top>
                  <bot>4</bot>
                </frac>
              </math>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Interaction</cell>
            <cell>The basic ability of a character to interact with other people.</cell>
            <cell>
              <math>
                <frac>
                  <top>CHA+KNO+INT</top>
                  <bot>3</bot>
                </frac>
              </math>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><hit-points /></cell>
            <cell>The amount of damage you can receive before dying.</cell>
            <cell>
              <math>BLD+WIL</math>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Magic Points</cell>
            <cell>The number of Magic Points you can draw on to cast magic spells or perform supernatural feats</cell>
            <cell>
              <math>(WIL+BLD)*10</math>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <caption>Sub-Attributes</caption>
      </figure>
      <text>Encumbrance, <base-armor />, HP, and MP will be discussed in more detail in later
sections.  Keep this in mind as you may need to update them later.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Character Points</title>
      <text>The remainder of the character creation process is done through the expenditure
of Character Points, otherwise known as CP.  Talk with your GM about how many
CP you should use to create your character with.  We have found that for a
group of 3-4 players 125 CP is about right.  Typically the more players, the
fewer CP characters should have.  This will keep the group from becoming too
powerful<mdash/>unless this is the GM<squo/>s intent.</text>
      <text>You will use your CP to <dquo>purchase</dquo> the remainder of your character.  The rest
of your character is broken into three categories where you will spend these
points:</text>
      <itemized-list>
        <item>
          <text>Mundane
        <description-list><item><description>Attributes</description><text> increasing starting attributes</text></item><item><description>Skills</description><text> normal skills, proficiency and knowledge of various topics</text></item><item><description>Combat Skills</description><text> techniques for fighting and defense.</text></item></description-list></text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <text>Arcane / Magic
        <description-list><item><description>Spellcasting</description><text/></item><item><description>Psionics</description><text/></item><item><description>Witchcraft or Ritual Magic</description><text/></item><item><description>Supernatural abilities (super powers)</description><text/></item></description-list></text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <text>Technology
        <description-list><item><description>Mecha and Robotics</description><text>Robotic bodies, limbs, powered armor, and robotic suits</text></item><item><description>Augmentations</description><text>Cybernetics, genetic mutations, and chemical augmentations</text></item><item><description>Weapons</description><text/></item><item><description>Armor</description><text/></item><item><description>Equipment</description><text> &amp; other material possessions</text></item></description-list></text>
        </item>
      </itemized-list>
      <note>IMPORTANT NOTE!<Apathy/> does not have <dquo>character classes</dquo> that are
common to many role-playing systems.  The <Apathy/> system allows the player
to decide every detail pertaining to his character, rather than being stuck
with a <dquo>default</dquo> set of abilities and skills.  It is up to the player to use
his CP to develop a well-rounded character.  Note that there are NO skills
that come <dquo>free.</dquo>  If your character is literate, then that skill needs
to be purchased.  Know how to drive a car?  Buy the skill.</note>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Increasing Attributes (optional)</title>
      <text>If your attributes aren<squo/>t quite where you desire, you will need to get more
Attribute Points so you can purchase a better attribute.  Each Attribute Point
costs 1 Character Point.  Once you purchase the number of Attribute Points you
want, just look at the table found in the Attributes section above to see
how many total Attribute Points you must spend to get that attribute.</text>
      <text>You must pay a number of Attribute Points equal to the difference between what
you want, and what you already have.  For example: if you currently have an 11
STR (6 Attribute Points) and wish to increase it to a 14 (21 Attribute Points)
that will cost you 15 Attribute Points (<math>9 - 4 = 5</math>).  Since Attribute Points
cost 1 Character Point each, going from an 11 in an attribute to a 14 will cost
15 CP.</text>
      <text>Remember to keep track of how many Attribute Points you have spent on your
attributes so you can easily increase them at a later date.</text>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Skills</title>
    <text>All characters have skills.  Skills represent what your character has learned
and what they know how to do.  Other than being useful in game, skills help to
distinguish your character from everyone else in the world.  Are you going to
play a diplomat?  You better have diplomacy, law, and similar skills.  A
warrior?  Better have that shield and/or weapon skills handy!</text>
    <text>Skills have a number of pieces of information associated with them.  They have
a Rank}, Associated Attribute, Description,
and Level.</text>
    <text>The rank determines how hard a skill is to learn.  Higher the rank, the more
time and CP it will take to get better at it.  Rank 1 skills are the simplest
and easiest to learn.  Skills that are more difficult have higher ranks.  Rank
can also be thought of as the <dquo>cost</dquo> or <dquo>price</dquo> of a skill.</text>
    <text>An associated attribute tells you what attribute is used in the skill roll.
This is the attribute that is used along with any particular skill.  This is
discussed in more detail below.</text>
    <text>The description will let you know the scope of <action plural="yes" /> that a skill
encompasses.  The things listed are not the only things available under that
skill, but just some of the more common applications of the skill.  If you have
a question, ask your GM about his take on a particular skill.</text>
    <text>Level is how good your particular character is at the skill. You will use CP
to purchase levels in a skill, which is discussed below.  If you don<squo/>t know a
skill at all, you have Level 0 in that skill<mdash/>meaning you don<squo/>t know anything
about it.  The more you know about the skill, the higher your level.
This is often abbreviated as <dquo>Lvl</dquo> (alt. <dquo>LVL</dquo>).  You must purchase your
skill levels with CP.  Below is a simple chart indicating what different levels
correspond to:</text>
    <figure>
      <table>
        <head>
          <cell align='center'>Level</cell>
          <cell align='left'>What it means</cell>
        </head>
        <row>
          <cell>0</cell>
          <cell>No knowledge of the skill.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>1</cell>
          <cell>Amateur.  You know something about it.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>2</cell>
          <cell>Had some training or experience</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>3</cell>
          <cell>Beginning professional or serious hobbyist</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>4</cell>
          <cell>Professional</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>5</cell>
          <cell>Experienced professional</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>6</cell>
          <cell>Exceptionally good.  Among the best in the country.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>7</cell>
          <cell>Among the best in the world.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>8+</cell>
          <cell>Among the best ever</cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      <caption>Skill Level and Descriptive Equivalents</caption>
    </figure>
    <text>Like most of character creation, skills are purchased using CP.  The higher
the rank, the more expensive it will be.  The higher the level you want in the
skill, the more expensive it will be.</text>
    <text>For those that are mathematically inclined, here is the formula for determining
CP of a particular skill level and rank:</text>
    <math><sum><from>i=1</from><to>Desired Level = n</to><of><parenthesis>
            Rank * i
        </parenthesis></of></sum>
=
<frac><top>
        n<sup>2</sup>+n
    </top><bot>
        2
    </bot></frac></math>
    <text>For the rest of us, use this nifty table, and multiply the value listed by the
rank.</text>
    <figure>
      <table>
        <head>
          <cell align='left' border-right='1px black'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
          <cell align='center'/>
        </head>
        <row>
          <cell>Desired Level</cell>
          <cell>1</cell>
          <cell>2</cell>
          <cell>3</cell>
          <cell>4</cell>
          <cell>5</cell>
          <cell>6</cell>
          <cell>7</cell>
          <cell>8</cell>
          <cell>9</cell>
          <cell>10</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>CP Cost for Rank 1</cell>
          <cell>1</cell>
          <cell>3</cell>
          <cell>6</cell>
          <cell>10</cell>
          <cell>15</cell>
          <cell>21</cell>
          <cell>28</cell>
          <cell>36</cell>
          <cell>45</cell>
          <cell>55</cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      <caption>CP cost of Desired Level, precomputed</caption>
    </figure>
    <text>See the trend?</text>
    <text>If not, here<squo/>s yet another way to look at purchasing skills.</text>
    <text>To get level 1 of a skill, you must spend the Rank in CP.  To get to the next
level, add the rank of the skill to the amount of CP you spent the last time you
increase the skill (and just that last increase, not the total amount you<squo/>ve spent
on the skill) and that is the amount that you need to spend.</text>
    <example>
      <title>Computing Skill Cost</title>
      <text>I want to purchase the shield skill
(rank 2).  To get Lvl 1
I would need to spend
2 CP.  Now, if I want to go from Lvl 1, to Lvl 2, I would add the rank (2) to
the amount I spent on the last level increase (2 CP), to get the new cost, in
this case I would need to spend a total of 4 CP (rank of 2 + 2 CP from last
purchase).  So now the total amount I have spent on this skill is 6 CP.  Lets say
I<squo/>m not happy with my Lvl 2 shield skill, and wish to upgrade it to level 3.
I would again take the rank (2) and add it to the amount I spent on the last
increase (4) to get the number of CP I must spend to upgrade the skill.  In this
case, I must spend an additional 6 CP.  Therefore, to get a level 3 shield skill
(or any skill or rank 2), I must spend a total of 12 CP.</text>
    </example>
    <text>If you take a look at the little chart above, you will see that at the desired
skill level (3) the CP cost is a 6, which I then multiply by the rank (2) to get
12 CP, the same thing I got when I did it out by hand.</text>
    <text>Note that the chart will only tell you how many total Character Points.  To get
the number of CP needed to increase to the next level, just subtract the upper
number from the lower one.  A more complete version of the above table can be
found at the end of this manual.</text>
    <text>Once you are in game and earning experience, you can increase the level of a
skill you currently have at least one level in by paying the appropriate CP
cost.  If you wish to learn the first level of a skill you don<squo/>t have yet, it
takes a number of weeks of intense studying equal to the rank of the skill.</text>
    <section>
      <title>Skill Specialization (optional)</title>
      <section>
        <title>Specialization in most Skills</title>
        <text>It is possible to specialize in many skills.  When specialized, a character
knows more about a certain aspect of the skill than other parts of the skill.
In game terms, you are +1 LVL when performing a check in the area of your
specialization, but are -4 to your roll when you are performing a check outside
of your specialization.  Specializing does NOT cost any extra CP.</text>
        <example>
          <title>History<rightarrow/>Spanish</title>
          <text>Ralf Gr<umlaut>o</umlaut>osse-Kunstleve is a historian.
Specifically, he is knowledgeable
about Spanish history. He has a LVL 3 History skill with a specialization in
Spanish History.  This means that if Juan had to make a skill check related to
Spanish history, he would roll 4 dice.  (3 from his LVL, +1 from the specialty.)
However, if he had to make a History roll about another kind of history, he
would only roll 3 dice, and be at a -4 to his roll.</text>
        </example>
        <text>Note that you can choose to buy a particular skill more than once with different
specialties, if you feel like it.  When this happens the roll for <dquo>outside
of specialty</dquo> skill checks is the highest of the skill levels -4 +1 for each
skill beyond the first.</text>
        <example>
          <title>Chemistry<rightarrow/>WMD</title>
          <text>Dr. Klo<overbrace>tz</overbrace>enstein is a scientist.
He has LVL 3 Chemistry with a specialty in
Chemical weapons and poisons.  As well, he has LVL 4 Chemistry with a
specialization in the chemistry of explosives.  Dr. Klotzenstein<squo/>s rolls are
as follows:

    <itemized-list><item><text>For Weapons/poisons: 4 dice</text></item><item><text>For Explosives: 5 dice</text></item><item><text>For Non-specialty rolls, 5 dice -3.</text></item></itemized-list></text>
        </example>
        <text>It is possible to specialize in most skills.  Talk to your GM about specializing
to see which skills you think are appropriate and which ones are not.</text>
        <text>Specializing in skills is purely optional.</text>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Specialization applied to Weapon skills</title>
        <text>It is also possible to specialize in weapon skills.  If a character has a
specialized weapon skill that means that he is especially proficient with a
very specific type of weapon.  When wielding a weapon that matches a character<squo/>s
specialty, that character receives +1 LVL to the skill.  This bonus applies to
attack (strike) rolls, and defensive rolls (parry), if applicable.  When using
a weapon that is outside the character<squo/>s specialty, the character is at -1 LVL.
Note that Weapon skill specialization does NOT affect damage rolls.</text>
        <text>Specializing in a weapons skill costs 3 CP in addition to the normal cost of the
skill. Specializing can be applied to all weapon proficiency type skills and
the shield skill.</text>
        <example>
          <title>Axes<rightarrow/>Nordic War Axe</title>
          <text>Bj<struck>o</struck>rgen
is a warrior with a liking for the Nordic War Axe.
He has the skill
<dquo>Archaic Weapons: Axes</dquo> at level 3.  As well, he is specialized in the Nordic
War Axe.  The total skill cost is 9 CP.  That is 6 CP for Level 3 in a Rank 1
skill, Plus 3 CP from the specialization.  When welding a Genuine Nordic War
Axe<trademark/> in combat, Gunnar has 4 dice.  However, when using any other
kind of axe Gunnar only has 2 dice.</text>
        </example>
        <text>Note that some unusual or esoteric weapons require specialization.
This is because those weapons are different enough from common weapons that
they require special knowledge and experience in order to use them properly.</text>
        <text>Most characters that specialize in weapons are very particular about their
weapons.  For the character it is almost an obsessive-compulsive issue to
wield a particular weapon.  Generally the weapon must be very specific in order
to satisfy the specialty.  In medieval campaigns, a weapon specialty might
require a sword forged by a particular smith, or arrows made from a certain
type of wood.  In a modern campaign, a weapon specialty might entail a particular
make and model of rifle.</text>
        <text>Specializing in skills is purely optional.</text>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Rules (Rolls)</title>
    <text>What would an RPG be without rules?  <Apathy/> has a set of rules that allow
for just about any occurrence that an imaginative GM can put the players through.</text>
    <text>Lets start with the basics (some of this will be review):</text>
    <text>In <Apathy/>, there are three different types of die rolls.  Every time
you roll a die when playing <Apathy/>, you will use one of these sets of rules.</text>
    <section>
      <title>Attribute Checks</title>
      <text>Attribute checks are required anytime the GM wants to see if you did something
solely based on an attribute.  They are used whenever a player wants their 
character to do something tricky.  Attribute checks are purely based on a 
character<squo/>s core attributes.  They are completely separate from skills.  If a 
player needs to do something based on a particular skill, then see the skill 
roll section below.</text>
      <example>
        <title>Catch a Pack</title>
        <text>Barnacleez is trying
to catch a pack that was thrown at him.  The GM 
requires him to make a DEX check to see if he successfully caught the pack.</text>
      </example>
      <example>
        <title>Swim a Long Distance</title>
        <text>Thomas is trying to
swim a long distance while carrying a heavy load.
He has to roll a BLD check to see if he has enough stamina to make the swim.</text>
      </example>
      <example>
        <title>Decipher Symbols</title>
        <text>Wendy is trying to
decipher the meaning of some strange symbols written 
on a wall.  Since she has no applicable skills, the GM determines that she needs 
to make an INT check in order to figure out what they mean.</text>
        <text>Attribute checks are always rolled the same.  Roll ONE twenty-sided die, add 
the attribute to the die, and add any bonuses or negatives.  If the total (die 
roll + attribute + bonuses + negatives) is 25 or higher, then the check 
succeeded.  If you roll a 1, you fail automatically, no matter what your bonuses 
or attributes are.  If you roll a 20, you succeed automatically, no matter what 
the negatives might be.  For an attribute check, you always roll just one 
20-sided die.</text>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Contest of Attributes</title>
      <text>Contests of Attributes occur whenever two characters are competing at 
something that is largely dependent on an attribute and nothing else.  Arm 
wrestling is a contest of strength.   Racing to complete a puzzle is a contest 
of intelligence.  A trivia game would be a contest of wisdom, etc.</text>
      <text>A contest of attributes occurs only when there are multiple competitors 
(generally two) and only when there is no particular skill involved.  For 
example, arm wrestling is a contest of strength but a game of 1-on-1 basketball 
is generally not, because basketball is a complex game.</text>
      <text>When a contest of attributes occurs, all competitors roll 1D4 and add the
result to their attribute.  The highest score wins, and like scores tie.
The GM may wish to impose negatives and/or bonuses depending on the exact
circumstances of the contest.</text>
      <example>
        <title>Dougles vs. Enemy Soldier</title>
        <text>Douglas (STR 13) is fighting with an 
enemy solider (STR 12) over the possession of a single rifle.  The GM 
declares that a contest of strength will resolve who manages to gain 
possession of the rifle.  The GM rolls for the solider (a three) and 
Douglas rolls a 1.  The enemy soldier has a total of 15, and Douglas 
has 14.  Therefore, the enemy soldier wrestles the rifle out of
Douglas<squo/>s hands.</text>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Skill Rolls</title>
      <text>Skill rollsare used whenever a player wants to use one of his
character<squo/>s skills.  They are also used whenever two characters are competing
at something (Contest of skills) related to a skill. Skill rolls are also used
<dquo>to strike</dquo> or <dquo>to defend</dquo> in combat.</text>
      <text>To determine if you are successful in performing a skill, roll a number of D20s 
equal to the Level you have purchased the skill in.  To each die, add 
your 
current attribute referenced by the associated attribute value of the skill.  
Each time a die with this value added to it reaches 25 or above, this is called 
a success.  If you have at least one success, you successfully performed the 
skill.  Rolling a <dquo>20</dquo> on a die will give you +1 successes to however many 
you rolled normally.  Note that this makes it possible to have more successes 
than you have levels in a given skill.  Likewise, a roll of <dquo>1</dquo> is -1 
successes to your total.  If you have negative successes (caused by rolling 
more 1s than successes) then you have a critical failure!  In the case of a 
critical failure the GM will determine what (negative) outcome happens!</text>
      <figure>
        <table>
          <head>
            <cell align='center'>Roll</cell>
            <cell align='left'>Sample Outcome</cell>
          </head>
          <row>
            <cell>Strike (sword)</cell>
            <cell>Sword breaks or is dropped</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Strike (gun)</cell>
            <cell>gun jams or misfires</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Parry</cell>
            <cell>you drop your weapon and are struck by the incoming blow</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Diplomacy</cell>
            <cell>you make a faux pas that offends the parties involved</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Deception</cell>
            <cell>you are caught <dquo>red handed</dquo> in a blatant lie</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Medicine</cell>
            <cell>you make an outright mistake, harming the patient.</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <caption>Sample outcome for Skill Rolls</caption>
      </figure>
      <text>The GM will give penalties and/or bonuses to your skill roll based on the 
difficulty of the <action /> you are performing and what circumstances may be 
surrounding it.  When such a negative or bonus is given, this is subtracted 
from the associated attribute value, not the number of dice rolled for a skill.</text>
      <text>Basically stated, skill rolls work like this:  Roll 1D20 for each level you 
have in the skill.  To each die, add your associated attribute and any 
negatives 
or bonuses the GM gives you.  If the total on each die is 25 or greater that is 
a success.  If the die rolls a 20, regardless of bonuses, attributes, etc. you 
get +1 successes.  If a die rolls a 1, regardless of bonuses, etc. you get -1 
success.</text>
      <text>Note that the Maximum you can ever add to your die roll<mdash/>no 
matter how high 
your attribute or bonuses to succeed might be<mdash/>is 20.</text>
      <text>Also, if you are doing something simple with respect to your skill level 
then you don<squo/>t have to roll dice at all.  It<squo/>s assumed that you succeed 
examples.</text>
      <example>
        <title>Lookup Internt Address</title>
        <text>Amy has the Computer
Use skill at level 3.  She wants to look up an 
Internet address on the computer that she thinks might give the players some 
needed information.  Since this is a simple task and she has a significant 
level in the associated skill (Computer Use), then the GM rules that she does 
so automatically, with no roll needed.</text>
      </example>
      <example>
        <title>Investigate Mysterious Person</title>
        <text>Amy is still on the Internet.
Now she is attempting to dig up some 
information about a mysterious person.  The GM determines that Amy needs to 
use her Level 2 Investigation skill.  Amy has a 13 WIS, the associated 
attribute 
for Investigation.  The GM tells her that this is a normal difficulty skill, 
and there is no bonus or negative.  So Amy rolls 2D20 for the skill and rolls a 
6 and a 13.  After adding her WIS to each roll, she has a 19 and a 26.
Only the 
26 is a success since it is 25 or above.  Since she has at least one success,
Amy 
is able to find the information she was looking for.</text>
      </example>
      <example>
        <title>Fix a Beater</title>
        <text>Chris is trying
to fix an old car so he and his fellow characters can use 
it.  The GM determines that this falls under the Mechanic: General skill.  Chris
has a level 2 in that skill.  Furthermore, the GM determines that since the car 
is in really bad shape, that Chris has a -3 to his roll.  Chris has a 12 DEX.  
Chris rolls his dice and gets a 1 and a 16. (Chris is rolling two dice because 
he has a level 2 skill)  Adding his DEX to those rolls, Chris now has a 13 and 
a 28.  The 13 isn<squo/>t 25 or above, so it fails, but the 28 succeeds.  So far, 
Chris has 1 success.  However, the <dquo>1</dquo> Chris rolled is -1 success.  So, this 
gives Chris a total of 0 successes<mdash/>meaning the car didn<squo/>t get fixed.</text>
      </example>
      <example>
        <title>Shoot a Large Robot</title>
        <text>Billy is
a cybernetic gunfighter with a 22 DEX.  He is trying to shoot an 
enemy robot.  The GM determines that Billy gets a bonus of +3 to shoot the 
robot because it<squo/>s so large.  Normally, Billy would roll his dice and add +25 
to each one:  +22 from his DEX and +3 from the <size /> bonus.  However, this gets 
capped at +20.  Thus, Billy only gets to add +20 to each of his dice.</text>
      </example>
      <example>
        <title>Called Shot to Arm</title>
        <text>Billy is still fighting the same
giant robot.  This time, he<squo/>s trying to 
make a called shot and shoot the robot in the arm.  The GM determines that 
Billy gets a +3 bonus due to the robot<squo/>s <size />, but also a -4 to strike because 
of the called shot to the arm.  Thus, Billy adds up his bonuses:  +22 from DEX 
+3 from <size /> and -4 for the called shot.  This adds up to +21, but the bonus 
is capped at +20.  Again, Billy adds +20 to his dice.  Notice that the <dquo>+20 
cap</dquo> is applied AFTER all the bonuses and negatives are added up.</text>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Contest of Skills</title>
      <text>A contest of skills occurs when two people are trying 
to defeat each other in some manner with their skills.
If two characters were competing to see who could sing better, the 
character with the largest number of successes of the singing skill 
would win.  The most common example of this is combat.  In order to 
be successful in a combat situation<mdash/>such as attempting to hit an 
opponent with a sword while he is blocking with a shield, the 
initiator (or attacker) of the <action /> must make more successes 
than the defender.</text>
      <example>
        <title>Tom and the Shopkeeper in a Contest</title>
        <text>Tom is attempting 
to purchase an expensive suit of armor, and doesn<squo/>t want to pay 
full price.  So he is attempting to bring the price down by using 
the Bargaining skill.  The shopkeeper also has the Bargaining skill, 
so a contest of skills ensues.  Tom has a skill level of 3, and a 
WIS of 13 (the associated attribute for Bargaining); the shopkeeper 
has a level 4 Bargaining (he<squo/>s been at it longer than Tom has), 
and a WIS of 10.

Tom rolls 3 dice and gets a <dquo>14</dquo>, <dquo>20</dquo>, and a <dquo>3</dquo>.  Tom now 
adds his wisdom (13) to each of these.  The GM didn<squo/>t give any 
negatives or bonuses, so that is all that gets added.  After adding, 
the totals are 27, 33, and 16.  Two of these are 25 or higher, so Tom 
has two successes so far.  Note that Tom rolled one 20<mdash/>which gives him 
an additional success.  Tom has a total of three successes.
 
The shopkeeper rolls four dice (remember, he has a level 4 Bargaining), 
and gets a <dquo>1</dquo>, <dquo>12</dquo>, <dquo>15<squo/></dquo>, and an <dquo>18</dquo>.  After adding the 
shopkeeper<squo/>s WIS of 10, we get the following rolls: <dquo>11</dquo>, <dquo>22</dquo>, 
<dquo>25</dquo>, and <dquo>28</dquo>.  The 25 and 28 are both successes, but the 
<dquo>1</dquo> is a -1 success, so the shopkeeper has 1 total success.

Tom has 3 successes, and the shopkeeper has 1.  Since Tom initiated 
the bargaining, and has more successes than the <dquo>defender</dquo>, he is 
successful in his attempt to reduce the price of the armor.  How
much is determined by the GM, but it should be commensurate with 
the number of successes that Tom beat the shopkeeper by.</text>
      </example>
      <text>The winner of a contest of skills is whomever rolled the highest 
number of successes.  The margin of success is based on the difference 
between the two rolls.  For example, if the <dquo>winner</dquo> had only 1 more 
success than the <dquo>loser</dquo>, then the contest was close.  However, if 
the <dquo>winner</dquo> had three more successes than the loser, then it was a 
decisive victory!</text>
      <text>Ties are left up to the GM to resolve.  The suggested protocol is as follows:</text>
      <text>If the tie occurred on a contest that entails a single past event or 
is something that is <dquo>judged</dquo> by outsiders, then the winner is the 
character with the higher associated attribute.  (Example: who can 
paint a better picture, etc.)</text>
      <text>If the contest entails an ongoing event (such as the haggling over a 
suit of armor detailed above) then it is assumed that the competitors 
<dquo>keep at it</dquo> and a second roll is in order.</text>
      <text>The rules for combat are slightly more complicated; see below.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Skill Rolls and Related Skills</title>
      <text>If a character needs to make a skill roll and that character knows 
other skills that are somehow related to (or are similar to) the 
skill to be rolled, that character is generally entitled to a bonus 
to his or her roll.  The exact terms of the bonus, including what 
skills qualify as <dquo>related</dquo>, is determined by the GM on a case-by-case 
basis.  The general rule is that each level of a related skill conveys 
a +1 to the roll.  The maximum possible bonus from related skills is 
+5, regardless of the circumstances.</text>
      <example>
        <title>Paul repairing a device</title>
        <text>Paul is attempting to repair an 
electronic device.  The GM asks Paul to roll his Electronics skill, 
which Paul has at lvl 4.  Paul mentions that he also knows the 
skills Electrical Engineering: 2, Electrician: 3, Mechanic: General: 3, 
and Communications/Telco: 3.  The GM determines that since this device 
is purely electronic, Paul<squo/>s Mechanic skill is of no use.  As well, the 
GM decides that since this device is unrelated to communications, 
Paul<squo/>s Communications skill does not apply either.  However, the GM 
decides that Paul<squo/>s Electrical Engineering and Electrician skills 
are relevant.  The GM assigns Paul a bonus of +5 to his roll from his 
levels in those related skills.</text>
      </example>
      <text>Related Skill bonuses NEVER apply to 
combat skills or any skill used in a combat situation.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>All Other Rolls</title>
      <text>This type of die rolling is used for just about everything else in 
the game: rolling damage from combat, the duration of magical spells, 
or the number of monsters appearing in a group.</text>
      <text>Rolling dice is represented in the XDY+Z format; for example 
3D4+1.  This means that you roll three individual 4-sided dice, 
and add 1 to each die.</text>
      <text>If any die roll with its bonus added in equals or betters the maximum 
value on a die, then you get a rollover.  When a 
rollover happens, re-roll that die, without any bonus, and add its 
value to the total.  If the roll again has the highest value on the 
die, then another rollover happens.  This keeps going until the 
highest value on the die is not rolled.  Remember, after 
the first roll, the bonus is not applied; it<squo/>s just the 
raw die roll.</text>
      <text>This may sound confusing, so we<squo/>ll work with the example from above.
Let<squo/>s say you have to roll 3D4+1.  You get some four-sided dice and 
roll three of them.  Suppose the results are: 1, 3, and a 4.  After 
adding the +1 (from the die bonus), we now have: 2, 4, and 5.  We add 
all the totals up and get 11.  Now we have to deal with the rollovers.
Because the highest value on a four-sided dice is a 4, we have two 
rollovers: the 4 and 5.  So we roll each of these again, 
without the original bonus, and get a 2 and 4.  We add 
these to the total yielding 17.  But wait, we have yet another 
rollover (the 4).  So we roll that die again, and get a 3.  We now 
have a total of a 20 for our 3D4+1 die roll.</text>
      <text>The same rules apply for any die.  Lets say you are rolling six-sided 
dice.  If any die (after bonuses) has a 6 or higher, then you get a 
rollover.  On an eight-sided die?  You guessed it; a roll of 8 or higher 
will yield a rollover.</text>
      <text>If you have bonuses or negatives to a roll, add them up first, 
then perform the final roll.</text>
      <text>Note that if there is a minus to the die roll once all the 
bonuses/penalties are added up, then no rollover is possible.  An 
example is 1D4-1.  Even if you roll a 4 on the die it will be reduced 
to a 3, which does not yield a rollover.  No die (even 
after negatives) can give a value less than 1.  So, if you 
have a 1D6-4, and roll a 2 (which would theoretically total -2), 
then the actual total would be 1.</text>
      <text>Along with what is given above, die rolls might have a 
raw bonus.  This is represented by a bonus in brackets 
such as this: 3D4+1 [+4] (alt. 4+3D4+1).  Raw Bonuses are 
added to the resultant total of a die roll, NOT to each die; thus 
they do not affect rollovers at all.  This bonus is added in after 
all the rollovers are done with.  Consider the prior example of 
3D4+1 but with the [+4] added.  That would be written 3D4+1 [+4].
The total using the above numbers would be 24. </text>
      <text>Unless otherwise stated, all non-skill die rolls use this system.</text>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Combat Sequence &amp; Initiative</title>
    <text>Combat is based on a system of <italics>Rounds</italics>, <italics>Turns</italics>, and
<italics>Actions</italics>.  A <dquo>round</dquo> lasts about five seconds.  It is the
length of time in which all combatants have done something.  Each
round is broken down into <action plural="yes" />.  An <action /> lasts about 1 second.
Each combatant gets one or more <action plural="yes" /> during each round.  When all
combatants have used up their <action plural="yes" />, the current round is over and a
new one starts.</text>
    <text>During your turn, you determine what you wish to do with your
available <action plural="yes" />.  Almost everything that you do of significance
during your turn consumes an <action />   Simple examples of what can be
done in an <action /> are shooting a gun, swing a sword, moving, or using
a mystical ability.  Keep in mind that a lot of <dquo>boring</dquo> combat
stuff also takes up <action plural="yes" />: reloading your weapon, moving around,
ducking behind cover, or taking an item out of your pack.  Some things
that you will want to do will consume multiple <action plural="yes" /> per turn.</text>
    <image src='/MartialArts/Cpg359-49v.jpg'/>
    <text>All characters, by default, have three <action plural="yes" /> per round.
Certain skills or in-game effects might change this.  When combat is
going to start, all players need to figure out how many <action plural="yes" /> they
get.  (typically, this will be 3 each).</text>
    <text>At the beginning of combat, all characters must roll initiative.  This
determines who attacks first in the turn.  When combat starts,
participants must roll a 1D20 for their initiative. If any characters
have more than 3 <action plural="yes" /> per turn (due to a skill or magical effect or
somesuch), then those characters must roll initiative twice.</text>
    <text>Various bonuses or penalties apply to initiative rolls.  Certain
skills and magical effects can alter initiative.  As well, the GM may
apply initiative bonuses or penalties depending on game situations,
such as surprise attacks or ambushes.</text>
    <note>Most characters will have 3 <action plural="yes" /> per turn.  All 
three <action plural="yes" /> are 
taken at the same time, on that character<squo/>s initiative.</note>
    <example>
      <title>Tom<squo/>s Turn in Combat</title>
      <text>Tom is in combat.
Tom has three <action plural="yes" /> and he rolled an 11 as his 
initiative.  When it<squo/>s Tom<squo/>s turn in combat (11), he takes all three <action plural="yes" /> at 
that time.</text>
    </example>
    <text>The character that has the highest initiative goes first, and then the 
character with the next highest initiative takes their turn, and so 
forth down the line until all combatants have taken a turn.</text>
    <text>Once all turns are over, the current round of combat is over.  It then 
restarts with everyone<squo/>s initiative being the same as it was in the previous 
round.  This progression continues until combat is over.  If the combatants 
change significantly during combat<mdash/>for example, if new characters show up on 
the scene<mdash/>the GM might want to make everyone re-roll their initiative.  If 
something happens during combat that changes how many <action plural="yes" /> the combatants 
have, the GM should ask that initiative be re-rolled.</text>
    <text>Some things that you might want to do will take up multiple <action plural="yes" />.  A common 
example of this is spell casting, where many spells take several <action plural="yes" /> to 
cast.  If you do this, you may need to drag this type of <action /> across multiple  <action plural="yes" /> or even multiple turns.  For example, let<squo/>s say that you want to cast 
a spell that takes 3 <action plural="yes" />.  You can use your first <action /> to start casting, 
and then use your second and third <action plural="yes" /> to finish casting the spell.   At 
any time you may cancel (stop casting) the spell or ability with no penalty.  
When an ability or activity requires multiple <action plural="yes" />, it always takes place 
on the final <action /> that completes that activity.  Also, it is possible to be 
disturbed or disrupted if you are attacked while performing a multiple-action 
activity.  The GM should take note of this and might impose skill checks or 
other chances of failure if you get knocked around too much.</text>
    <note>Note that everything you may wish to do in combat 
requires one or more <action plural="yes" />.  
This includes moving around, drawing a weapon, 
using items, etc.  Undoubtedly, 
many of your <action plural="yes" /> will be used for things 
other than attacking.</note>
    <text>When in combat, some characters may want to delay their <action /> until 
later.  A character can always choose to <dquo>act later</dquo> in combat.  
When doing so the player states what new initiative number he 
wishes to act on.  The new initiative must be lower than his 
current initiative number.  Once a character<squo/>s initiative is 
delayed it remains delayed (though it could be delayed even further).  
That characters initiative remains at the new, lower, number for the 
remainder of combat, unless the GM asks all players to re-roll 
initiative.  <action plural="yes" /> cannot be split between different initiative 
numbers.  So, a character must either take all his <action plural="yes" /> at his 
normal initiative, or he must delay all his <action plural="yes" /> to a later initiative.</text>
    <example>
      <title>Tom<squo/>s initiative</title>
      <text>Tom<squo/>s initiative roll is an 18.  He 
and his fellow players were cornered by ogres for whom the GM has 
secretly rolled initiative.  Tom has the highest initiative roll, so 
he goes first.  Tom isn<squo/>t exactly sure what to do, so he delays 
his initiative until <dquo>10</dquo>.  The GM then resumes combat as normal, 
with the next highest initiative going first.  Tom has initiative 10 
for the remainder of combat.</text>
    </example>
    <text>Some game effects last a certain number of turns, or have a certain 
effect each turn.  These effects are counted and take place on 
the affected character<squo/>s turn.  They only are counted and occur 
if the character begins that turn with the effect in place.  
These effects occur at the beginning of that character<squo/>s turn 
in a given round.  These effects are automatic and do not consume 
any time from the character.  Resolve all effects before that 
character takes any <action plural="yes" />. </text>
    <example>
      <title>Lucy<squo/>s turn in combat</title>
      <text>It is Lucy<squo/>s turn in 
combat and she casts Regeneration on herself.  The effect of the 
spell is that each turn she gains 1D4+1 <hit-points />.  Now the spell 
has taken effect, but she does not gain any HP yet, nor does this 
turn count against the duration of the spell.  Now all other 
combatants take their turns.  When it is again Lucy<squo/>s 
turn (next round) she gains her 1D4+1 HP, just before 
her first <action />   This is also considered one turn out of the 
spell<squo/>s duration.</text>
    </example>
    <text>It is possible to <dquo>hold an <action />  </dquo> for later.  Holding an  <action /> means that the character is maintaining his current 
initiative number, but is saving an <action />  for a specific 
situation.  A character may only hold one <action />  at a time.  
Furthermore, you must declare what your held <action />  will be, and 
under what circumstances.  Held <action plural="yes" /> are resolved as soon 
as their conditions are met.  Held <action plural="yes" /> <dquo>expire</dquo> if their 
declared conditions never occur at the beginning of your next turn.</text>
    <example>
      <title>Tom holds an <action /> </title>
      <text>Tom<squo/>s initiative is 10.  During 
his turn he spends one <action /> to move behind some cover and another 
to ready his longbow.  Tom declares that he is going to hold his 
final <action />   <dquo>I am going to cover the hallway with my 
bow.  If I see a goblin come out of the hallway, I<squo/>m going to 
shoot at it</dquo>.  If a goblin does indeed come out of the hallway (and 
Tom can see this), then Tom may immediately take his held <action /> to 
fire an arrow at it.  However, if no goblin comes down the 
hallway before Tom<squo/>s next turn, then the held <action />  is wasted.</text>
    </example>
    <text>Notes for held <action plural="yes" />:</text>
    <numbered-list>
      <item>
        <text> You may only hold one <action /> at a time</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text> You must state specifically what the conditions for 
your held <action /> must be, and what your <action /> will be once 
those conditions are met.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text> Your held <action /> can be any activity you could do 
in one <action /> (including attacking, moving, using a magical ability, etc.)</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text> Held <action plural="yes" /> are lost if their triggering conditions never occur.</text>
      </item>
    </numbered-list>
    <section>
      <title>Weapons &amp; Equipment</title>
      <text>Most characters will carry equipment in combat.  This usually includes
weapons and armor.  There are no <dquo>class</dquo> restrictions for weapons or
armor.  Any character can wear any armor and wield any weapon,
provided that the character has the appropriate attributes and skills.</text>
      <text>Weapons have a minimum strength requirement (MSR).  The MSR
indicates what strength is required of the character to properly wield
a given weapon.  If the character<squo/>s strength is <italics>less</italics> than the
MSR, then the character has -1 to strike and [-1] damage for each
point of strength difference.</text>
      <text>The raw damage bonus (RDB) is calculated by subtracting 8 from
the wielder<squo/>s Str. The RDB is added as raw damage to
total of the weapon<squo/>s damage. However, all weapons have a
maximum strength bonus (MSB); if the RDB is greater than the
MSB, then the MSB is used as the RDB instead.</text>
      <example>
        <title>MSR for Bosk</title>
        <text>Bosk has a STR of 17 and is brandishing a
  Hercules Club (3D6C, MSR: 12, MSB: 13).  Because Bosk<squo/>s
  Str is higher than the minimum strength requirement of
  the Hercules Club (12), he is entitled to a damage bonus.  Subtract
  8 from Bosk<squo/>s Str score to calculate his bonus: <math>17 - 8 =
  9</math>. So this means that Bosk deals 9+3D6 C damage.</text>
      </example>
      <example>
        <title>Bosk with Knife</title>
        <text>Suppose Bosk pulls out a long knife
  (1D6+1 S, MSR: 8; MSB: 4).  Bosk<squo/>s Str is significantly
  higher than the minimum required for the weapon.  Calculating his
  theoretical bonus, we can write: 17 - 8 = 9.  At first glance, it
  appears that Bosk is entitled to a [+9] bonus.  However, the maximum
  strength bonus for the long knife is 4. Therefore, Bosk<squo/>s damage
  roll would be 4+1D6+1.</text>
      </example>
      <text>Bows never grant a damage bonus to characters with higher than 
required STR.  However, it is possible to purchase stiffer (stronger) 
bows that can take advantage of a character<squo/>s higher STR score.  
High-draw bows cost 20% more for every 1 STR point added to the 
MSR.  For each point, add [+1] damage.  This can be stacked.  So, a 
+1 bow costs 20% extra, a +2 bow costs 40% extra, etc.  Note 
that the maximum STR requirement that can be added to a bow of a 
given type is equal to half of its original MSR.  Note that the 
damage and strike penalty for having a lower-than-required STR does 
apply to bows.  Modern compound bows are adjustable and can be set 
to a higher than normal strength value without incurring additional cost.</text>
      <image src='/Magic/Lion-faced_deity.jpg'/>
      <text>Characters will have two hands that they may use to wield weapons.
All weapons are either one-hand or two-handed.  Two-handed weapons, of
course, require both hands to properly wield.  One-handed weapons
require only one hand.  Therefore a player could wield one single-hand
weapon, one two-handed weapon, two single-hand weapons, or one
single-hand weapon and a shield or other item. However, when wielding
two weapons the character can have penalties. Also, wielding two
weapons does not grant the ability to the character to strike with
both weapons in one <action />  In general, wielding two weapons gives the
user -3 and -6 to strike with the primary and off -hand
(respectively), and requires an additional <action />  These penalties can
be mitigated with skills from Martial Arts.</text>
      <text>Characters that use magic, aside from Martial Magic, must have at 
least one hand free when casting spells. 
Characters that use Faith magic must have a holy symbol in their 
grasp when casting magic; this requires a free hand to hold.  
Spellcasters are free to use two-handed weapons so long as they 
aren<squo/>t wielding the weapon at the same time as they are 
casting spells.  (Spellcasters can put away a weapon, cast magic 
freely, and then draw their weapon again, though this takes time)</text>
      <text>All firearms are assumed to be 2-handed by default.  However, pistols 
and submachine guns may be fired with one hand.  (See rules for using 
2-handed weapons with one hand below).  Larger firearms including 
rifles, shotguns, and heavy weapons (rocket launchers, etc.) must always 
be used 2-handed.  It always requires two hands to reload a firearm, 
no matter what kind it is.</text>
      <text>Bows are always two-handed weapons.  Hand (small) crossbows can be 
aimed and fired with one hand.  However, cocking and re-loading 
a crossbow always requires two hands.  Larger crossbows always 
require two hands to fire as well as load.  Siege weapons, cannons, 
heavy weapons, etc, always require both hands to be free in order 
to load, aim, and fire.</text>
      <text>It is possible to use two hands to fight with a one-handed weapon.  
In this case, the wielder has -1 to strike and effectively adds +3 
to his strength.</text>
      <text>It is possible to use some two-handed weapons with one hand.  To do 
so, add 4 to the minimum strength requirement of the weapon.  Note 
that many two-handed weapons always require two hands, period.  These 
are large firearms (rifles, shotguns), staves, pole arms, chains, and bows.  </text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Dual-wielding Weapons or Weapon &amp; Shield</title>
      <text>As noted above, it is possible for characters to wield two weapons in
combat, or a weapon and a shield. A character cannot attack
with both weapons during the same <action /> unless he takes the
Multi-weapon style skill in Martial Arts.  A character
using a weapon and a shield may not attack with his weapon and
shield bash in the same <action />  for the same reason.  When attacking
with both weapons the character makes two separate attack rolls, one
for each weapon; each attack is resolved separately. This takes two
separate <action plural="yes" />.</text>
      <description-list>
        <item>
          <description>Two normal weapons</description>
          <text> When wielding two weapons the weapon in the
  character<squo/>s <dquo>good</dquo> hand receives a -3 to strike and the weapon in
  the character<squo/>s <dquo>off</dquo> hand receives a -6. Some characters can have
  <dquo>even-more-offhand</dquo> weapons, such as a kick (or two), or literally
  having extra limbs. To calculate the negative to strike for wielding
  multiple weapons, first find the number of weapons being used, then
  order them (the strike order). The first weapon is at -3 to strike,
  the second at -6, the third ad -9, and so on, i.e. the k<sup>th</sup>  weapon is at -3*k to strike.</text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <description>Paired weapons</description>
          <text>, or one normal weapon and one backup weapon:
  Some weapons are well suited to, or even designed for, use in the
  <dquo>off</dquo> hand.  When using these weapons the penalty for the offhand
  weapon is -3 as opposed to -6.  The penalty for the primary weapon
  remains -3.  Specifically, these combinations are:

        <numbered-list><item><text>Any type of knife may be used in the off-hand in combination
    with any standard (non exotic) one-handed weapon in the main hand.</text></item><item><text>Two Kris, or one Kris Datoh (main hand) and one Kris (off
    hand).</text></item><item><text>One Katana (main hand) and one Wakizashi (off hand), but only
    if the wielder is specialized in both weapons and takes the
    appropriate penalty for using the Katana one-handed.</text></item><item><text>Any weapon that is normally used in pairs, such as Sai, Kama,
    tonfa, nunchaku, or Iron Claws.</text></item><item><text>Two identical handguns, but only with the appropriate penalty
    for using them one-handed.</text></item></numbered-list></text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <description>One normal weapon and a shield or item</description>
          <text> If the character is
  wielding a 1-handed weapon in his <dquo>good</dquo> hand, and his other hand
  is carrying a shield, a non-weapon holy symbol, or a utility item
  then there is NO strike penalty at all.  For the purposes of this
  rule a utility item is something such as a torch, walking stick,
  magical totem, leash, or bag.  Utility items are not weapons and
  must not require particular attention to carry.</text>
        </item>
      </description-list>
      <text>If a character is wielding two weapons, he may always choose to attack
with the main weapon only at no penalty.  In this case the weapon in
his off hand is considered merely carried, and is not <dquo>ready</dquo> for
combat. An attack with the off-hand weapon is always made with the
full penalty, regardless of what the <dquo>main hand</dquo> is doing.</text>
      <text>Note that the Ambidexterity skill from Martial Arts can reduce
the dual-weapon penalty; and that the Multi-weapon Style skill
allows the character to strike more than once during a single <action />  A different approach is the use of the Multitarget
skill which allows the martial artist to strike multiple times with a
single weapon in a single <action /> </text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Combat Overview</title>
      <text>Resolving an attack is a three-step process:</text>
      <numbered-list>
        <item>
          <text>The attacker makes a strike roll.  A strike roll is an attempt
  to hit an opponent using a weapon or ability.</text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <text>The defender may attempt a defensive maneuver.  A defensive
  maneuver is a special skill that is used to avoid or reduce the
  damage from an incoming attack.</text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <text>If the attack was successful, damage is rolled, calculated, and
  applied to the target.</text>
        </item>
      </numbered-list>
      <text>This process is explained in detail below.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Attacking</title>
      <text>An attack is nearly anything that you try to do to an opponent during
your turn.  Typically an attack is a physical strike against your
opponent with a weapon (such as your fist or a sword), but it could
also be the use of a supernatural ability, magic spell, or a modern
device such as a gun.</text>
      <text>When you attack, you use one of your skills in an attempt to damage
your opponent.  Normally, this will be a <dquo>basic attack</dquo> skill from
Martial Arts.  Any time you make an attack like this, you roll a
Strike Roll.  Strike roll is just a special name for a
skill roll in combat<mdash/>they work just like normal skill rolls.  To
recap, roll a number of D20s equal to your level of the skill you are
using to attack with (i.e. use the Large Sword skill to strike with
your bastard sword), add your attribute and any bonuses or negatives.
For each die that hits 25 or better, you have a success.  <note>If
  you have at least one success, you strike the target.</note>  Otherwise
you miss your target.</text>
      <text>Some attacks don<squo/>t require a skill roll.  This includes special
attacks that automatically hit your opponent (such as certain
abilities from Martial Arts) as well as magical spells or supernatural
powers that are auto-targeting.  For example, the magic spell
Ray of Heat automatically hits your opponent, with no strike
roll needed.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Defending</title>
      <text>The target of an attack usually receives an attempt to defend himself.
<note>Defending is using your skills to avoid getting hit by an
  incoming attack.</note>  There are many different skills that are
available for defense.  They are called defensive maneuvers. A
defensive maneuver is a special skill or ability that you use
specifically in response to being attacked; otherwise they work like
normal skills.  A target of an attack may attempt to use any
one defensive maneuver in order to protect himself from the
attack. The most common are parrying, blocking, and the Dodge
skill.  These are described below.  Other defensive maneuvers may be
found in the Martial Arts section.</text>
      <description-list>
        <item>
          <description>Parry</description>
          <text> Parrying is using your weapon to deflect a blow from
  another weapon.  Parrying may only be performed with melee weapons,
  against either a melee or hand to hand attack.  Parrying is
  ineffective versus other attacks, such as explosives, bullets,
  chemical splashes, magical energy, etc.  Parry is not a skill
  itself, rather the skill roll for parrying is based on the weapon
  skill you are trying to parry with.  For example, you would use your
  Knife skill to parry using your dagger.  You must have your
  weapon drawn and ready in order to use it to parry.  Note, that this
  is the same skill that is used for attacking with your weapon, so
  most characters will have a good chance at parrying.  <note>A
    weapon or similar combat skill is used for parrying.  Also note
    that parrying is always subject to GM approval.  The GM determines
    the outcome of a successful parry, though it usually means that
    the defender avoids all damage.  However, if you are parrying an
    attack from a heavy or large weapon with a small weapon, the GM
    might want to impose a different outcome.</note></text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <description>Block</description>
          <text> Blocking is putting a shield between you and an incoming
  attack.  <note>Upon a successful block, a shield<squo/>s armor values
    are added to any armor that you are currently wearing</note> (see
  below).  You can attempt to block any incoming attack that you are
  aware of.  Blocking can be used against melee attacks, missile
  weapons, arrows, gunshots, and unusual attacks such as a fireball or
  an acid splash.  Larger shields will make it easier to block, more
  info can be found in the shields section.  <note>The Shield
    skill is used for blocking.  Blocking means that the blow hits,
    but the defender gets to add the armor of the shield to his own
    armor value.</note>  In the case of a non-standard attack, such as a
  splash of acid, the shield simply stops a certain percentage of the
  damage outright.</text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <description>Dodge</description>
          <text>one of the best types of defense.  Dodge is an
  (expensive) skill; dodging is moving your body out of the way of an
  incoming attack.  By sidestepping, ducking, throwing yourself to the
  ground or similar <action /> you can avoid any attack completely and
  take no damage.  The Dodge skill is used for dodging.  On a
  successful dodge the blow doesn<squo/>t hit, period.  However, dodge is a
  high rank skill, so most characters will not be very good at it.</text>
        </item>
      </description-list>
      <text>Now that you know what the types of defenses are, we are going to lump
them together and call them <dquo>defense</dquo> for the sake of simplicity for
what is to follow.</text>
      <text>To defend against an attack, you must succeed at your defending skill
roll.  And you must have MORE successes at the attacker had in his
attack roll.  For example, if an attacker has 3 successes to strike
you, then you would need at least 4 successes at your defensive skill
to protect yourself.  If you have fewer successes than the attacker,
you are struck by the attack.  You can only attempt to defend against
an attack with one type of defense.  You can only try to block, dodge,
or parry once per attack but not multiple of these at a time (i.e. you
cannot attempt to block and dodge the same attack).  You can attempt
to parry one attack and then dodge the next attack, however.</text>
      <text>If you are struck you will likely take damage from the attack.  Also
note that you cannot defend (parry, block, or dodge) an attack that
you did not know about!</text>
      <text>Note that there are other defensive maneuvers aside from Dodge, Parry,
and Block.  These include certain magic spells (Blink, for example),
martial arts abilities (such as Preemptive Dodge), or supernatural
powers.  Regardless of what defense a character chooses to use, only
ONE defense maneuver may be used against any one incoming
attack<footnote>Some magical spells or super powers of a defensive
  nature are active for a set duration<mdash/>usually several rounds.  Such
  spells, such as full barrier, are not defensive maneuvers.  These
  spells are independent of defense.  A character using such a spell
  may still use a defensive maneuver if she chooses to.  Magical
  spells, martial arts techniques, and supernatural abilities are
  considered defense maneuvers whenever they are single-use effects
  that are used against only one specific attack (such as
  Blink).</footnote><footnote>Some attacks, such as automatically targeting
  magical spells, will strike your opponent regardless of defense.
  Defensive maneuvers are ineffective against these spells.  For
  example, Ray of Heat as discussed above will always strike its
  target.  Call Lightning will always strike its target, if the caster
  succeeds on his magical control roll to cast the spell.  For these
  abilities, defensive maneuvers have no effect.</footnote>.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Damage</title>
      <text>When an attack hits its target, it will inflict damage upon it.  Every
weapon has a damage rating associated with it as well as a damage type
(for example: a dagger is a 1D6 P weapon).  The damage rating is the
amount of damage it will do, and the damage type reflects how the
weapon deals its damage.</text>
      <text>Here<squo/>s a key of the different damage types with abbreviations in
parenthesis and what they are typically associated with:</text>
      <description-list>
        <item>
          <description>Piercing (P)</description>
          <text> using a sharp tip to penetrate the target creating
  a hole or deep cut within the target.  Some melee weapons, most
  bullets, and other penetrating weapons deal piercing damage.  Armor
  can protect against this type of damage.</text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <description><slashing /> (S)</description>
          <text> using a cutting edge to slice the target creating
  a fairly shallow long cut within the target.  Most melee weapons
  such as knives and swords, as well as lasers deal <slashing /> damage.
  Armor can protect against this type of damage.</text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <description><crushing /> (C)</description>
          <text> using a heavy blunt edge in an attempt to fracture
  or break the target.  This is typically the hardest damage to
  protect against, and as such, is a favorite type of damage for melee
  combat.  Punches, clubs, staves, and explosions deal <crushing />
  damage.  Armor can protect against this type of damage.</text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <description>Undefined (U)</description>
          <text> using energy to cause damage within the target.
  This can include electricity, heat, magic, sickness and other
  <dquo>odd</dquo> types of damage.  Normal armor cannot protect against this
  type of damage.  Only your character<squo/>s <base-armor /> (BA) can protect
  you from undefined damage.  Any time someone takes undefined damage
  he or she will always take at least one point of damage, regardless
  of the <base-armor />.</text>
        </item>
        <item>
          <description>Direct (D)</description>
          <text> extremely damaging attacks deal D damage.  There is
  no way to protect yourself from <direct-damage />, as it will bypass all
  armor and other protections that you have on.  Damage from D attacks
  is subtracted directly from <hit-points /> (HP).</text>
        </item>
      </description-list>
      <text>Consider the dagger again: 1D6 P</text>
      <text>This tells us that a strike from a Dagger deals 1D6 damage.  Also, we
know that it deals piercing damage.</text>
      <text>Ok, so now we<squo/>ve got our weapon<squo/>s damage rating and it<squo/>s damage type.
Roll the given damage as described in the dice rolling section at the
beginning of the rules section.  The higher the damage roll, the more
severe the attack was upon the target.</text>
      <text>After the damage roll is determined, subtract that damage from the
target<squo/>s <hit-points /> (HP).  Armor can reduce the damage taken, which
brings us to<ellipsis/></text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Armor</title>
      <text>Armor is any covering that you are wearing or behind that will absorb
some of the damage applied to you.  All armor is given three numerical
ratings for piercing, <slashing />, and <crushing /> protection.  The higher
any one number is, the better it will protect you from that type of
damage.  Typically this value sequence is represented as P/S/C
(Piercing/<slashing />/<crushing />).  An example would be 3/2/3, which
provides 3 points of piercing protection, two points of <slashing />
protection, and 3 points of <crushing /> protection.</text>
      <text>When taking damage subtract the armor value, which matches the damage
type of the weapon, from the damage amount.</text>
      <text>Here are a few examples:</text>
      <example>
        <title>Carlos vs. the Bandit</title>
        <text>Carlos was attacked by a bandit
  with a short sword.  The bandit made his skill roll to attack and
  had three successes.  Carlos attempts to parry and had only one
  success.  Since Carlos has fewer successes than the attacker, he
  fails to parry and takes full damage.  The GM rolls damage for the
  bandit and determines that the bandit<squo/>s sword blow deals 8 damage.
  Carlos is wearing soft leather armor, which has a P/S/C rating of
  2/3/0. We know the short sword dealt 8 damage.  But it is a <slashing />
  weapon (denoted by the S in the weapon damage), so the armor
  provides 3 points of protection against this attack.  So we take the
  damage of the weapon (8) and the amount of protection the armor
  gives (3), and subtract the armor value from the weapon damage.  So,
  Carlos just took 5 damage (8-3=5).</text>
      </example>
      <example>
        <title>Lira the Gladiator</title>
        <text>Lira is fighting a gladiator-style
  duel.  Her opponent attacks with a spear and has two successes to
  hit.  Lira wants to block and rolls her shield skill.  She has four
  successes on her skill roll.  This means that she successfully
  blocked the incoming attack with her shield.  The GM rolls damage
  for the attack and gets 14 P.  (that<squo/>s a strong blow!)  Lira is
  using a Splint Shield (P/S/C of 9/9/9) and is wearing Hard Leather
  armor (3/4/1).  First, apply the damage against Lira<squo/>s shield.  Her
  shield has an armor of 9 versus P.  This means that her shield stops
  9 points of the incoming damage.  However, since the spear blow
  dealt more damage than her shield has armor, the weapon continues
  through her shield<mdash/>which now has a hole in it.  Lira now deals
  with the remaining 5 damage.  (14 damage was dealt, minus the 9
  taken by the shield = 5).  Her armor has a P value of 3, meaning
  that she only takes 2 points of damage to her HP total.  (14 damage
  - 9 from shield - 3 from armor = 2)</text>
      </example>
      <text>Now that you have that, lets introduce a few tricks.  The entire next
two paragraphs are incredibly important, so pay attention!</text>
      <text>Weapons that deal undefined or <direct-damage /> (U or D damage) bypass
all armor values.  Undefined damage can be protected against by your
character<squo/>s <base-armor /> (BA) sub-attribute.  Just subtract the BA from
the damage taken as if the BA was normal armor.  Note that <base-armor />
is not used for protecting against anything but undefined damage!  A
target will always lose at least one HP when hit with an attack that
deals undefined damage.</text>
      <text><direct-damage /> cannot be protected against.  Not by normal armor, Base
Armor, not anything.  It<squo/>s harsh, so be careful when on the receiving
end of something that deals D damage.  D damage is applied directly to
your <hit-points />.</text>
      <section>
        <title>Armor Piercing</title>
        <text>Some weapons have a note that says <dquo>AP</dquo> followed by some number.
This kind of weapon has an unusual ability to pierce armor.  If an
armored target is struck by a weapon with <dquo>AP</dquo>, the armor is reduced
by the AP number for the purposes of damage calculation.  Note, that
this cannot go negative.  If an <dquo>AP: 10</dquo> weapon strikes someone
wearing 5 armor, then the armor is totally ignored.  It does not,
however, go to -5.</text>
        <example>
          <title>Lira Strikes With Gladius</title>
          <text>Lira is wielding a gladius,
  which is a type of short sword that has AP: 5.  She successfully
  strikes her opponent, and rolls 11 damage.  Her opponent has an
  armor of 7 versus <slashing /> damage.  First, deduct the AP from the
  armor: 7 armor - 5 AP = 2.  Then, deduct the armor from the damage
  like normal: 11 damage - 2 armor = 9 damage.  Lira<squo/>s opponent takes
  9 damage.

  Consider the same situation as above, but assume that Lira<squo/>s
  opponent<squo/>s armor is only a 3 versus <slashing />.  First, deduct the AP
  form the armor: 3 armor - 5 AP = -2.  However, this cannot be
  negative, so we cap it at zero.  Now, deduct the result from the
  damage: 11 damage - 0 = 11.  Lira<squo/>s opponent takes all 11 damage.</text>
        </example>
        <text>AP is effective against armored targets, but it does nothing against
unarmored targets.  Note, that most weapons with AP don<squo/>t deal very
much damage.  It is usually a good idea to use AP weapons versus
armored targets only, and use <dquo>normal</dquo> weapons versus unarmored
targets.</text>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title><hit-points /></title>
      <text><hit-points /> are numbers used to represent how injured or healthy a
character is.  A character will have TWO Hit Point numbers.  Your
maximum <hit-points /> determines how tough your character is at full
health.  This number will rarely change.  It is determined by your BLD
and WIL attributes, and will rarely change unless your attributes
change.</text>
      <text>Your current <hit-points /> is the most important number.  It will
likely change frequently during combat.  <hit-points /> are generally
represented as a fraction: <math><frac><top>Current HP</top><bot>Max HP</bot></frac></math>.  When the game
begins, your character will be fully healthy and uninjured.  Thus,
when starting, your current HP will be equal to your maximum.</text>
      <image src='/Map/Forte-marghera-02.jpg'/>
      <text>As you get injured, any damage you take (after applying armor, etc.)
will be applied to your current HP.  As you get injured, your current
HP drops.  Over time, your body will heal itself, and your HP will go
up.  Seeking medical attention will speed this process.  Other things,
like magic or cybernetic devices, can heal you as well.</text>
      <text>Your current HP can never exceed your maximum HP.  As a general rule
for minor injuries (less than 5 HP), you gain back 1 HP per day of
average activity.  For significant HP losses, it takes (Max~HP -
Current~HP)<sup>2</sup> days to fully recover your HP.</text>
      <text>If a character is resting and is under basic medical care, then your
healing time is cut in HALF.  If your character is under the care of a
professional Doctor or Healer, healing time is cut to one QUARTER of
normal time.</text>
      <text>If your current HP falls below 0, your character falls unconscious.
It is possible to remain conscious by making a willpower check at -X,
where X is the amount below zero your HP are.  If your current HP are
below 0, your character is bleeding badly (internal bleeding is
possible too) and you will loose 1 HP per round, unless you receive
medical attention.  If your current HP ever reaches the negative of
your maximum HP, you have died.</text>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
</part>
<part>
  <title>Rule Sections</title>

  <chapter><!-- S Academics -->
    <title>Academics</title>
    <reference hrid="Academic" />
  </chapter><!-- /S Academics -->

  <chapter><!-- S Augmentations -->
    <title>Augmentations</title>

<text>Augmentations are modifications to the body made through technology. 
This can be anything from using a metal implant to repair a broken bone, to 
replacing a person's brain with a computerized electronic brain.</text>

<text>In general, augmentations fall into two categories.  They are either 
ADDITIONS to the body or REPLACEMENTS of something already there.</text>

<text>An addition is something that is added to the body that normally isn't there.
A good example is a cardiac pacemaker.  Additions add new functionality to the 
body---either as a ``fix'' for an illness, or as an upgrade to the body.  Some 
additions are very small devices that perform simple functions.  Others are 
large and complex systems that might require significant body modification!</text>

<text>A replacement is when a part of the body is removed and replaced by something 
which performs a similar task.  Replacements are usually upgrades of some kind, 
but might also be used as a repair for a body part that was injured or for 
utility purposes.</text>

    <section><!-- Additions -->
        <title>Additions</title>

<text>There are two basic types of addition augmentations.  The first are small 
devices that don't take up a lot of room.  These are easy to add to the body 
because they don't require any power or a lot of space.  As a general rule, 
this type of augmentation is very small and its function is often limited.</text>

<text>The second type are larger, complex systems, which take up a lot of space in 
the body.  Generally, the only way to add something like this to your body is 
to remove, move, replace, or otherwise modify some other
part of your body in 
order to accommodate it.  This works on a system of slots (see below) which is 
similar to the Mecha system.</text>

    </section><!-- /Additions -->
    <section><!-- Replacements -->
        <title>Replacements</title>

<text>Augmentation replacements, in their most basic forms, are exactly the same 
function-wise as normal body parts.  Of course, many augmentation parts are 
upgrades of some sort.  They might be stronger, faster, or more durable than 
normal.  Some augmentation replacements have new functions or different 
abilities than normal.</text>

    </section><!-- /Replacements -->
    <section><!-- Augmentation Limbs and Bodies -->
        <title>Augmentation Limbs and Bodies</title>

<text>Entire limbs or even entire bodies may be replaced with augmented versions.  
There are two basic types of replacement limbs and bodies: Robotic or Cybernetic.</text>

<text>Robotic limbs are built entirely from non-organic materials.  They are machines
made of steel, high-tensile alloys, wires and high pressure hoses.  Movement 
comes from hydraulics, electric motors, gears and levers.  Robotic body parts 
contain no flesh or blood.</text>

<text>Cybernetic limbs are basically organic.  They consist of bone, tendons, and 
muscles just like ``natural'' limbs.  However, cybernetic limbs are enhanced 
with technology including electric implants, genetically modified tissues, 
and some synthetic material reinforcements.</text>

<text>These rules apply to cybernetic and robotic components:</text>

        <section><!-- Robotics -->
            <title>Robotics</title>

<itemized-list>
    <item> Do not bleed when injured (though they might leak oil or make sparks)</item>
    <item> Have unnatural heat signatures</item>
    <item> Do not look or feel realistic in the slightest; rather they look 
like machinery.</item>
    <item> Take double damage from electrical sources.</item>
    <item> Are immune to disease, poison, and magical effects that work on 
living targets (a robotic body part is not alive).  Note that this 
means that healing magic or typical healing/medical items have no effect on robotics.</item>
    <item> Have double the HP of non-robotic parts.</item>
    <item> Robotic limbs cannot be upgraded directly.  They can, however, be 
easily removed and replaced with upgraded parts.</item>
    <item> Used robotic parts generally have high resale value and demand.
Used parts are regularly available.  Many robotic parts are interchangeable.</item>
    <item> Robotic parts are considered fairly easy to replace and repair.  
Some parts can be swapped in a matter of minutes.</item>
    <item> Robotic parts do not heal automatically.  If damaged, repairs must be
made by a mechanic or by replacing the damaged parts with new ones.</item>
</itemized-list>

        </section><!-- /Robotics -->
        <section><!-- Cybernetics -->
            <title>Cybernetics</title>

<itemized-list>
    <item>
         Bleed when injured
    </item>
    <item>
         Appear normal when viewed casually, or on thermal sensors.  Many 
cybernetic limbs will appear 100% normal even under close visual inspection.  
However, inspection by a knowledgeable person (Doctor, Nurse, Cyber Doctor, 
etc.) will reveal the true nature of the limb.
    </item>
    <item>
         Usually feels realistic to the touch, but not necessarily.
    </item>
    <item>
         Are fully susceptible to disease, poison, and life-affecting magic 
just like any other living tissue (cybernetic body parts are living tissue)
    </item>
    <item>
         Cybernetic parts can be upgraded at a later date without total 
replacement.  However, this usually requires surgery.
    </item>
    <item>
         Cybernetic parts are usually built around the user's body.  Used 
cybernetic parts are valuable, but the potential market is limited to those 
people who are very similar to the original owner.  Therefore the used 
cybernetic parts market tends to be flooded with supply for which it is 
difficult to find a buyer.  It is often time consuming to find a donor or 
source for a particular part.  Cybernetics parts prices for both buyers and 
sellers will vary wildly depending on market conditions, which are nearly 
impossible to predict.
    </item>
    <item>
         Repair to cybernetic limbs is a combination of electro-mechanical work 
and traditional medicine.  Repairing significant injuries or adding/removing 
cybernetics often entails surgery, a hospital stay, and may well require 
lengthy recovery time.
    </item>
    <item>
         Minor injuries to cybernetic limbs heal just like injuries to a normal 
human.  Magical healing and regeneration works for cybernetics in most cases, 
though healing may be incomplete if the damage is severe.
    </item>
</itemized-list>

        </section><!-- /Cybernetics -->
    </section><!-- /Augmentation Limbs and Bodies -->
    <section><!-- General Augmentation Rules -->
        <title>General Augmentation Rules</title>

<itemized-list>
    <item>
         All humanoid characters have, by default, (size) free slots in the body.
These are assumed to be located in the torso.  (Humans, which are size 2, 
start with +2 slots) If you want more slots to store things in, you have to 
purchase augmentations that give you back additional slots.
    </item>
    <item>
         After all augmentations are chosen for a character, add up the slot 
total.  This number must be positive.  (In other words, augmentations cannot 
be installed unless there are slots available to house those parts)
    </item>
    <item>
         A robotic limb may be attached to any kind of torso.  However, a 
cybernetic limb can only be attached to a natural (non-robotic) torso.  
This is because all cybernetic limbs depend on the support organs and 
blood supply found in the torso.
    </item>
</itemized-list>

    </section><!-- /General Augmentation Rules -->
    <section><!-- Determining the Cost of an Augmentation body part -->
        <title>Determining the Cost of an Augmentation body part</title>
        
        <note>This section is incomplete.</note>
        
    </section><!-- /Determining the Cost of an Augmentation body part -->

    <section><!-- Arm, Hand -->
      <title>Arm, Hand</title>
      <reference hrid="Content/Augmentations/Arm, Hand" />
    </section><!-- /Arm, Hand -->

    <section><!-- Body -->
      <title>Body</title>
      <reference hrid="Content/Augmentations/Body" />
    </section><!-- /Body -->

    <section><!-- Head -->
      <title>Head</title>
      <reference hrid="Content/Augmentations/Head" />
    </section><!-- /Head -->

    <section><!-- Leg -->
      <title>Leg</title>
      <reference hrid="Content/Augmentations/Leg" />
    </section><!-- /Leg -->

    <section><!-- Torso -->
      <title>Torso</title>
      <reference hrid="Content/Augmentations/Torso" />
    </section><!-- /Torso -->

  </chapter><!-- /S Augmentations -->

  <chapter><!-- S Equipment -->
    <title>Equipment</title>

    <section><!-- Ammunition -->
      <title>Ammunition</title>
      <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Ammunition" />
    </section><!-- /Ammunition -->

    <section>
      <title>Armor</title>
        <section><!-- Basics for Armor and Damage -->
          <title>Basics for Armor and Damage</title>

<itemized-list>
    <item> Armor has 3 main values: Piercing, slashing, and crushing.  
  Armor values are represented by 3 numbers separated by slashes 
  (represented by:  P/S/C; piercing/slashing/crushing).  Example: Armor 
  with values of 4/3/7 would have 4 points of protection vs. Piercing, 
  3 vs. Slashing, and 7 vs. crushing damage.</item>
    <item> Armor does not protect from Undefined (U) or Direct (D).</item>
    <item> A character<squo />s Base Armor is the only thing that can protect vs. 
  U damage.  Nothing can protect against D damage.</item>
    <item> All non D/U damage has an associated damage type to is; either P, 
  S, or C.  Subtract all matching armor values of the character from 
  the damage being done.  If the damage value is still above 0, then 
  the character takes that amount of damage.</item>
    <item> A weapon with an armor piercing (AP) attack will list the amount 
  of AP it has.  Subtract this AP number from all of the armor<squo />s 
  damage values when determining its protection against the attack.  
  This cannot drop the armor<squo />s value below 0.</item>
    <item> GMs determine when armor is damaged beyond use/protection.</item>
    <item> Hard Armor is any armor that uses hard
  ceramic/plastic/metallic/wooden plates or coverage to protect 
  the character.  Hard armor is MUCH more durable than non-hard armor.  
  Hard armor is denoted by <dquo>hard</dquo> on the armor sheet.  Note that 
  the components of hard armor are hard.  They can<squo />t be bent 
  without damaging the armor.  Hard armor is generally made specifically 
  for the wearer, it will only fit others with nearly identical 
  body proportions.</item>
    <item> Soft armor (armor that isn<squo />t considered hard) is at least 
  somewhat flexible.  It will generally fit anyone of similar size/stature. </item>
    <item> Armor with the descriptor of <dquo>fire</dquo> has fire protection.  
  This means the armor has the <dquo>natural</dquo> ability to deflect 
  and protect against fire attacks.  The armor will protect from all 
  fire damage (assuming the fire hits the armor, so full suits are 
  better for this).</item>
    <item> Armor can be layered, but only one hard suit can be worn at a 
  time.  A person can have different hard armors on different parts of 
  the body.  Non-hard armors can be layered indefinitely.  Add all 
  armor values of the armors together to give the full armor protection.  
  If any armor has fire protection, fire will be stopped, but any armor 
  on top of it is still susceptible to the fire.</item>
    <item> Encumbrance is determined by: BLD/3</item>
    <item> A character can wear (without penalty) as much armor in size 
  levels as his Encumbrance score will allow.  Add up all layers of 
  armor to get the complete Size level of the armor, if this number 
  is equal or less than Encumbrance, then no negatives are given to the player.</item>
    <item> When a character has more armor than his Encumbrance (ENC) 
  allows, then the player has the following penalties against him:
        <itemized-list>
            <item> -2 DEX per pt over ENC</item>
            <item> -1 action per 2 full points over ENC</item>
        </itemized-list>
    </item>
    <item> An armor<squo />s Class is a general idea of what period of history/future 
  the armor would appear.  A later period can find the earlier armor.</item>
</itemized-list>

    </section><!-- /Basics for Armor and Damage -->
    <section><!-- Shields -->
        <title>Shields</title>

<itemized-list>
    <item> When creating a shield, there are 2 factors.  The material the 
  shield is made of, and the type of shield.  Choose both of these 
  values when creating a shield to get the full set of statistics 
  for the shield.
    </item>
    <item> On a successful block, a shield will subtract its appropriate 
  armor value from the damage.  Any damage that penetrates the shield 
  will then be applied against the user<squo />s armor.
    </item>
    <item> Shields can be used to block U attacks that are <dquo>thrown</dquo> 
  at them.  These include fireballs, lightning strikes, breath 
  weapons, chemical splashes, etc.  To block one of these attacks, 
  the user must make a block roll at -3.  If successful, then damage 
  will be reduced based on the type of shield:
        <itemized-list>
            <item> Buckler: Full damage</item>
            <item> Small: <math>1/4</math></item>
            <item> Large: <math>1/2</math></item>
            <item> Tower: <math>3/4</math></item>
        </itemized-list>
    </item>
</itemized-list>

    </section><!-- /Shields -->

    <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Armor" />

    </section><!-- /Armor -->

      <section><!-- Energy Weapons -->
        <title>Energy Weapons</title>
        <text>
Most energy weapons are powered by a battery pack.  These are interchangable between weapons.  Energy within the packs is consumed as the weapon is fired, like normal bullets.  They are called <dquo>batts</dquo> or <dquo>b-paks</dquo> in slang. B-paks store energy in units of EU.  Different weapons consume EU at different rates.  Smaller weapons use 1 EU per shot.  Larger weapons might use more.  Pistols can hold ONE pack.  Rifles/cannons can usually hold 3. B-paks can be recharged.  Recharging a pack takes about thirty seconds per EU that has been used.  As a general rule, it costs $1 per EU to have pack recharged.  HD paks require special equipment to charge and these cost about $1.50 per EU to charge.
        </text>
      </section><!-- /Energy Weapons -->

      <section><!-- Melee -->
        <title>Melee</title>

          <text>
For damage type listed as _/_, the weapon can deal either type of
damage for a given attack.  For a P/S weapon, the attcker can choose
to do a P or S attack. For every point of STR under Min. STR, the
attack gets -1 damage and -2 to strike/parry. STR Req is the minimum
strength required to wield the weapon. For every point of STR over the
Strength Requirement, add one point of damage to the raw roll, up to a
maximum of the MSB (Max Strength Bonus) A raw bonus is always
indicated with square brackets.  So 3D4+1 [+4] would be a normal 3D4+1
roll, with an additional 4 added to the final result. When wielding a
1-H weapon with two hands, assume the wielder has +2 STR.
          </text>

          <description-list>
<item><description>Hands</description> Number of hands required to use the weapon</item>
<item><description>Rec</description> Number of actions it takes to recover after attacking with
  the weapon.  This many actions must be spent to get the weapon ready
  for attack again.</item>
<item><description>Enc</description> Represents the weight of the weapon.  This consumes
  Encumbrance just like armor.  Only use this when the weapon is
  actually being used.</item>
<item><description>Range</description> the effective ``Reach'' of the weapon in feet.  If your
  target is beyond your range, you cannot strike them. You can spend
  an action to gain range on your opponent. If your target is closer
  than 1/2 range, then you are at -6 to strike the target.</item>
          </description-list>

        <section><!-- Options for Melee Weapons -->
          <title>Options for Melee Weapons</title>

          <text>
Prices listed are for basic weapons with enough durability to function
in real combat situations.  They are not showpieces or wallhangers.
However, other options are available for an extra cost:
          </text>

          <figure>
            <table>
              <head>
                <cell align="left" border-right="yes" />
                <cell align="center" />
                <cell align="center" />
                <cell align="center" />
              </head>
              <row>
                <cell span="4">Options for Mel<grave>e</grave>e weapons</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Exceptional Quality<cell></cell>+1 damage<cell></cell>double cost<cell></cell>Adds 1 to rarity</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Master Quality<cell></cell>+2 damage<cell></cell>10 times cost<cell></cell>Adds 3 to rarity</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Legendary Quality<cell></cell>+3 damage<cell></cell>100 times cost<cell></cell>Adds 5 to rarity</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Vibro-edge (bladed only)<cell></cell>+10 AP<cell></cell>5 times cost<cell></cell>ULTRAMODERN</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Wooden Training<cell></cell>1/2 damage, C<cell></cell>1/10<sup>th</sup> cost</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <caption>Options for mel<grave>e</grave>e weapon construction</caption>
          </figure>

          <text>
For other than normal sized weapons (mecha, etc.), all stats are
2<sup>Size-1</sup> normal.  This applies to strength requirement, strength
bonus, damage dice number, etc.
          </text>

        </section><!-- /Options for Melee Weapons -->

        <section><!-- Axes -->
          <title>Axes</title>

          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Axes" />
        </section><!-- /Axes -->

        <section><!-- Blunt -->
          <title>Blunt</title>

          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Blunt" />
        </section><!-- /Blunt -->

        <section><!-- Body -->
          <title>Body</title>

          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Body" />
        </section><!-- /Body -->

        <section><!-- Chained -->
          <title>Chained</title>

          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Chained" />
        </section><!-- /Chained -->

        <section><!-- Exotic -->
          <title>Exotic</title>

          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Exotic" />
        </section><!-- /Exotic -->

        <section><!-- Knives -->
          <title>Knives</title>

          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Knives" />
        </section><!-- /Knives -->

        <section><!-- Large Swords -->
          <title>Large Swords</title>

          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Large Swords" />
        </section><!-- /Large Swords -->

        <section><!-- Monofilament -->
          <title>Monofilament</title>

          <text>
The Monofilament Whip is length of metallic, diamondoid, or silicoid wire that is the thickness of a single molecule, with a weight on one end.	The Archaic Weapon<mdash />Chain skill is used.  A skill roll of 4 or less is considered a critical failure (instead of the normal 1). This modified critical failure is there for people who are skilled.  Those who are not get a critical failure on a 9 or below.
          </text>

          <text>
The recover time of the Monofilament Whip cannot be reduced by strength, and will always require a 1 action to recover from safely. The user can attempt to reduce the recover time to 0, but there is a 50% chance that the user will strike himself with the	whip dealing full damage to himself.
          </text>

          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Monofilament" />
        </section><!-- /Monofilament -->

        <section><!-- Plasma -->
          <title>Plasma</title>

          <text>
Plasma weapons are designed for a specific set of modifications. These
are:
          </text>

          <figure>
            <table>
              <head>
                <cell align="left">Type</cell><cell width="1.5in">Effect</cell><cell align="center">Cost Factor</cell>
              </head>
              <row>
                <cell>High temperature</cell>
                <cell>Blade is hotter than normal, dealing +1 damage, can be purchased up to 3 times (each time double cost)</cell>
                <cell>x2</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Over powered field</cell>
                <cell>The magnetic field is stronger than normal, giving a +5 STR when breaking from a lock</cell>
                <cell>x2</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>High speed blade</cell>
                <cell>The plasma weapon can be turned on in 0 actions</cell>
                <cell>x1.5</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Power burst</cell>
                <cell>Once per minute the blade's power can be increased to deal +3 damage</cell>
                <cell>x1.5</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
            <caption>Plasma Weapon Modifiers</caption>
          </figure>

          <section><!-- Notes for Plasma Weapons -->
            <title>Notes: specific to Plasma Weapons</title>

            <itemize-list>
              <item>Plasma weapons are a bladeless handle (typically looks like a
  normal weapon handle or a flashlight) from which a glowing blade of
  extremely hot plasma vents forth.  The plasma is held in the shape
  of a cylinder (or blade) by a magnetic field. They take an action to
  turn on.</item>
              <item>Due to the difference between using a plasma weapon verses
  normal weapons, they require the Archaic Weapons - Energy skill to
  use. Anyone can use their normal sword skill (or axe skill
  respectively) but will get a critical failure on a 4 or below
  (instead of the normal 1).</item>
              <item>Plasma weapons cannot be parried by non-plasma weapons,
  likewise, they cannot parry non-plasma weapons.  Similarly, shields
  cannot block plasma weapons.  Plasma weapons can parry other plasma
  weapons, and force fields protect against them as normal If a plasma
  weapon comes in contact with another one, there is a 25% chance the
  magnetic fields of the blades will lock together. It is easy to tell
  if combatants are locked as an extremely bright glow emanates from
  the contact point of the weapons. Getting out of a lock requires an
  action where a strength contest ensues.  If there is more than a
  difference of 8 between the two strength rolls, the lock is broken
  and the loser loses his or her next action.  If no break occurs, the
  combatants must attempt again on the next action. Either combatant
  in a lock can turn off their weapon, in which case he or she
  automatically loses the lock challenge, and gets the same negative
  as if he lost due in a STR contest.</item>
              <item>One side effect of having a magnetic field around the blade, is
  that it is possible to parry projectile energy attacks (such as
  shots from a beam rifle).  Doing so the wielder is at a -8.</item>
            </itemize-list>

          </section><!-- /Notes for Plasma Weapons -->

        </section><!-- /Plasma -->

        <section><!-- Polearms -->
          <title>Polearms</title>
          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Polearms" />
        </section><!-- /Polearms -->

        <section><!-- Rocket Assisted -->
          <title>Rocket Assisted</title>

          <text>
Rocket-assisted weapons are modern versions of traditional archaic weapons.  They have small rocket motors contained in the weapon.	When the weapon is swung,  the motor ignites, giving extra force to the blow.  They are used with the same skill as normal archaic weapons.
          </text>

          <text>
If such a weapon is used, and the target is missed, then it takes an extra two actions to recover.  If the target is hit but the blow	is parried or blocked, then it takes the normal time to recover.
          </text>

          <text>
When using rocket assisted weapons, you need an extra success to parry melee attacks.  (At least two better than attacker.)
          </text>

          <text>
Each weapon can store up to 5 <dquo>rocket charges.</dquo>  When these are used up, they must be refilled before the weapon can be used.	Each charge costs $100 to refill.
          </text>

          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Rocket Assisted" />
        </section><!-- /Rocket Assisted -->

        <section><!-- Staves -->
          <title>Staves</title>
          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Staves" />
        </section><!-- /Staves -->

        <section><!-- Thrown -->
          <title>Thrown</title>
          <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Melee/Thrown" />
        </section><!-- /Thrown -->

      </section><!-- /Melee -->

      <section><!-- Miscellaneous -->
        <title>Miscellaneous</title>
        <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Miscellaneous" />
      </section><!-- /Miscellaneous -->

      <section><!-- Ranged -->
        <title>Ranged</title>
        <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Ranged" />
      </section><!-- /Ranged -->

      <section><!-- Shields -->
        <title>Shields</title>
        <reference hrid="Content/Equipment/Shields" />
      </section><!-- /Shields -->

  </chapter><!-- /S Equipment -->
  <chapter><!-- S Magic -->
    <title>Magic</title>

  <section><!-- Introduction -->
    <title>Introduction</title>
  
    <text>
  Magic exists in many forms.  It is a supernatural energy that
  permeates everything in the world.  Characters with the right skills
  can bend this energy to their will<mdash />and perform amazing feats in the
  process.  Magic is capable of healing the sick, raising the dead,
  creating a great fireball, protecting the caster from harm<mdash />and
  nearly anything else you can imagine.
    </text>
  
    <text>
  Magic, whatever type it might be, is all about manipulating MANA.
  Mana, as mentioned above, is a supernatural energy that is present in
  everything.  It is in the air, the ground, in your food, even in your
  body.  Mana is what is responsible for <dquo>enforcing</dquo> physical laws
  such as gravity, etc.  When a person uses magic, they are manipulating
  mana to do what they want.  Normally, this is the mana that is in
  their own body.  It is possible to work with mana outside one<squo />s body
  as well.  Nobody really knows exactly how mana works, but special
  gestures and body movements handed down throughout time are believed
  to initiate complex quantum-mechanical events that result in seemingly
  impossible things taking place<mdash />magic.
    </text>
  
    <text>
  Mana is found in all things.  However, more mana is found in some
  things than others.  Gases (air, for example) have very little mana.
  Denser substances such as water and stone have more mana.  Complex
  things such as man-made objects (pottery, woodcarvings, machinery,
  etc.) contain quite a lot of mana.  Living things, from mice to humans
  to whales, contain even more mana.  Mana is released back into the
  environment when living things die, or when mana-rich objects decay,
  are burned, or broken.  Other objects tend to <dquo>soak up</dquo> mana that is
  released near them.  Thus, older items tend to contain more mana than
  do <dquo>new</dquo> ones.  Whenever an item is broken it is possible to extract
  some of its mana as it dissipates back into the environment.  This is
  also possible when a living creature dies.  In game terms, we call
  mana <dquo>MP</dquo> (Mana Points / Magic Points).
    </text>
  
    <text>
  Examples of locations/things that are very rich in mana:
    </text>
    
    <itemize-list>
      <item> Graveyards, grave markers</item>
      <item> Large Churches, Cathedrals, holy symbols, idols, and relics</item>
      <item> Museums, famous artwork or historical objects</item>
      <item> Antiques</item>
      <item> Ancient ruins, crypts, etc.</item>
    </itemize-list>
  
    <text>
  Examples of locations/things that have a lot of mana:
    </text>
  
    <itemize-list>
      <item> Old houses, family heirlooms</item>
      <item> Smaller churches and shrines.</item>
      <item> Local landmarks such as wishing wells, old trees, popular meeting places</item>
      <item> Very old people, especially those that are revered by others.</item>
      <item> Important people with a lot of public exposure or reknown
    (royalty, politicians, popular musicians, etc)</item>
      <item> Slaughterhouses</item>
      <item> Fossils, natural gemstones</item>
    </itemize-list>
  
    <text>
  Examples of locations/things that have very little mana:
    </text>
  
    <itemize-list>
      <item> Barren landscapes such as desert or arctic regions</item>
      <item> Sky</item>
      <item> Some underground caves or dungeons</item>
      <item> <dquo>Ghost towns</dquo> / looted or abandoned buildings</item>
      <item> Newly cleared land</item>
    </itemize-list>
  
  </section><!-- /Introduction -->
  
  <section><!-- Types of Magic -->
    <title>Types of Magic</title>
  
    <section><!-- Invocation Magic (spellcasting) -->
      <title>Invocation Magic (spellcasting)</title>
  
      <text>
  Invocation spellcasting is the most common and basic form of magic.
  This is the art of the wizard and sorceress, where characters use
  innate mana to cast spells.  Invocation spells are based on
  methodical, practiced, gestures and chanting of magical incantations.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Incantation magic is learned.  The invocation magician will have a
  list of spells that she has studied and memorized.  As long as she has
  mana (MP) available, she may cast any spell that she knows.  Because
  invocation magicians use innate mana and well defined, repeatable,
  forms it is the easiest type of magic to learn.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Spells are learned from other magicians, studious research, or a
  combination of the two.  Research requires access to various books on
  the subject of magic, including book(s) that are specifically about
  the spell to be learned.  True books on magical subjects are few and
  far between, and books about high level spells are extremely valuable.
  Invocation magicians have invented a special language to record and
  describe magic spells and the procedures required to cast them.  All
  true magical books will be written, at least in part, in this
  special language.  Wizards and Sorceresses might hail from different
  countries, races, and moral standpoints<mdash />but they all share common
  ground in the ability to read magical script.  Magical script is
  specially designed to describe and transcribe magical spells,
  therefore it is rarely used for other purposes.  It is difficult to
  carry on a conversation, written or spoken, in the language of magic.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  More often than not a wizard will belong to a particular clan or
  school, where many wizards pool their knowledge and references for
  members to share.  In such situations there will usually be more
  experienced spellcasters that may teach their skills to junior
  members.  Wizards may be children of existing wizards or they might be
  apprentices or students at an established wizard<squo />s school or place of
  business.  Wizard secret societies are common as well.  Some are
  devoted to particular schools of magic.  Others are devoted to a
  certain cause and happen to share arcane secrets to persue common
  goals.  Wizard secret societies and wizard schools are places where
  other wizards can learn new spells and find magical items.  However,
  most magic secret societies have a strict hierarchy and code of
  conduct.  Special oaths, tithes, and obedience to the order are often
  required, and favors always entail repayment.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Spells are purchased (learned) similar to skills.  However, there are
  no levels for spells.  A character either knows a given spell, or they
  don<squo />t.  If you like you can think of this as a <dquo>level 1 skill</dquo>.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  There exist different schools (aka categories) of magic.  Some Wizards
  specialize in certain schools, but that is purely optional.  Any
  character may learn spells from any category<mdash />but with the following
  restrictions.  A character may only learn a given spell if she knows
  at least one spell of lower rank from the same school.  As well, the
  rank of the spell must be no higher than your <spellcasting />
  skill level.  For example, you cannot learn a rank 4 <dquo>Air</dquo> magic
  spell unless you already know a rank 3 <dquo>Air</dquo> spell, AND you must
  have Level 4 or higher <spellcasting />.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  You can learn any spell, regardless of type, if you have a
  spellcasting skill at least three levels higher than the rank of the
  spell.  For example, if you have a spellcasting skill level of 6, then
  you could learn any spell of rank 3 or lower, regardless of school or
  prerequisite lower-rank spell.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  A character with level 1 or higher spellcasting can always learn Rank
  1 magical spells from any school without restriction.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Note that a Wizard or Sorceress character must have at least one level
  in Magical Studies in order to read spell books and to learn the
  intonations required for magical incantations.  Beyond that Magical
  Studies is a purely optional skill.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Characters that cast Invocation magic must have at least two free
  points of Encumberance available.  If not, they are not able to cast
  magic.
      </text>
    </section><!-- /Invocation Magic (spellcasting) -->
  
    <section><!-- Ritual Magic -->
      <title>Ritual Magic</title>
  
      <text>
  Ritual magic is performed in elaborate <dquo>performances</dquo> involving a
  much human involvement.  Magic rituals involve material components
  (ingredients) and a great deal of chanting, mumbling, gesturing, and
  the like.  The traditional image of a witch, bent over a bubbling
  cauldron containing newt eyes and salamander toenails is a good
  example of ritual magic.  Whereas traditional spellcasting is an
  almost scientific pursuit, ritual magic is more of an art. Rituals are
  conducted with a trained eye and experience.  Because ritual
  ingredients vary in quality and potency, precision has little
  use. Ritual magicians are shamans, witches and warlocks.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Ritual magic is not religious.  In fact, it is no more religious than
  making a bowl of oatmeal or mixing some cement.  However, in many
  cultures ritual magic is heavily associated with religion, especially
  in primitive, animistic, or tribal societies.  In these cultures
  ritual magic is the domain of the <dquo>witch doctor</dquo> or <dquo>medicine
  man</dquo><mdash />people who hold important positions in the tribe, often
  including that of a kind of priest or spiritual leader.  Therefore,
  there is a strong association between ritual magic and primitive,
  pagan, religions.  Many ritual magicians are religious figures,
  members of mysterious cults, etc.  Some ritual magicians have been
  known to practice animal or even human sacrifice (an excellent, though
  horrific, source of MP for rituals).  In these societies ritual magic
  is often believed to be religious in nature despite the fact that it
  is decidedly not.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Ritual magic users do not use innate MP to perform magic.  Rather,
  they use material components (ingredients) to create magical effects.
  Performing rituals requires a large amount of space and various
  supplies and components. Ritual preparation and casting is a time
  consuming and often messy proposition.  Therefore, most ritualists
  have a set area where they can store their materials and perform
  rituals: usually a quiet location away from prying eyes.  This might
  be a purpose-built room in the home or a secret <dquo>lair</dquo> in a basement
  or abandoned building.  It might even be a cave or hidden woodland
  grotto.  Such an area is a very personal space for the ritualist, and
  while it might be neatly organized or highly messy, it will be arrayed
  exactly how its owner prefers.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Most ritual supplies are re-useable, and a ritualist<squo />s <dquo>kitchen</dquo>
  will be well stocked with such items.  These include such things as
  wands, knives, scales, measuring devices, a fireplace, cauldrons,
  bottles, pots, strainers, mirrors, precious gems, candles, assorted
  tools, and so on.  Approximately $1000 * Rank worth of supplies is
  required in a ritualist<squo />s <dquo>kitchen</dquo>.  (In other words, in order to
  perform the Ritual Stoneform, which is a rank 6 spell, $6000 worth of
  supplies are required to be on hand) These supplies are reuseable and
  are used for many different rituals.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Specific spells require different ingredients.  Ingredients could be
  nearly anything, including herbs and roots, body parts (animal and
  human), minerals, chemicals, plants, and so forth.  Some of these are
  common and will be used for many different spells.  Others are quite
  specific and rare, and have very specific applications.  A ritualist
  will usually have a personal stockpile of ingredients and components
  stored away.  This stockpile will usually include all but the most
  expensive of components.  Of course, some components can be difficult
  to find and some must be fresh, so any ritualist will definately have
  the means to locate components that she needs.  Some components might
  be gathered personally, through the use of skills such as herbalism,
  alchemy, hunting, or scrounging.  Other components are purchased by
  the ritualist.  Some components may be purchased at common merchants
  while others must be purchased from special (and sometimes illicit)
  vendors.  Most ritualists will have known connections through which
  different components and supplies might be shared, purchased, or
  loaned.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  The cost of ingredients for a particular spell is approximately 1/10
  of the <dquo>scroll or potion</dquo> cost from the spell chart. This assumes
  fair prices in an open market.  However, this cost might vary greatly
  depending on various circumstances.  For example, in a certain town
  components for Fire spells might be common and therefore very
  inexpensive, while components for Earth spells might be rare and
  therefore much more expensive.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  In addition to its specific <dquo>recipe</dquo>, any ritual spell will also
  require the infusion of mana.  As mentioned above, in ritual magic the
  MP does not come from the caster.  The caster must gather objects
  containing sufficient MP to conduct the spell.  As mentioned above,
  mana is present in nearly everything, but generally not in sufficient
  quantity to do any good.  Therefore, the ritualist must seek out items
  that are rich in MP to use when conducting a ritual.  This process
  results in the destruction of the items used!  This might even entail
  the sacrifice of living things<mdash />if such an amount of MP is required.
  Generally, items yielding MP for ritual use will cost about $1 per MP
  required, though this will vary.  Much like individual spell
  components, a ritualist will tend to hoard items that may be
  sacrificed for MP.  Common items are living plants and small animals,
  antiques, old artwork, fossils, old holy items, old clothing
  (especially from special occasions) and well-used household goods.
  MP-source items are not spell-dependant.  MP items can be used for ANY
  spell.
      </text>
  
      <itemize-list>
        <item> NO MP from the character are required for ritual magic</item>
        <item> Each spell<squo />s components cost 1/10th of the <dquo>scroll/potion</dquo>
    cost from the spell table, PLUS $1 for each MP required.
    Components are consumed and can only be used once.  (note that costs
    are approximate and should be determined by the GM)</item>
        <item> The time required to prepare for a given ritual is equal to
    Rank-1 hours.  Once preparations are made, the ritual must be
    conducted within 12 hours or the preparations are wasted and must be
    begun again.  Preparation uses up one half of the required ritual
    ingredients.</item>
        <item> The time required to perform a given ritual is [Time] minutes.
    Conducting the ritual itself must be done within 12 hours of
    preparations being made, and uses up the remaining half of the
    ritual ingredients.</item>
        <item>	Ritual spells cost 1 less Rank to learn than normal</item>
        <item> Ritual magicians learn free rituals as they gain levels in
    Ritual Magic, according to the chart below; note that they are free
    to purchase other spells as they desire.</item>
      </itemize-list>
  
      <figure>
        <title>Rank of Ritual Spell</title>
        <table>
          <head>
            <cell align="center">Level of Ritual Magic</cell>
            <cell align="right">1</cell><cell align="right">2</cell>
            <cell align="right">3</cell><cell align="right">4</cell>
            <cell align="right">5</cell><cell align="right">6</cell>
            <cell align="right">7</cell><cell align="right">8</cell>
            <cell align="right">9</cell><cell align="right">10</cell>
          </head>
            <row>
              <cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>3</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>4</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>5</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>6</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>7</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>8</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>9</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>2 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>10</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1 </cell>
            </row>
        </table>
        <caption>Rank of Ritual Spells per Ritual Magic Level</caption>
      </figure>
  
      <text>
  Ritual magicians may also perform a ritual in a special manner,
  infusing the spell into an object, such as a weapon or magical totem.
  Infusing a spell takes the same amount of time as performing the
  ritual in normal fashion.  Once the spell is infused in an item, it
  may be released very quickly.  Releasing a charge (the energy and
  magical effects of a stored ritual) requires 1 action, regardless of
  the original casting time of the spell.  Infused ritual items are only
  good for twenty-four hours, at which point the charge is lost and the
  item returns to normal.  The ritualist may create charges of extended
  duration when he first performs the infusion, but each 24 hours of
  time requires another batch of the requisite spell ingredients (not
  Mana).  Therefore, it can become very expensive to make long duration
  infused items.  An infused item may be used by anyone, not just the
  ritualist.
      </text>
  
    </section><!-- /Ritual Magic -->
  
    <section><!-- Religious and Faith Magic -->
      <title>Religious &amp; Faith Magic</title>
  
      <text>
  Religious magic is magical effects that are brought into reality by
  the combined will of the caster and the caster<squo />s god(s).  Whereas
  primitive religions and cults tend towards the use of ritual magic,
  Religious or Faith magic is practiced by priests of clearly defined
  and well organized religions.  Most religions that practice Faith
  magic have a clearly organized hierarchy within the church.  Religious
  dogma and/or scripture is well defined and is extensively documented.
  Faith-magic using religions are not necessarily <dquo>good</dquo>, but they are
  usually known to the general public and often actively recruit new
  members.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Religious magic is taught by a particular Church. Each faith has one
  or more magic schools associated with it.  These nearly always include
  <Spiritual /> and <Life /> magic, and may include others.  Most
  faiths have 3 or 4 schools of spells.  A faith caster has access to
  all spells in the school(s) associated with his <faith />, except
  those whose rank is higher than his level of faith, and those which
  are specifically prohibited by his Church.  For example, a <dquo>good</dquo>
  tending religion would typically deny harmful <Life />-magic spells
  to their adherents, for example curse.
      </text>
  
      <itemize-list>
        <item>	MP are consumed as normal spellcasting</item>
        <item>	A holy symbol is required for religious magic casting</item>
        <item>	A successful Faith check must be made for casting faith magic.</item>
      </itemize-list>
  
      <text>
  Priests, monks, and warriors of faith practice religious magic.  All
  religious spells are channeled through a holy symbol (see below).
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Once a day the caster must engage in prayer.  The exact means of
  praying is left up to the players &amp; GM, but during this time the
  priest will choose which spells he as access to for the remainder of
  the day.  The caster may choose any combination of spells he has
  access to, provided that he has enough MP (at the time of prayer) for
  that particular combination.  The caster must allocate MP and spells
  during this prayer session.  Until the next prayer session those are
  the spells the caster may use.  A holy symbol of at least +0 quality
  is required for this prayer, otherwise the caster cannot allocate
  spells for that day.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  A faith magic user always uses the <faith /> skill for any and all
  magic-related skill rolls, including those that would normally require
  <spellcasting /> or <magical-control />, etc.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  A <holy-symbol /> is always required to cast <faith /> magic.
  If a holy symbol is not available, then Faith magic simply cannot be
  cast.  Thankfully, a simple gesture or trinket often suffices.  There
  are different types of holy symbols.  <dquo>Better</dquo> and more significant
  holy symbols offer a better bonus to Faith magic casting:
      </text>
  
  
      <figure>
        <table>
          <head>
            <cell width="2em">Bonus</cell>
            <cell width="4.5in">Description</cell>
            <cell width="1.5in">Cost</cell>
          </head>
          <row>
            <cell>-1</cell>
            <cell>A gesture made by the Faithful, or a crude marking (such as a cross hastily drawn on a parchment)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>0</cell>
            <cell>An inexpensive <dquo>trinket</dquo> type holy symbol, or a common copy of a holy book / scripture.  Generally mass-produced.  Might be given away at a particular church, or might be available for purchase.  Also a holy symbol made by a marginally skilled craftsman or apprentice.  Example: prayer beads, a simple carved wooden cross, a mass-printed holy book, etc.  Cost:  $5 or more.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>An unusually high quality trinket made by a good craftsman (such as a fine gold crucifix necklace).  Or, a good quality weapon bearing religious inscription and symbols. Or, an item from a particular church which is not available to the general public (such as the robes of an ordained priest), or a fine quality holy book.</cell>
            <cell>Cost:  At least $500 plus the cost of the <dquo>base item</dquo></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>2</cell>
            <cell>A trinket or jewelry made by a master craftsman and of fine pedigree and history.  Or, a weapon or other object of superior quality with appropriate engravings and blessings.</cell>
            <cell>Cost: at least $5000 plus the base cost of the item.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>3</cell>
            <cell>An artifact or relic of religious significance, generally has a famous history within the church, or a Legendary quality weapon blessed by a member of the church with Faith: 7 or higher.</cell>
            <cell>Cost: $1,000,000 or more.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>An artifact or relic of tremendous religious significance.  Items like this are literally worshipped in the particular religion.  There will only be a handful of items like this in existence for any one religion at any given time (if any at all).  Examples:  Spear of Destiny, Holy Grail, piece of the true cross, skull of a major saint.</cell>
            <cell>Cost: priceless.</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <caption>Bonuses provided by a <holy-symbol /></caption>
      </figure>
  
      <text>
  Anytime a Faith magic caster has to make a magic-related roll
  (<dquo>Magical Control</dquo> roll, or a strike roll associated with a magical
  spell, etc), use the caster<squo />s Faith skill.  Whatever holy symbol that
  the caster has is then applied as a bonus to that roll.
      </text>
  
    </section><!-- /Religious and Faith Magic -->
  
    <section><!-- Martial Magic / Super Power Combat -->
      <title>Martial Magic / Super Power Combat</title>
  
      <text>
  Martial magic is the ability to perform supernatural <dquo>attacks</dquo> in
  conjunction with normal combat, such as fist fighting, martial arts,
  or combat with weapons.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Martial Magic always works in conjunction with some kind of verbal or
  somatic component.  This means that the fighter must perform a
  particular combat form (kata), stance, or must shout a particular
  phrase in order to use the ability.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Martial magic is always taught from master to student.  It is a
  closely guarded secret of warrior secret societies, secluded martial
  arts temples, or families with great fighting traditions.  Once a
  warrior masters the traditional (non-supernatural) combat arts, he may
  be taught martial magic.  Since martial magic is highly dependent on
  particular combat forms and stances, it is nearly impossible to learn
  on one<squo />s own or from a book.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Magical effects that ordinarily require touch do so for the martial
  magician as well.  This is normally done by striking the target with
  some kind of melee attack.  The character does not have to deal damage
  per se (if the target is wearing armor) but he must connect with a
  solid blow.  The magical energy (effect) is transferred through the
  blow.  Martial magic users may choose to use a normal touch instead.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Magical effects that are projectile in nature (such as
  <fireball />) and normally require a strike roll must be used in
  conjunction with a missile or projectile weapon of some kind (thrown
  weapon, arrow, dart, or even a bullet).
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Magical effects that are autotargeting when performed by a spellcaster
  (such as <lightning-bolt />) are no longer autotargeting.  The
  Super Power combatant must strike with any attack of his choice, which
  may be a ranged attack or a melee attack.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  The effects of a martial magic spell are in addition to those normally
  associated with a strike in combat.  If a martial artist punches a
  target and also performs the spell <Vampiric-Drain />, then the
  target will suffer normal damage from the Punch, as well as the damage
  and effects from <Vampiric-Drain />.  Likewise, if a martial
  magician shoots a target with an arrow in conjunction with
  <Energy-Blast />, then both the arrow and <Energy-Blast /> deal
  damage.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Martial magic works similar to spellcasting, with the following notes:
      </text>
  
      <itemize-list>
        <item> MP are consumed just like spellcasting</item>
        <item> Touch spells require a successful strike roll in combat</item>
        <item> Ranged spells require a missile weapon of some kind</item>
        <item> Auto-target spells are now <dquo>cast</dquo> by a WIL check of the user</item>
        <item> Martial Magic spells are learned/purchased just like normal Spells</item>
        <item> Martial Magic users must have at least 1 level in <mysticism /></item>
      </itemize-list>
  
      <text>
  Rather than purchasing the <spellcasting /> skill, a Super Power
  Fighter adds together his skill level of <Martial-Arts /> and
  <mysticism />.  The total is considered the skill level of
  <dquo>Martial Magic</dquo>
      </text>
  
    </section><!-- /Martial Magic / Super Power Combat -->
  
    <section><!-- Mysticism / Psionics -->
      <title>Mysticism / Psionics</title>
  
      <text>
  Psionics is the ability to perform magic or supernatural acts by pure
  force of will.  No incantations, materials, or special preparation is
  required.  A character that can perform these feats is called a
  Mystic.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Whereas most magic users have trained to develop their abilities,
  Mystic characters are more often <dquo>gifted</dquo> with magical abilities.
  Quite often these powers manifest themselves as a result of a
  traumatic event, such as a near-fatal accident, that is experienced by
  the character.  They may also be abilities that are passed down
  through a particular family<mdash />in which case the character is simply
  born with his unique powers.  Mystic characters have an innate ability
  to perform their abilities<mdash />which are completely independent of any
  kind of structured <dquo>method</dquo> or <dquo>technique</dquo>.  While mystic
  characters might join magical societies they cannot <dquo>learn</dquo> or
  <dquo>teach</dquo> mystic techniques to others.  Psionic abilities are
  something that a mystic discovers herself.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Mystic rules:
      </text>
  
      <itemize-list>
        <item> MP are consumed just like spellcasting</item>
        <item> No verbal, somatic, or material components are required.  A
    mystic can be totally still and silent and can sill use his
    abilities, though the time required to perform (use) a mystic
    ability is exactly the same as standard spellcasting.</item>
        <item> Spells are purchased from the spell list at will.  There is no
    need to follow a particular category.  The only restriction is that
    learned spells must be no higher level than the character<squo />s
    <mysticism /> skill.</item>
        <item> Mystics always use the WIL attribute for magic-related rolls,
    such as <Magical-Control />, regardless of the normal attribute
    that would be used for that roll.</item>
      </itemize-list>
  
    </section><!-- /Mysticism / Psionics -->
  
    <section><!-- Beast Magic (summoning) -->
      <title>Beast Magic (summoning)</title>
  
      <text>
  Beast Magic is a unique magic school.  It is the art of summoning
  creatures to aid their master.  Any magic user (spellcasting, ritual,
  etc.) may purchase summoning spells as normal.  However, a spellcaster
  that specializes in Beast Magic (and has no other magical aptitudes)
  may purchase summoning spells as if they are one rank lower than
  normal.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  There are five basic summoning spells:
      </text>
  
      <description-list>
  <item><description>Gate</description> allows the summoner to call forth a creature that appears
    somewhere near the caster.  The location of appearance must be
    within direct line of sight of the caster, and no more than 30 feet
    away.  Once the creature appears, it is free to do whatever it wants
    based on its own free will<mdash />the caster simply transports it to a
    new location.  It will return to its original location after 3D6
    rounds.</item>
  
  <item><description>Summon</description> allows the summoner to call forth a creature near the
    caster (like Gate).  This creature is bound to follow SIMPLE
    directives given by the caster.  The creature will not act in a
    hostile manner towards the caster.  If a summoner casts another
    Summon spell while another one is currently active, he must make a
    Magical Control roll.  Failure means that the new spell fails and
    the first expires immediately.</item>
  
  <item><description>Pact</description> allows the caster to form a complex bond with a creature,
    making that creature his Familiar.  The caster must first find a
    creature to use pact with<mdash />such as summoning the creature by gate
    or summon) The caster may <dquo>control</dquo> the creature in a manner
    similar to summon.  This is permanent and lasts until either the
    caster or the Familiar is slain.  If the caster casts Pact a while
    he already has a Familiar, the original spell expires and the caster
    suffers 1D6+3 U.  While active, the Familar is aware of what happens
    to the caster, and vice versa.  A basic empathic link exists between
    the creature and the caster.  The caster may make a Magical Control
    check in order to <dquo>listen in</dquo> on any of the familiar<squo />s senses at
    any point in time.</item>
  
  <item><description>Control</description> is very similar to summon except that the caster has
    exacting and specific control over the creature(s) summoned.  The
    caster can literally operate the creature(s) as though by <dquo>remote
    control</dquo>.  While Control is active, the summoner is responsible for
    literally every action made by the summoned creature<mdash />it has no
    will of its own.</item>
  
  <item><description>Transform</description> is a powerful technique in which the caster takes the
    form of the creature summoned.  The caster literally becomes the
    creature in question, but retains his own mental state and skills in
    addition to the skills of the summoned creature.  All physical
    attributes (STR, DEX, BLD) of the summoned creature replace those of
    the character, but the character retains his own mental attributes
    (INT, WIS, WIL, CHA).  This effect lasts 4x 1D4 turns.  It cannot be
    ended at will.  The transformation requires three actions to
    complete.  When the spell expires, the caster will be very tired,
    and will suffer the effects of slow, loosing 1 action per turn for
    1D4+1 turns.</item>
      </description-list>
      
      <text>
        These summon spells are used in conjunction with whatever
    creature <dquo>spells</dquo> a summoner knows.  In order to learn a creature
    spell, the Summoner must have encountered such a creature.  The rank
    of example creatures is shown below.  For others, see the Beastiary
    section.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  These summon spells are used in conjunction with whatever creature
  <dquo>spells</dquo> a summoner knows.  In order to learn a creature spell, the
  Summoner must have encountered such a creature.  The rank of example
  creatures is shown below.  For others, see the Beastiary section.
      </text>
  
      <figure>
        <table>
          <head>
            <cell align="center">Rank</cell>
            <cell width="4.5in">Spell (choose specifically)</cell>
          </head>
          <row>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>Insects, songbirds, rats, mice, other small rodents, frogs/toads, salamanders, misc. other small reptiles or amphibians.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>2</cell>
            <cell>Dogs, cats, exotic small animals, larger birds (crow, raven, owl, etc.), common snakes.  Raccoon, possum, etc.  Bats, small flying/gliding mammals.  Wallaby.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>3</cell>
            <cell>Very large dogs, Cow, goat, sheep, deer, antelope.  Large predatory birds (hawk, eagle), large reptiles (small crocodile, monitor lizard, large snake).  Lesser monkeys.  Lynx, Kangaroo</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>Crocodile, Horse, Bull.  Exotic 4-legged animals.  Large constricting snakes.  Apes.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>5</cell>
            <cell>Hippo, Cape buffalo, Lion, Black Bear</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>Elephant, Rhinocerous, Grizzly or Polar bear.  Mammoth</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <caption>Summonable animals by Rank</caption>
      </figure>
  
      <text>
  For generic animals follow the table above.  For very specific,
  exotic, or rare animals jump to the next higher rank.  (Example:
  Summon Frog: rank 1.  Summon Brazilian Poison-dart frog: rank 2.)
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Whenever a summoning spell is cast the Summoner must make a Magical
  Control skill check.  The negative to the roll is the total summoning
  rank(s) of the creatures to be summoned.  A summoner can attempt to
  summon multiple of the same creature simultaneously, but not a mixture
  of different creatures.  The caster has a bonus to this check based on
  what <dquo>Beast Lore</dquo> skills he knows.
      </text>
  
    </section><!-- /Beast Magic (summoning) -->
  
    <section><!-- Magic-Related Skill Summary -->
      <title>Magic-Related Skill Summary</title>
  
      <itemize-list>
        <item> Spellcasting gives additional LVL<sup>2</sup> <times /> WIS MP.  This is the
    governing skill for learning Invocation spells.</item>
        <item> Magical Studies is the academic study of magic and how it works.
    It also gives the player the ability to identify magical items or
    effects (a simple skill test), and to determine what a particular
    magical item/effect does (GM determines difficulty of the test). It
    also conveys the ability to read and write magical script.  This
    skill does not convey the ability to use magic; this skill does not
    provide MP.</item>
        <item> Magical Control gives additional (LVL<sup>2</sup><times />WIL)<times />2 MP, and is used
    to strike with and to control the effects of some spells.  While
    this skill is not required for magic use, it is commonly used.</item>
        <item> Mysticism gives an additional (LVL<sup>3</sup><times />WIS) MP.  This is the
    governing skill for learning Mystic / Psionic spells.</item>
        <item> Faith is not technically a magic skill.  However, it is used for
    Faith magic, and provides (LVL<sup>2</sup><times />WIL<times />1.5) MP.  Faith only
    provides MP to those characters who actually know Faith magic
    spells.  If a non-faith spellcaster has this skill (For example, a
    Wizard that also happens to be religious) then it does NOT provide
    any MP.</item>
        <item> Ritual Magic is used for Ritual Magic spells.  No character can
    learn a ritual spell with a higher rank than her level of Ritual
    Magic.  This skill does not provide MP.</item>
      </itemize-list>
  
      <text>
  There exist different types or categories of magic.  The different
  types of magic are:
      </text>
  
      <description-list>
        <item><description>Air</description> Air magic is varied and effective for combat mages.  The
    lower rank spells are a mixture between utility types and damaging
    spells.  The higher level combat spells are quite powerful.  Air
    magic contains Lightning spells, which have wildly varying damage
    potential.</item>
  
        <item><description>Life</description> Life magic is capable of curing the wounded, healing the
    sick, and even inflicting horrible diseases upon your opponents.  It
    is a favorite of religious orders, either for good or evil.  Most
    combat magic in this category is limited because the spells require
    touch to cast.  Some spells are capable of dealing a great deal of
    damage, but usually over a period of time.  Sufficiently advanced
    mages who practice life magic can raise the dead or kill the living
    with a simple gesture.</item>
  
        <item><description>Spiritual</description> Magic of the Spiritual category is uncommon at best.
    With relatively few low-rank spells it is usually reserved to
    advanced practitioners of magic.  However, it has some unique spells
    that make it very effective.  Spiritual magic is particularly well
    suited for combating demons or spirits.  Higher level mages can lay
    waste to legions of their enemies with single spell.</item>
  
        <item><description>Light</description> With few exceptions, Light magic is a utility category.
    It can be used to illuminate dark passages beneath the earth or
    deceive with illusion and tricks.  Light magic has many useful
    spells, many of which are available at low or middle levels.  It is
    a very useful type of magic for the rogue or healer-type character
    who wants to be useful but doesn<squo />t want to fight.  A few high level
    light spells can deal excellent damage, but only at a steep MP cost.</item>
  
        <item><description>Physical</description> Physical magic is an excellent choice for
    <dquo>dual-classed</dquo> characters that practice magic and also fight in
    melee combat.  At lower and middle levels, physical magic allows one
    to improve the abilities of others, and to manipulate the physical
    world with magic.  He can also repair broken weapons or mend
    machines.  At higher levels the school offers very effective
    defensive spells and the highly effective gravity-based offensive
    magic, which always deals solid damage.</item>
  
        <item><description>Arcane</description> Arcane magic has no direct offensive capability; this
    would appear to be a weak form of magic that has little use for an
    adventurer.  However, the ability of arcane magic to support,
    enhance, and empower the caster or his allies is unmatched.  It is
    excellent when paired with other magic of a more offensive nature.</item>
  
        <item><description>Fire</description> Fire magic is a traditional offensive type of magic.  It<squo />s
    spells deal high damage and are without equal for causing
    large-scale destruction.  They are also quite mana-efficient.
    However, fire magic is the easiest of all <dquo>supernatural</dquo> attacks
    to defend against.  Fire magic is also noisy, flashy, and very
    intimidating to one<squo />s opponents.  Unfortunatley, this makes it
    nearly impossible to use in a stealthy manner.</item>
  
        <item><description>Earth</description> Earth magic is a varied school that combines defensive
    and offensive spells.  While neither type of spell is the most
    powerful available, they are not to be underestimated.  Earth magic
    has a number of very useful utility spells.</item>
  
        <item><description>Water</description> At lower levels, water magic is fairly weak, though it
    does combine both offensive and defensive spells.  Middle ranks
    offer effective protection and more effective combat spells.
    Higher-level water magic is legendary in effectiveness and is very
    powerful, Though many of the offensive spells have a long casting
    time, they are nearly impossible to defend against.</item>
      </description-list>
  
    </section><!-- /Magic-Related Skill Summary -->
  
  </section><!-- /Types of Magic -->
  
  <section><!-- General Notes -->
    <title>General notes</title>
  
    <text>
  Most spells automatically succeed (there is no skill check necessary,
  except for Faith Magic).  Once cast, it is possible for some spells to
  miss their target however.  For these spells, the player must make a
  skill test using MAGICAL CONTROL (or <faith />) to determine if the
  strike is successful.  See the spell listing for what spells are
  auto-targeting and which aren<squo />t.
    </text>
  
    <text>
  If the player is interrupted while spell casting (e.g. takes damage,
  gets knocked around, etc.), he must make a skill check (Magical
  Control).  If he fails the check, the spell fails, but the MP are not
  lost.  <note>The caster may not speak while spellcasting, but may
  move around, dodge, and perform very simple physical activities.</note>
    </text>
  
    <text>
  A spell always takes effect at the end of the casting period.  The MP
  are consumed at the exact instant that the spell takes effect.
    </text>
  
    <text>
  A casting time of zero (0) means that the caster may cast the spell
  anytime, even in response to something (e.g. getting shot
  at), or having no actions remaining at the time.  Such spells require
  no command words, components, or gesturing of any kind.
    </text>
  
    <text>
  Note that a Faith magic caster must always make a Faith roll in order
  to cast any magical spell.
    </text>
  
    <section><!-- Magic Points -->
      <title>Magic Points (MP)</title>
  
      <text>
  Any character has innate MP; magic related skills will give additional MP.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  MP are consumed whenever spells are cast.  They are recovered
  according to the following chart:
      </text>
  
      <figure>
        <table>
          <head>
            <cell align="right" />
            <cell align="left" />
          </head>
          <row>
            <cell>Strenuous Activity:</cell><cell>0 per hour</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Normal Activity:</cell><cell>5 per hour</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Restful Activity:</cell><cell>10 per hour</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Sleeping:</cell><cell>20 per hour</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Meditation or prayer:</cell><cell>20 per hour</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <caption>Mana Point replacement per hour.</caption>
      </figure>
  
    </section><!-- /Magic Points -->
  
    <section><!-- Magical Tools -->
      <title>Magical <dquo>Tools</dquo>: Books, Scrolls, and Potions</title>
  
      <text>
  There exist three different kinds of magic-related books.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Type 1 is a volume that contains detailed information on how to cast a
  particular spell (or spells).  Books of this type are always written
  in magical script.  Anyone with the Magical Studies skill can read and
  understand this kind of book.  However, only those with Spellcasting
  can make real use of the contents.  A Spellcasting character can
  easily learn new spells from a book of this type.  Books of this type
  are very valuable.  The cost of a spell book like this is equal to the
  <dquo>Book</dquo> price column of the magic table.  If the book contains
  multiple spells, then its value is equal to the sum of the costs for
  each spell contained.  Generally speaking, books of this type only
  contain multiple spells when they are compendia of low-level spells in
  a given school of magic.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Type 2 is a volume that describes how to perform a particular spell in
  ritual format.  Books of this type might be written in any language,
  and are generally not written in magical script.  If a Ritual magic
  using character can read a book of this type, it is something like a
  cookbook for a particular ritual spell.  The character could keep the
  book as a reference or could use it to learn the ritual described.
  Ritual spell manuals are worth approximately one-quarter the cost of a
  Type 1 book.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Type 3 is a book that describes other forms of magic.  Since Faith
  magic, Martial Magic, and Mysticism are dependant on the individual
  <dquo>casting</dquo> the spell and not on some external <dquo>formula</dquo> or
  <dquo>recipe</dquo>, it is essentially impossible to truly document how to
  perform a given spell with nothing more than a book.  These books are
  of interest to sages and scholars who are interested in arcane
  subjects.  However, they are little more than a curiosity to actual
  practitioners of magic.  Given enough books of this type it is
  possible for a sufficiently advanced magical practitioner to figure
  out a new spell or technique, but it is no guarantee.  Books of this
  type are worth approximatley one-tenth of the listed price, depending
  on the exact subject matter contained within the volume.  They may be
  written in any language.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  Magical potions or scrolls are single-use magic spells.  Anybody can
  use a potion or scroll<mdash />whether they know anything about magic or
  not.  Spells that affect the caster or a willing recipient are
  potions.  Drinking the potion causes the spell to take effect.  Other
  spells take the form of scrolls.  Reading the scroll aloud causes the
  spell to take effect.  Both scrolls and potions are single-use only.
  Potions can be drunk in one action.  Scrolls ALWAYS take 3 actions to
  use regardless of the spell.
      </text>
  
      <text>
  A person with Magical Studies can create Books, Scrolls, and Potions
  of any spell he/she knows.  Producing such works is a long and
  expensive process:
      </text>
  
      <description-list>
        <item><description>Books</description> Requires a number of days equal to twice the rank of the
    spell squared to create.  No MP are required, but special precious
    inks and paper are required.  These materials cost approximately
    half the value of the book.</item>
  
        <item><description>Scrolls/Potions</description> Require LVL<sup>2</sup> hours to create.  They require
    MP equal to a normal casting of the spell to be expended, and
    require precious materials valued at not less than three-quarters
    the value of the finished item.  A ritualist may prepare a potion in
    half that time.</item>
      </description-list>
  
    </section><!-- /Magical Tools -->
  
    <section><!-- Magical Miscellany -->
      <title>Magic Terminology &amp; Misc.</title>
  
      <description-list>
        <item><description>Black</description> spells are those associated with evil, death energy, and
    demonic influence.  While they are not necissiarily evil, they are
    generally indescriminate in their targets.  Black spells never
    affect demons, undead, or targets that are not living, such as
    ghosts or robots.</item>
  
        <item><description>White</description> spells are those that are comprised of life energy.  They
    are technically not <dquo>good</dquo> aligned, though they are a favorite of
    <dquo>good</dquo> religious orders.  White spells that cause damage only
    affect demons, undead, and spirits.</item>
  
        <item><description>Auto</description> spells are those that are automatically targeting.  That
    means that once cast the spell will never miss or malfunction.
    However, in order to cast an auto-targeting spell, the caster must
    be able to clearly see and identify his target.</item>
      </description-list>
      
    </section><!-- /Magical Miscellany -->
  
  </section><!-- /General Notes -->


  </chapter><!-- /S Magic -->
  <chapter><!-- S Martial Arts -->
    <title>Martial Arts</title>

    <text>
The governing skill for <martial-arts /> is the Academic Skill,
<martial-arts />, which is rank 2.  All combat skills fall under
the <ae />gis of <martial-arts />. This means that a character engages in
combat<mdash />whether or not they have any facility in Martial
  Arts<mdash />they must still engage as a Martial Artist. For instance,
the Academic skill Hunting covers many areas (ambuscade, rifle
or bow shooting, skinning, stalking etc.), however these skills are
related to a stress-free environment. <combat />, on the other hand, is a
high-stress environment requiring special training for weapons. Those
skills considered useful for hunting have little use in a combat
arena<mdash />and may even be a detriment.
    </text>

    <section><!-- Rules -->
      <title>Rules</title>

      <text>
<martial-arts /> covers the use of all weapons (ranged, melee,
ultratech, mecha, et al.), in addition to hand-to-hand (HtH) combat,
and the set of specialized skills that are associated with the
<martial-arts /> governing skill.  The maximum level that any
character may have in any <martial-arts /> skill is less than or equal to
his level in <martial-arts />, i.e. if he has 3 Levels in <martial-arts />,
then all of his <martial-arts /> skills must be Level 3 or less.  The
basic Martial Art skill confers upon the martial artist the ability to
purchase the different skills listed in this section.
      </text>

      <text>
For each level the martial artist has in <martial-arts /> they may choose
one <martial-arts /> skill; for this skill, any time the martial artist
would have to roll the skill, they get an extra die to do so. A
skill may only be chosen
Level-in-<martial-arts />/2 times (the Lvl in
<martial-arts />, divided by two, rounded-down).
      </text>


      <example>
        <title>Kim improves his Nyrkkeily</title>
        <text>
Kim NG<cedilla>o</cedilla>c G<vcap>o</vcap>ay is an
  expert in Norse Boxing (Nyrkkeily), he chooses, when he gets his
  first level in <martial-arts />, he also buys a level in <dquo>Punch/Kick;</dquo>
  in particular, he also assigns his level-bonus to <dquo>Punch/Kick.</dquo>
  This means when he rolls to strike with a punch he rolls two
  dice and not one.
        </text>
      </example>

      <text>
After the <martial-arts /> skill has been purchased, skills from
the four basic categories may be acquired; the four categories
represent different capabilities that <martial-arts /> covers. The
five categories are <basic />, <combat />,
<defensive />, and <modifier />. The different categories
focus on different phases of <combat />, such that <combat />
skills are designed to aid the Martial Artist with movement,
entering/exiting combat, the knowledge of combat, deployment, and
higher-level strategy. <basic /> skills are involved in the
nitty-gritty (basic) postures and moves to actually strike
the opponent and inflict harm or
death. <defensive /> skills are designed to deflect,
dodge, and/or otherwise avoid the mishap of being harmed by another
pugilist. <modifier />s represent ways to modify
<basic /> skills.
      </text>

<description-list>
  <item><description><basic /></description> These skills represent <basic /> combat actions, such as
  punching or kicking, grappling, the use of weapons and other
  primitive attacks. <note>Only <basic /> attacks may be modified
    by a <modifier />.</note></item>
<item><description><combat /></description> These are the skills for being in, around, or preparing
  for combat. For example, knowledge of the terrain, etiquette, being
  prepared to move quickly and with assurance.</item>

<item><description><defensive /></description> These are the skills used for defending against an
  attack. They are the foil to the <basic /> skills.</item>

<item><description><modifier /></description> A <modifier /> is a skill used to modify a <basic /> attack. A
  <modifier /> changes the behaviour of a <basic /> attack; the <basic /> attack
  is now considered a <special /> attack of the same name with the
  <modifier /> as the adjective, for instance, if the Martial Artist is
  modifying a Punch with a Bash, then this is now a <special />
  attack, <dquo>Bashing Punch.</dquo> Since a modified <basic /> attack counts as a
  <special /> attack, it may not be further modified, as only <basic />
    attacks can be modified. There are certain <combat /> skills which
  enable the Martial Artist to consider certain specific combinations
  of <modifier />/<basic /> to be <basic /> attacks.</item>
</description-list>

      <note>A <modifier /> may not be used more than Lvl times per turn.</note>

      <example>
        <title>Candlestick modifies his punch</title>
        <text>
Candlestick has two
  levels in <martial-arts />; he has bought Punch at rank 3
  and level 3, and chosen it as his bonus; he also has Bash at
  level 1 and Feint at level 1. He is striking at the Giant
  Hispaniola Solenodon with a Bashing Punch. Because he is
  using Bash with his Punch his punch is now considered
  <dquo>special</dquo> and may not be further modified, even though he could
  still use his Feint this turn.
        </text>
      </example>

    </section><!-- /Rules -->
    
    <section><!-- Further Commentary -->
      <title>Further Commentary</title>

      <text>
You will note that there is no <dquo>chi</dquo> or <dquo>super-powers</dquo> in
<martial-arts />. In fact, the skills are deliberately kept
pedestrian<mdash />those possessed (or assumed to be possessed, if possible)
by the greatest <dquo>non-mystical</dquo> martial artists in the <squo>real world.</squo>
This is done deliberately to provide a clear separation between the
Supernormal<mdash />governed by Magic and Traits<mdash />and the
mundane reality of kicking, spitting, biting and hurting. If
you want to create a character that has truly jaw-dropping magical
abilities, like flying-through the air, or punching through a
fired-brick wall, bending steel, or leaping from roof-top-to-roof-top,
consider looking into the Magic and Traits section. In
Magic there a several categories that would benefit a Martial
Artist tremondously.
      </text>

      <section><!-- Advanced Martial Arts -->
        <title>Advanced Martial Arts</title>

        <text>
Also there are several para-skills which are tremondously
important to the dedicated Martial Artist: Kata,
Kung Fu, Waza, and Jitsu. These skills allow the
Martial Artist to transform his very <basic /> and <defensive /> attacks,
allowing him to perform prodigious feats: a Savage Feinting Death
Strike is only possible by using these skills.
        </text>

      </section><!-- /Advanced Martial Arts -->

    </section><!-- /Further Commentary -->

  </chapter><!-- /S Martial Arts -->
  <chapter><!-- S Mecha -->
    <title>Mecha</title>



  </chapter><!-- /S Mecha -->
  <chapter><!-- S Monsters -->
    <title>Monsters</title>

    <section><!-- Building a Monster -->
        <title>Building a Monster</title>

<text>Because of the wide variety of monstrous creatures available in
literature and fantasy, it is a somewhat futile task to attempt to
construct an exhaustive list. In addition, most GameMasters find that
while any particular monster is <emph>okay</emph>, the specific monster they
are envisioning is not available to them. The <emph>Monster</emph> section
is thus divided into three parts:</text>

<description-list>
    <item description="Base types">: the fundamental attributes, abilities, and <dquo>look</dquo>
  of the base creature</item>
    <item description="Templates">: modifications to the base-type that give the
  <dquo>flavor</dquo> of the monster</item>
    <item description="Examples">: that have been pre-generated</item>
</description-list>

        <section><!-- Base Types -->
            <title>Base Types</title>

<text>The base-types are the fundamental <dquo>type</dquo> or <dquo>look</dquo> of the
monster, they are:</text>

<description-list>
    <item description="Anthropoid"> essentially symmetric, bipedal, a head (and possible
  tail) etc.; a <emph>human</emph>-like monster
    </item>
    <item description="Bipedal"> covers non-anthropoid bipedal monsters, e.g. Duck,
  Chipmunk, Wyvern (two legs, two wings)
    </item>
    <item description="Quadruped"> typical of regular animals (mammals), e.g. Dog,
  Dragon (two legs, two arms, two wings)
    </item>
    <item description="Serpent"> tubes, e.g. Snail</item>
    <item description="Polymelic"> monsters with many legs or many arms, e.g. Angelus
  Guhendrian (torus with twelve wings, and an eyeball)
    </item>
    <item description="Amorphous"> blobs, pools, puddles, whiffs-of-smoke </item>
</description-list>

<text>When constructing a monster, the base-type must be chosen. Based on
the base-type, the size of the creature is chosen. The table below
lists the fundamental physical attributes of the various base-types.</text>

<figure>
    <table>
        <head>
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" border-right="1px black" />
        </head>
        <row>
            <cell span="12"><smallcapsbold>The fundamental base-types for monsters</smallcapsbold></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>Type</cell>
            <cell>1/2</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>2</cell>
            <cell>3</cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>5</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>10</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell>Anthropoid</cell>
            <cell span="11">
                Height: <math>Size<sup>2</sup><times /> 40 cm</math>
            </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell />
            <cell span="11">
                Weight: Height/2 kilograms
            </cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Str</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell><emph>n/a</emph></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Bld</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell><emph>n/a</emph></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Dex</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell>Bipedal</cell>
            <cell span="11">
                Height: <math>Size<sup>2</sup><times /> 35 cm</math>
            </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell />
            <cell span="11">Weight: Height/3 kilograms</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Str</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell><emph>n/a</emph></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Bld</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell><emph>n/a</emph></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Dex</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell>Quadruped</cell>
            <cell span="11">
                Length: <math>Size<sup>2</sup><times />35 cm</math>; Height: <math>1/3<times />Length</math>
            </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell />
            <cell span="11">Weight: Length/2 kilograms</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Str</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
            <cell>144</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Bld</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
            <cell>144</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Dex</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>6</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell>Serpent</cell>
            <cell span="11">
                Length: <math>Size<sup>2</sup><times />40 cm</math>; Height: <math>1/8<times />Length</math>
            </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell />
            <cell span="11">Weight: Height/2 kilograms</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Str</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
            <cell>144</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Bld</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell><emph>n/a</emph></cell>
            <cell><emph>n/a</emph></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Dex</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>8</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell>Polymelic</cell>
            <cell span="11">
                Size: <math>Size<sup>2</sup><times />30 cm</math>, in some dimension
            </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell />
            <cell span="11">Weight: Size/3 kilograms</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Str</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell><emph>n/a</emph></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Bld</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell><emph>n/a</emph></cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Dex</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>7</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell>Amorphous</cell>
            <cell span="11">
                Diameter: <math>Size<sup>2</sup><times />50 cm</math>
            </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell />
            <cell span="11">Weight: <math>Diameter<sup>3</sup></math> kilograms</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell span="12"><hrule /></cell></row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Str</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
            <cell>144</cell>
            <cell>169</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Bld</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
            <cell>36</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>64</cell>
            <cell>81</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
            <cell>121</cell>
            <cell>144</cell>
            <cell>169</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><smallcaps>Dex</smallcaps></cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>1</cell>
        </row>
    </table>
</figure>

        </section><!-- /Base Types -->

        <section><!-- Adding a Template -->
            <title>Adding a Template</title>

<text>There are several important items missing from the
<emph>base-type</emph>. These are covered by <emph>Monstrous Templates</emph>
which add things such as <emph>mental attributes</emph> (and <smallcaps>Cha</smallcaps>!),
<emph>special abilities</emph>, and a description of the monster, including
any relavent interaction statistics, such as combat, elocution etc.</text>


        </section><!-- /Adding a Template -->
    </section><!-- /Building a Monster -->
    
    <section><!-- Monsters -->
      <title>Monsters</title>
      <reference hrid="Content/Monsters" />
    </section><!-- /Monsters -->

  </chapter><!-- /S Monsters -->
  <chapter><!-- S Traits -->
    <title>Traits</title>

<text>Traits are supernatural (supernormal or paranormal) capabilities. They
are differentiated from <magic /> because they are singular in
nature. For instance, a trait could be a specific power that a monster
has, a specific power of a SuperHero. It can be the result of means
magical, chemical, mutation, or some future technology.</text>

<text>The important part is that the power occurs singularly and
uniquely and is not part of some larger <dquo>system,</dquo>
i.e. <magic />. <traits /> are generally bought at only one
level, but can be purchased at higher levels, if it is pertinent. If a
<traits /> needs <dquo>points</dquo> to power it, these are taken from the
character's Mana Points.</text>

<text>Since many traits overlap magical spells, there is a specific trait
designed for using abilities to some specific spell, this trait is
called <spell-ability />.</text>
    
    
    <section><!-- Traits -->
      <title>Traits</title>
      <reference hrid="Content/Traits" />
    </section><!-- /Traits -->

  </chapter><!-- /S Traits -->
</part>
</arpg>