
    <category name="Content/Monsters">
      <default name="">
        <field name="Name"  title="yes"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
      </default>
      <datum name="Allip">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Allip</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Takes no damage from non-magical attacks. Immune to psionics.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR:<notappl/>DEX: 12 BLD: 10 INT: 11 WIS: 11 WIL: 11 CHA: 8 HP: 30 Actions: 3 P/S/C: none Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Touch of Madness: Permenantly drains 1 WIL from the target per hit. Requires Touch.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Properly speaking, an Allip is a special kind of Undead or Spirit. An Allip is born whenever a person is deeply wronged by some tragic act and is thereby driven to madness and suicide. The body dies while the person's soul continues to live as a ghostly being. An Allip has the attributes of whatever the human had before his suicide. They are truly insane and are driven by madness and the overwhelming desire for revenge. The only desire of an Allip is to avenge itself by tormenting the person or persons responsible for his suicide. When the person(s) responisible die, an Allip vanishes into nothing. Moving requires intense concentation, and therefore an Allip cannot move very quickly.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Babau">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Babau</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Dodge while grappling (3 dice) Regenerate 15 HP/turn</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Vulnerable to fire (1.5x damage) 100 HP Size: 1 Actions: 3 plus 1 move Attack/Parry: 6-8 (+3 vs size-2 targets) Dodge: 5-8 (or 3-8 when grappling) Natural Armor: 5/5/5 Base Armor: 10</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Slap with limb: limb stetches into tentacle-like whip. Deals <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><rOff>+</rOff><raw>15</raw><kind>C</kind></roll> and scores an automatic grapple Energy drain: Requires a grapple first. Deals <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>5</raw><kind>U</kind></roll> with automatic success.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Appearance: A babau is a constructed creature, similar to a golem. As such they vary in exact appearance. However, all babaus resemble some other creature from which they are made<ndash/>most commonly an infant of any humanoid race<ndash/>though they could be made from any living creature. A babau looks like the creature that it was made from, with the following features: they are always naked and carry no equipment or weapons, they are perfectly pitch black, and their body lacks much of the detail of the original creature<ndash/>most delicate or &quot;sharp&quot; features are smoothed over. Babaus have no eyes or ears or toes<ndash/>they have only the tinest of bumps where these features once were. Their fingers are small nubs, and their mouth is a tiny wrinkle. Habits: Babaus are constructs and as such, they do whatever their creator has &quot;programmed&quot; them do to. The programming of a Babau is set during their creation, and typically includes such activities as guarding a certain area or performing menial labor. Becasue the complexity of a babau's programming is directly related to the learning ability of the original creature, the most common babau is made from an infant or young child of an intelligent race (such as human). If a babau is made from an animal, it is only suitable for the most basic of menial tasks. Combat: Babaus can be effective combatants due to their impressive strength, resiliance, and unique attacks. However, their combat strategy is preprogrammed, and such they never deviate in their behavior. This behavior is set by their programming, and thus it varies depending on their programmer's wishes. Generally their attack strategy is to strike and grapple an opponent using their limb-tentacles. Once they have secured a grapple, they use their energy drain attack as often as possible. They typically are programmed to flee and regenerate if they are seriously wounded. If a Babau is hit by a slashing weapon that deals more than 5 damage, the babau splits into two halves. Each is the size of the original babau. One half sustains whatever damage was dealt by the blow. The other one has full HP. Example: Eric attacks a Babau with a short sword, and rolls 14 damage. After deducting the Babau's natural armor, the damage sustained is 9 S. Since this is more than 5 damage, the Babau splits in two. One half sustains that 9 damage. The other half is at full HP.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Basilisk">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Basilisk</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Once per turn the basilisk can turn an opponent to stone with just a gaze. This power does not work if the target is COMPLETELY enclosed, no eyeslits in armor, NOTHING. The basilisk must have a line of sight with the target.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 13 DEX: 14 BLD: 13 INT: 3 WIS: 5 WIL: 10 CHA: 2 HP: 60 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 15/14/11 Size: 6', 10' from snout to tail Dice: Strike: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> ; Claws: <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns></roll> ; Spines: anyone touching the spines will take <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>P</kind></roll> and be poisoned for <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> turns, taking <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> damage a turn.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A basilisk is a large lizard-like creature that is about ten feet long when fully grown. It has a stout, thick body and a short, heavy tail. It weighs about 400 pounds. The creature has six powerful legs and a large head with strong jaws. Basilisks eat just about anything, including stone. The basilisk is covered with armored scales that are colored similar to it's habitat. Woodland basilisks are green, scrubland basilisks are a dull brown, etc. The Basilisk's scales are slick with poison, and a Basilisk's gaze can turn a living target to stone, instantly. Basilisks are of high animal intellience (predator) and are totally fearless. A basilisk is unafraid of death, and cannot be awed or surprised. They are solitary animals and fairly rare. They have a long life span.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Bugbear">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Bugbear</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Nightvision and exceptional hearing</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 16 DEX: 13 BLD: 20 INT: 10 WIS: 12 WIL: 13 CHA: 6 HP: 40 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 10/10/9 (4/4/4 natural) Size: 7' average Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 2; Block: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bte: <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> ; Claws: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> ; but will usually have an archaic weapon, prefers this type of attack</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Bugbears are humanoid creatures that are covered with coarse brown hair. They have dog-like ears and flattened noses, and otherwise appear human-like. They tend to be stronger and tougher than the average human (higher STR and BLD), but they are less intelligent (8 INT and WIS is common). They have a simple tribal society. They are capable of making tools and act much like primitive humans. They will often be found farming or hunting animals with simple weapons.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Cave Droll">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Cave Droll</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Dodge (stats above; is generally used as a last resport. Add +2 dice when jumping away to escape) Heat Sense (as a viper: can &quot;see&quot; warm-blooded targets even in complete darkness) Leap: 15 feet Ambidexterity: A Cave Droll, once latched in place, can attack with both knees and a bite in one action.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Beast 20 HP (Female) 28 HP (Male) Size: 1 Actions: 3 Attack: 4-13 (+2 vs. medium targets such as humans) Dodge: 2-16 Natural Armor: 4/6/2 (Male: 5/7/3) Base Armor: 0</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite (once per round only) Male: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll>  <and/>  <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> from poison for <roll><num>1</num><face>12</face><bns/></roll> turns Female: <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll>  <and/>  <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> from poison for <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> turns Knee Attack (male only) May attack with both knees simulaneously in one action with no penalty <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><rOff>+</rOff><raw>3</raw><kind>P</kind></roll> each Spit Poison (female only) up to 5 times per day, range of 15 feet. <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> for <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> turns</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Apperance: The Cave Droll is a small reptile with a bulbous, bean-shaped body. Its body is approximatley one foot long and is reminiscent of a fat, bloated, sack. It has two spindly forelimbs that have 3-fingered hands and opposeable thumbs. Its legs are narrow but are much more muscled than the forelimbs and have 3-toed feet. Both the fingers and toes feature sharp claws. The body is completely covered with scales; those on the back are keeled and are quite hard. Coloration is chiefly a dark olive green, with streaks of brown and other earth tones throughout. The sexes are different in appearance: Males have a bright orange or yellow patch on the throat area, directly below a large mouth lined with sharp teeth. The male's knees are capped with large horny spikes. Females lack the colored throat patch and the knee spikes. Their mouths are considerably smaller and have far smaller teeth. Habits: Cave Drolls are omnivorous predators. They lair in secluded areas, most commonly caves, but any dark location with shelter from the elements will do. Cave Drolls will eat any kind of animal or insect they can subdue and kill, and are also known to eat sweet fruits or berries when they can find them. Hunting tactics generally involve subduing prey with brute force. While Cave Drolls are not active man-hunters, they have been known to kill and eat humans that stray too near their lairs. Combat: The animalistic intelligence of Cave Drolls prevents them from utilizing strategy. They are not subtle combatants and have no concept of trickery or prioritizing targets. However, their hunting instincts are strong, and they are known to hide motionless while prey approaches, suddenly making an ambush attack to kill it. Individuals simply grab and devour small prey, such as rodents or lizards. Larger animals are swarmed and attacked en masse: Males attack prey by first jumping at it and latching on with their claws. Then, they repeatedly pummel it with repeated blows from their spiked knees, and deliver their poison bite. Females keep their distance from prey, surround it, and spit poison globs.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Cave Horror">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Cave Horror</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Low-light vision Spider Climb ability Leap: 30 feet</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Monster 160 HP Size: 3 Actions: 3 Attack: 4-15 Leg 3-15 Bite Parry: 4-15 Natural Armor: 15/10/5 body, 30/20/10 limbs Base Armor: 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>5</raw><kind>S</kind></roll> Leg Claws <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>3</raw><kind>S</kind></roll> Slam (after leaping) <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>10</raw><kind>C</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Apperance: The Cave Horror, also known as the &quot;Great Eatler&quot;, resembles an enormous beetle. The body is approximatley four feet long, three feet wide, and two feet thick. It is covered in a hard, shiny, black carapace. Its head is the size of a basketball and has two large compound eyes and large, sickle-like manibles as prominent features. The creature has four legs, each of which is nearly twenty feet long fully extended, but are usually carried in a peaked arrangement with the feet close to the body. Each foot is tipped with two wicked claws. It's appear slender and delicate, but the chitonous covering is extremely hard. It's limbs have the strength of iron bars. Habits: Though it appears to be a gigantic insect, the Great Eatler is actually a hateful monster. It is cunning, patient, and greedy to the extreme. Cave Horrors build their lairs deep in caves or similar areas, keeping well hidden from likely disturbance. When the mood suits it<ndash/>frequently<ndash/>or when disturbed, the beast awakes and looks for potential prey. The Cave Horror uses its exceptional perception skills to track and locate its chosen target. It observes its target(s) for some time, before deciding when and how to attack. It often times strikes from the darkness or hiding (often on the celing), surging forth to attack the victim and then retreating to plan a future attack. Cave Horrors do not covet treasure specifically, but generally accumulate it due to their long lifespan and propensity to attack sentient prey. Combat: The Cave Horror is an intelligent combatant. It follows and observes targets before beginning combat with a suprise attack. It may make use of ambushes or tricks in order to gain the upper hand<ndash/>or simply to confuse, distract, or block of its prey's escape route. When actually fighting the Cave Horror relies on its claw attacks and its bite.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Centaur">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Centaur</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Running speed: 30 mph</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 15 DEX: 15 BLD: 13 INT: 12 WIS: 11 WIL: 12 CHA: 10 HP: 30 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 3/3/3 (can also wear armor) Size: 8' tall, 7' long Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 3; Block: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Hooves: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll> ; can also use any human weapons</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A centaur is a cross between a human and a horse. They have the body of a horse, but a human torso extends where the horse's neck and head would normally be. They are an intellgent, proud race, whose mental attributes average a 12. They have 4 legs like a horse, and have two human-like arms. Centaurs are peaceful and enjoy intellectual and athletic pursuits.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Chimera">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Chimera</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>The dragon's head can breath fire once per turn instead of biting dealing <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> damage. Can fly at 30 mph and run at 20 mph</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 18 DEX: 14 BLD: 20 INT: 10 WIS: 12 WIL: 15 CHA: 6 HP: 130 Actions:: * P/S/C: 20/20/20 Size: 10' long with an 8' tail Dice: Strike: 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Can make a total of 3 bites, 1 claw attack, and 1 tail attack per turn. Bite: <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns></roll> ; claw: <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> ; tail: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A chimera is a powerful monster that appears as a mix between several different animals. The front half of it's body is that of a Lion, and the back half is that of a goat. It has three heads: a goat, lion, and a serpent. It has a tail with bony spikes along it's length. It has a pair of bat-like wings atop its back. Each head can function indipentantly of the others, but the Lion head controls the body. All three heads can attack independently.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Cockatrice">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Cockatrice</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Once per turn the cockatrice can turn an opponent to stone with just a gaze. This power does not work if the target is COMPLETELY enclosed, no eyeslits in armor, NOTHING. The cockatrice must have a line of sight with the target.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 4 DEX: 14 BLD: 6 INT: 3 WIS: 5 WIL: 10 CHA: 2 HP: 25 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 2/3/2 Size: Turkey sized Dice: Strike: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>-</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> ; claws: <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A cockatrice is a grotesque bird-like creature that is about the size of a turkey. It is covered with tough, warty skin and it also has scales on some parts of it's body. Cockatrices eat only stone, and are found in groups of 6-10. They aren't particularly intelligent and spend their time looking for food (things to turn to stone and then eat) and sleeping. Cockatrices, like the Basilisk, have the ability to turn a target to stone with just a gaze. The bite of a cockatrice can also turn a target to stone.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Deviruchi">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Deviruchi</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Dodge (stats above) Skewer Reciprocal Attack with pitchfork only (see martial arts) Regenerate 2 HP/turn</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Demon (vulnerable to white magic, immune to fire) 32 HP Size: 1 Actions: 4 Attack/Parry: 4-13 (+2 vs. medium targets such as humans) Dodge: 3-16 Natural Armor: 3/4/2 Base Armor: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>&quot;poke&quot;: Tiny Pitchfork of Heat: <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><rOff>+</rOff><raw>1</raw><kind>P</kind></roll> and <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> from heat (but does not have fire effect) &quot;fire&quot;: Fire Fountain: Requires 3 actions to cast. This ritual requires at least 2 Deviruchi to participate in, which they do by simultaneously plunging their pitchforks into the ground. This causes an eruption of fire from the ground that affects a 10' diameter circle. Damage dealt is <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> Fire + <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> for each additional Deviruchi present beyond the first two. &quot;zap&quot;: Black Ray: This attack works like the spell Black Beam, except it is less powerful (damage dealt is <roll><num>1</num><face>12</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> and the damage received is <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> ). It can be &quot;cast&quot; only once per turn. &quot;bite&quot;: Bite: Deals <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>1</raw><kind>P</kind></roll>. If wounded, the target suffers an additional <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> from poison. The poison damage takes place the next turn, and only once.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Apperance: A small daemon standing approximatley 18&quot; in height. The body is round and plump, resembling a pillow. Coloration is almost entirely black; some specimens exhibit faint red spots or a red stripe along the back. Two tiny bat-wings grow from its back, but they are too small to be used for flight. Its arms are small, and usually carry an iron pitchfork approximatley 24&quot; in length. They usually do not speak, but are known for chattering in an excited manner when fighting or tormenting the wounded. Habits: Deviruchi are among the lowliest of daemons. As such, they are not particularly intelligent, though they are intensely curious and of the same mental capacity as a child. As they are physically and intellectually weak, their masters rarely attempt to give them significant responsibilities; rather they are simply dispersed in the world, spreading havoc and furthering all manner of evil. Deviruchi may therefore be found in nearly any location or climate, so long as humans or innocent beasts are present to torment. Combat: Deviruchi are small, fast-moving, and have numerous offensive capabilites. They are fairly dangerous 1-on-1, but are especially dangerous in groups. When a group of Deviruchi is encountered, all individuals generally swarm and attack the same opponent. However, they are easily distracted and may quickly shift from one opponent to the next for seemingly no reason. They rarely fight with any sort of organized strategy, however all Deviruchi relish combat and enjoy inflicting pain and suffering on any living thing. They are unlikely to run from a fight, though they do scatter and regroup when overwhelmed.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Dirge Worm">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Dirge Worm</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>poison resistance burrowing infravision tremorsense Paralyzing slime: touching slime or being constricted requires the victim to make a BLD check at -3. Failure drops the user to half STR. (pass= no effect)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Takes half damage form poison. 500 HP Size: 2 (25' long, but diminished size due to narrow body) Actions: 3 plus 1 move Attack: 7-6 (bite or stinger) Dodge: 5-6 Natural Armor: 10/15/30 Base Armor: 15</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite <roll><num>4</num><face>10</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>10</raw><kind>P</kind></roll> Stinger <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> , 20 AP and poision for <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> turns: <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll>  <and/>  <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> BLD Constrict (must bite first), 4x <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> Spell-like abilities: Darkness 1/turn Carpet of Adhesion or slipperyness at will Spider Climb 2/day Rock to Mud 2/day Create Portal 2/day Advanced Slow 2/day Negate 1/day Geo Transport 1/day</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Apperance: The dirge worm is a revolting and horrific monster which is constantly surrounded with the stench of decaying flesh. The creature's body resembles a bloated grub or worm, except it is twenty-five feet long and two feet in diameter. Its skin is a tough, transparent membrane which is coated in a yellowish slime. The skin is stretched tight around the creature's body, making it look like it might burst at any moment. The combination of the slime and the transparent skin makes a dirge worm appear to be a writhing tube of mutilated flesh<ndash/>when in fact it is a living creature. A Dirge Worm's head resembles a grotesquely oversized human head. It has no hair and is covered with the same transparent skin and slime of the body. The forehead is extended, the mouth exaggerated, and it has tiny black eyes. The creature has no lips, and thus its mouth<ndash/>full of jagged teeth<ndash/>is clearly visible. Dirge worms move like a snake and are capable of extreme speed. Habits: Dirge worms live underground. They lair in caves, old dungeons, sewers, abandoned mineshafts, and similar locations<ndash/>anywhere damp and dark with sufficient space to accomodate their size. Dirge worms eat dead, decaying flesh. To this end they attack large prey. They often lair near humanoid settlements, from which they raid livestock and people alike. They haul the dead back to their lair and leave the bodies to rot. Once the flesh is sufficienly putrid, the creature consumes it. Dirge worms are fond of eating minor undead, such as zombies, as they are &quot;instant&quot; sources of dead, decayed flesh. They are also attracted to graveyards, burial pits, or battlefields where they collect great quantities of corpses to feed their insatiable hunger. Dirge Worm slime is valued by Necromancers for use in fell ritals. Thus some powerful necromancers seek out dirge worms and even supply them with zombies and other hapless victims in order to have a source of slime readily available. Though they are powerful, Dirge Worms prefer not to fight directly. They use their abilities to hide and move in darkness to suprise and overwhelm prey. Combat: When &quot;hunting&quot; prey, the dirge worm waits for its target to pass close by. It then bursts forth from the ground or from a hiding spot in a nearby marshy area, to attack. Usually one bite is sufficent to kill a potential victim. If facing multiple targets it uses its spell-like abilities immedietly to gain an advantage early on, then fights with its teeth and stinger.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Doppleganger">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Doppleganger</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can completely imitate the physical characteristics of another creature. The doppleganger gets all physical attributes, HP, armor, and attacks. This can only be done after slaying the original creature.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 10 DEX: 8 BLD: 10 INT: 12 WIS: 13 WIL: 20 CHA: 8 HP: 20 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: none Immune to psionics Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 3; Dodge: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Assumes any attacks of copied creature</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A doppleganger is an unusual creature with the ability to assume the appearance and abilities of other living creatures. The doppleganger's true form (which is very rarely seen) is a short (4') grey-skinned humanoid with large, slanting, eyes. In it's true form a doppleganger is quite weak and is similar to a human child in ability. The doppleganger can, however, transform its body (permanently) into the body of any other living creature of size 1, 2, or 3. When it does this, it gains the attributes and abilities of whatever creature it <ldquo/>copied<rdquo/>. Note that in order for this transformation to be possible, the doppleganger must first have slain the creature to be copied.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Dragon">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Dragon</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A large winged reptile with a long neck and tail. Dragons have horned heads and a spiny ridge that runs along the back and down the tail. Dragons are very intelligent creatures and generally know a great deal of magic. They occur in various varieties and are generally rare creatures. The skin of a dragon, which is covered in fine armored scales, is very tough and is beautiful to look at. All dragons have some sort of breath weapon<mdash/>commonly this is fire, but it could be ice, poison, acid, etc. Dragons can fly at great speed and have powerful bodies.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Dragon - Mature">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Dragon - Mature</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly 70 mph. Has a breath weapon (acid, poison, ice, lightning, or fire) that deals <roll><num>8</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> damage. 1 &quot;free&quot; breath weapon attack can be made per turn.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 30 DEX: 22 BLD: 33 INT: 18 WIS: 20 WIL: 20 CHA: 16 HP: 1000 Actions:: 5 P/S/C: 40/40/40 Size: 50' from head to base of tail with a 30' tail Dice: Strike: 7; Dodge: 4; Block (with claws): 8</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>7</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> ; Claws: <roll><num>9</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns></roll> ; Tail: <roll><num>9</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll> ; Bat with wings: <roll><num>6</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll> and blows target back 20 feet.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A large lizard creature. Usually knows a great deal of magic, typically will know every spell of rank 6 or less, with 1500 MP. A dragon becomes fully mature around 600 years after birth.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Dragon - Old">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Dragon - Old</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly 60 mph. Has a breath weapon (acid, poison, ice, lightning, or fire) that deals <roll><num>12</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> damage. 1 &quot;free&quot; breath weapon attack can be made per turn.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 28 DEX: 16 BLD: 30 INT: 24 WIS: 26 WIL: 22 CHA: 18 HP: 800 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: 30/30/30 Size: 60' from head to base of tail with a 40' tail Dice: Strike: 5; Dodge: 4; Block (with claws): 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> ; Claws: <roll><num>6</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns></roll> ; Tail: <roll><num>11</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll> ; Bat with wings: <roll><num>6</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll> and blows target back 20 feet.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A large lizard creature. Usually knows a great deal of magic, typically will know every spell, with 4000 MP. A dragon becomes old around 3000 years after birth. Dragons have no known limited lifespan.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Dragon - Young">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Dragon - Young</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly 40 mph. Has a breath weapon (acid, poison, ice, lightning, or fire) that deals <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> damage. 1 &quot;free&quot; breath weapon attack can be made per turn.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 24 DEX: 18 BLD: 23 INT: 14 WIS: 16 WIL: 20 CHA: 14 HP: 300 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: 20/20/20 Size: 20' from head to base of tail with a 10' tail Dice: Strike: 5; Dodge: 4; Block (with claws): 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> ; Claws: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns></roll> ; Tail: <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll> ; Bat with wings: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll> and blows target back 20 feet.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A large lizard creature. Usually knows a great deal of magic, typically will know every spell of rank 4 or less, with 600 MP</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Dragonette">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Dragonette</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly 20 mph. Can breath fire or ice (choose one). Fire deals: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> ; ice deals <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> D. Can teleport once per turn up to 200' away.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 6 DEX: 14 BLD: 10 INT: 10 WIS: 12 WIL: 11 CHA: 18 HP: 20 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 4/4/4 Size: 3' from head to base of tail with a 2' tail Dice: Strike: 3; Dodge: 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> ; claws: <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Trainable. Very personable creatures, and will often play with people, and will take food from them as well. They are very prized as pets, but they are free-willed. If a dranette is held against it's will, it will attempt to escape asap.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Dragonling">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Dragonling</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly 30 mph. Can breath fire or ice (choose one). Fire deals: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> ; ice deals: <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> D.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 16 DEX: 16 BLD: 18 INT: 14 WIS: 12 WIL: 15 CHA: 12 HP: 60 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 16/16/16 Size: Human sized with 4' tail Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 3; Block: 4; Parry: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>P</kind></roll> ; Claws: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> ; Tail: <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns></roll> ; will usually use a one-handed weapon and prefers this method of attack.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Dragonlings aren't actually dragons, they just appear to be related. They are bipedal creatures with thick scales (usually golden) covering the body. It has a long tail with small spines along the spine. Will usually use human weaponry.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Dryad">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Dryad</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can run 30 mph. Can hide within its own tree. Beauty Lvl 4. Any creature that wishes to attack a dryad must make a wilpower check at -8 to do so.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 8 DEX: 14 BLD: 12 INT: 14 WIS: 14 WIL: 14 CHA: 12 HP: 24 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: none Size: Human sized Dice: Dodge: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>None</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>All dryads have a tree that is &quot;theirs&quot;, never travels more than a mile from it. If the tree dies, the dryad dies, and vice versa. Dyads will occasionally help travelers by offering fruit and healing. They know all the Heal and Cure spells at level 1.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Electric Beast">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Electric Beast</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Elemental - Air">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Elemental - Air</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Elemental - Earth">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Elemental - Earth</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Elemental - Fire">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Elemental - Fire</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Elemental - Water">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Elemental - Water</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Embalmed Master">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Embalmed Master</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Regenerate 15 HP/turn Preemptive Block 5/8 Anticipated Dodge 3 Multitarget 3 Fiendish Maneuver 4 Immune to acid, poision, and biological damage. Takes half damage from white sources due to the evil wards tattooed on the body</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Undead 400 HP Size: 2 Actions: 4 plus 3 move Attack 9/5 with chains 10/5 with melee weapons Parry: 10/5 with melee weapons Dodge: 6-5 Armor: 15/18/3 Infernal Chain, 20/20/20 natural, TOTAL: 35/38/23 Base Armor: 20</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Chain Whip: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><rOff>+</rOff><raw>10</raw><kind>S</kind></roll> range of 15 feet, target has -5 to defend Fist: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>20</raw><kind>C</kind></roll> , and Disrupt Life on contact Wounding War Hammer +2: <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns><rOff>+</rOff><raw>20</raw><kind>C</kind></roll> and wound deals <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>6</bns></roll> per turn. Wounds stack. Evil totem: <roll><num>1</num><face>10</face><bns/><mul>2</mul></roll> near, <roll><num>1</num><face>10</face><bns/><mul>20</mul></roll> touching</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>The Embalmed Master was the greatest work of the necromancers Erasmus Diggle and Duncan Nusukan. This evil creature represented the best of their combined skills in embalming, undead animation, dark magic, and artificing. Duncan Nusukan chose the body of his enemy, King Asmodius, for this horrible creation. Apperance: The Embalmed Master at first glance appears to be a large man wearing armor. However, continued observation results in the viewer realizing the true nature of this horrid creation. Asmodius' body, stripped of its skin, has been chemically embalmed and infused with unholy magic, as an &quot;embalmed zombie&quot;. The creature bears magical tattoos worked directly into the muscles, futher empowering it. The armor it wears is made of heavy chains, riveted into a suit of chain mail of gross proportions. Additional iron chains dangle from the armor and drag across the ground like a train of a noble's robe<ndash/>a horrific mockery of Asmodius' former position in life. Habits: Like an Embalmed Zombie, the Embalmed Master is the undead servant of it's creator, Duncan Nusukan. His default &quot;programming&quot; is to act as Nusukan's bodyguard. He must obey Nusukan's every whim, and thus may be sent on special missions. Despite being under Nusukan's control, the Embalmed Master may &quot;think&quot; for himself, and is therefore far more skilled than a simple zombie. Combined with his immense strength, he is a powerful foe indeed. Combat: The Embalmed Master fights as an expert warrior would fight, as he retains his former combat experience. However, he is bound to obey any orders issued by Nusukan.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Featherfolk">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Featherfolk</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly 30 mph.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 12 DEX: 14 BLD: 12 INT: 14 WIS: 16 WIL: 12 CHA: 12 HP: 30 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: None, but may wear armor Size: Human sized with a 25' wing span Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 3; Block: 4; Parry: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Same as a human. Will often use melee weapons or long bows.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Featherlings are winged humanoid creatures that look similar to humans. They have long (1' long) pointed ears and slanted eyes. In place of hair they have large brightly-colored feathers. They are smart and cunning, equal to a human in every aspect.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Freysian Cave Hopper (&quot;Deadly Insect&quot;)">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Freysian Cave Hopper ( <ldquo/>Deadly Insect<rdquo/>)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>darkvision jump 25 feet flight (at normal move speed, but clumsily) poison sting</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Beast 50 HP Size: 1 Actions: 3 Attack: 2-10 bite, 3-10 sting. (+3 vs. humans due to size) Move: 3 Natural Armor: 5/5/7 (chitin shell) Base Armor: 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><raw>5</raw><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll> (bite is not poisonous) Sting: <roll><raw>5</raw><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>P</kind></roll> 10 AP primary damage, plus poison Poison deals <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> instantly, plus <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> and <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> BLD for next <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> turns. The sting is intensley painful and the target is reduced to 1 action per turn unless he can make a WIL check (-3) each turn the poison is in effect. Anything requiring concentration (such as casting a magic spell or using many academic skills) requires a skill roll at a penalty of -3 due to the pain. Chirping: Sonic effect in a 90-degree cone. Targets within 10 feet are deafened for <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> minutes and loose <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>-</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> actions next turn. Targets out to 20' loose their next action only.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Apperance: This insect resembles an oversized leaf grasshopper, approximatley two feet long. It has six legs. The rearmost pair are enlarged for jumping while the other four legs are much smaller. Each leg ends in a clawed foot. The creature has a chitinous body colored a green or brown shade, often similar to that of its enviornment. Like a normal grasshopper, the Freysian Cave Hopper has wings and can fly (albeit in a clumsy fashion). Its inner wings are a bright scarlet red color; these are not visible unless the creature is actually flying. In a wooded area Freysian Cave Hoppers can be very difficult to see as they blend in with the foliage quite effectively. Habits: The creature is an omnivourous scavenger: its typical diet is mostly plant matter, but it will eat carrion as well as dead or decaying plants. It does not sleep, and spends most of its time searching for food and potential mates. Fresian Hoppers are not agressive and do not hunt live prey. However, they are fiercely territorial of their &quot;nest&quot; area. They are usually solitary, meeting others of their kind only to mate. Females defend their egg sacs but once the young hatch they are left to fend for themselves. Combat: Freysian Hoppers do not enter combat unless attacked or defending their nest or egg sac. When pressed into combat they attempt to frighten intruders by making a loud chirping sound (similar to that of a cricket, but loud enough to cause temporary deafness) and unfolding their red inner wings as a kind of threat display. Their bite is weak, though their powerful sting is intensely painful and is potent enough to kill a healthy adult if medical assistance is not available.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Gargoyle">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Gargoyle</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly 20 mph.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 16 DEX: 14 BLD: 16 INT: 10 WIS: 12 WIL: 11 CHA: 6 HP: 50 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 9/9/9. Base armor of 10 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 2; Parry: 4; Block: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll>. Will usually use humanoid weapons and armor.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>argoyles are gray-skinned humanoid creature with wings protruding from the shoulders. They have human like attributes, but have double the HP. Gargoyles sleep by turning into a stone statue. They can fly up to 20 mph. Gargoyles have a tribal society.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Gargoyle - Mage">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Gargoyle - Mage</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly 20 mph.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 16 DEX: 12 BLD: 12 INT: 16 WIS: 18 WIL: 17 CHA: 6 HP: 30 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 9/9/9. Base armor of 10 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 3; Parry: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll>. Will usually use humanoid weapons and armor.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Gargoyles are winged humanoids. Their skin has a stone-like appearance. All gargoyles can turn into a statue at will. Knows a good deal of magic. Magic Studies: 5; Magic Control: 5; and 450 MP</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Ghost">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Ghost</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Ghoul">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Ghoul</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Only fire can deal damage to a ghoul</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 10 DEX: 12 BLD: 10 INT: 4 WIS: 8 WIL: 10 CHA: 2 HP: 30 Actions:: 2 P/S/C: none Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Touch: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll>. Bite: <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> , and poison for <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll>.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Ghouls are a variety of undead. They are stupid, relentless, creatures that exist only to eat the flesh of the dead. Ghouls prefer to eat the flesh of whatever species they were in life. They are very slow moving, but quite strong. Ghouls deal cold damage by physical contact and have a bite that is posionous to living creatures. Ghouls regenerate very quickly. They are extremely weak against fire.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Giant Slipper Snail">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Giant Slipper Snail</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Low-light vision Sense vibrations Immune to Poison Hide in Shell</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Beast 70 HP Size: 2 Actions: 3 Attack: 3-17 Tentacle; 1-10 bite Natural Armor: 5/15/10 shell (may vary depending on what is on the shell) Base Armor: 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Tentacle slap: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>2</raw><kind>C</kind></roll> Tentacle constrict: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>8</raw><kind>C</kind></roll> , only available on a previously slapped target Size 2 or smaller Bite: <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll> Spray ahesive: As the spell Carpet of Adhesion (twice per day); may be sprayed outward or secreted on the floor directly. Posion Dart: (once per day) Range of 30 feet Deals <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> Poison deals <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>-</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>S</kind></roll> TR, <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> , and -1 action for <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> rounds</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Apperance: This strange creature appears to be a pile of rubbish at first glance. It is actually a type of pretatory snail. The snail's body resembles that of a giant slug, over five feet long and about two feet thick. Like a slug, its body is rubbery and has no bones, so it can squeeze into various shapes. It's shell is shaped like an upside-down shoe. The bottom side is halfway covered and is flat, lying close to the ground. The upper side of the shell is bean-shaped. The creature covers it's shell with various detritus that it collects from its enviornment, thereby camoflaugeing itself. It keeps its eyestalks well hidden inside the trash covering its shell. The creature's &quot;face&quot; features four eye stalks and four muscular prehensile tentacles that it uses to eat and manipulate objects. It's mouth features a beak similar to that of a squid, and a fleshy tubelike proboscis through which it can secrete its adhesive or fire its poison dart. Habits: The Giant Slipper Snail is a terrestrial ambush predator. It hides very effectively after having covered its shell with detritus from the area in which it hunts, making it blend into the background. It sits motionless for long periods of time (days if need be) waiting for potential prey to walk nearby. After detecting the approach of potential prey (from vibration in the ground) it attacks once the prey is close. The creature is extraordinarly stupid and kills only to eat meat. Once any prey has been devoured, it scatters the remains about, sometimes attaching parts of the victim to it's shell. Gaint Slipper Snails eat the entire body of their prey, including bones, hair, and teeth, which provide the minerals it needs to grow its shell. Combat: Giant Slipper Snails are not combative in general, however they are prone to attack nearly anything when hungry. A large prey target is attacked using its poison dart. The creature then waits for the poison to take effect before taking further action. Smaller prey animals (rodents, frogs, lizards, and the like) are simply grabbed and constricted using its tentacles. If the snail encounters a tough prey animal, it simply retreats inside it's armored shell and uses it's adhesive to stick itself to the floor, waiting for the threat to go away.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Gnoll">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Gnoll</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>When in a pack, will have a +1 damage bonus</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 15 DEX: 14 BLD: 13 INT: 10 WIS: 12 WIL: 8 CHA: 8 HP: 36 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: Leather or light plate Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 3; Parry: 3; Block: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>P</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Gnolls are hyena-like beasts with human heads and faces. Some Gnolls have human-like arms and walk like apes. Most are much more hyena-like, however. They are cunning animals that enjoy the slaughter of weaker animals, or whatever they can successfully attack. They are easily scared and are fearful of flashy displays of power. They are gregarious and are generally found in groups of <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> individuals. They are scavengers and will eat whatever they can find.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Goblin">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Goblin</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>None</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 10 DEX: 8 BLD: 8 INT: 8 WIS: 8 WIL: 8 CHA: 8 HP: 16 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: Leather if anything Size: 3'-4' tall Dice: Strike: 2; Parry: 2; Dodge: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Will usually use a short sword, small club, or dagger. May also have a shield.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Goblins are pathetic, hideous humanoid creatures with green, wart-covered, skin. They are cruel and delight in causing trouble and tormenting others. Most goblins are of low intelligence and are very superstitious. They have a tribal society lead by a cheftain or shaman, who generally knows some low level magic. Goblins use simple weapons and some might wear basic armor such as leather.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Griffon">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Griffon</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly at a speed of 50 mph. Has excellent vision, as well as the ability to see in complete darkness. Will kill harpies on sight (has a +2 damage bonus against harpies)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 16 DEX: 13 BLD: 18 INT: 5 WIS: 8 WIL: 10 CHA: 10 HP: 50 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 4/4/4 Size: Lion sized Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Beak: <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> ; Claws: <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>S</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Griffons have the body and hindquarters of a lion and the head and neck of an eagle. They have feathered wings and are agile fliers. They are proud and majestic creatures that care for their young defiantly.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Gurgoyle">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Gurgoyle</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can leap 100 feet</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 20 DEX: 15 BLD: 20 INT: 10 WIS: 12 WIL: 11 CHA: 6 HP: 80 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: 16/16/16. Base armor of 15 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 2; Parry: 4; Block: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll>. Will usually use humanoid weapons and armor.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Gurgoyle is a cousin of the Gargoyle. Gurgoyles are stronger and tougher, but less intelligent. They are far more common than gargoyles. Generally, gurgoyles are found with their more intelligent bretheren, who subjugate them as soldiers. Though stupid, they are formidible fighters. Like gargoyles, they transform into stone statues during sleep.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Harpy">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Harpy</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can fly at 30 mph. Harpies have a terrible stench that follows them wherever they go. All non-harpies are at -2 actions when within 25' of the harpy.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 14 DEX: 15 BLD: 13 INT: 10 WIS: 12 WIL: 10 CHA: 4 HP: 34 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: None Size: 6' tall with a 30' wingspan Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws: <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns></roll> and will poison when damage is done. The poison will do <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> damage a turn for <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns></roll> turns.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Harpies are hideous nude humanoids that live in a bee-like society. The majority are female. Harpies have a horrible stench that surrounds them and their colony. They have bat-like wings and clawed hands and feet. They have a tendency to form colonies on cliff sides facing the ocean.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Hellcat">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Hellcat</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Anyone who touches or attacks a hellcat is immediately struck by fire dealing <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll>. If the bite deals damage, then fire poison races through the target dealing <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> D a turn until death (an ice spell or cure can stop this)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 14 DEX: 14 BLD: 18 INT: 14 WIS: 13 WIL: 16 CHA: 10 HP: 40 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: 5/5/5 Size: Lion sized Dice: Strike: 5; Dodge: 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> ; Bite: <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A lion-like creature, the Hellcat's body is covered with a mane of blazing fire. They are voracious predators and will eat anything they can catch and kill. Hellcats are immune to non-magical damage, except ice or water based attacks. Anything touching a Hellcat suffers a fire based attack, which also poisons them.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Hobgoblin">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Hobgoblin</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>None</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 15 DEX: 14 BLD: 12 INT: 12 WIS: 10 WIL: 10 CHA: 8 HP: 30 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: Any normal armor Size: 4'-5' tall Dice: Strike: 3; Parry: 3; Dodge: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Will use any melee weapon or crossbow</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>obgoblins are larger, smarter versions of goblins. They are generally 4-5 feet tall and have human-like skin and hair. They understand tactics, and are not easy to scare like goblins are. Goblins will usually rely on the smarts of a hobgoblin if possible. Hobgoblins are either solitary or members of small family groups ( <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> individuals). They tend to be hateful of other races and creatures, except goblins. They have a complex polytheistic religion. Hobgoblins use human like weapons and armor, but never the more advanced varieties. Though hobgoblins are capable of understanding concepts such as deceit, trickery, etc. they prefer to use brute force to overwhelm their opponents.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Hydra">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Hydra</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Each head can act independently of the others, consequently, each head gets one &quot;free&quot; attack a turn. This can be a bite, or to breath fire ( <roll><num>6</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> ). The 3 attacks listed are for tail and claw attacks.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 30 DEX: 22 BLD: 33 INT: 10 WIS: 12 WIL: 10 CHA: 6 HP: 500 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 16/16/16; Base armor of 15 Size: 50' from head to base of tail with a 30' tail Dice: Strike: 5; Dodge: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>5</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> ; Claws: <roll><num>6</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>S</kind></roll> ; Tail: <roll><num>7</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>ydras are massive beasts that enjoy destruction, plundering, and the hoarding of valuables. They have multiple heads (anywhere from three to nine) on long necks and a stout barrel-like body with a long scaly tail. They have thick, stubby legs that look vaguely like those of a frog or toad. Hydras are amphibious but are poor swimmers. They will often live in or near shallow bodies of water. They favor swampy areas. Each head can act indipendantly of the others.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Ifrit">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Ifrit</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Immune to fire of any kind. Normal fire will HEAL an Ifrit instead of damaging it. Merely touching an Ifrit deals <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> fire damage.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 35 DEX: 13 BLD: 25 INT: 8 WIS: 12 WIL: 16 CHA: 8 HP: 200 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 4/8/10 Size: 14' tall; 10' tall when hunched over Dice: Strike: 4 Dodge: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Punch, kick. Bite deals <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll>. Flaming dash attack takes whole turn, deals 4x <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> fire</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A rare, solitary, beast that looks something like a gorilla. It is covered in gold-colored shaggy hair which burns with fierce flames. Walks bipedally but uses hands to steady itself. It is thought to be an ancient variety of fire elemental.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Imp (any)">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Imp (any)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>-2 to strike any imp Natural armor 3/3/3, 6/6/6, 9/9/9 Raise a dead imp: 1 action (Darkling only) Summon <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> red imps or 1 black imp: 1action (Darkling only)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Imps are the most common (and weakest) variety of demon. They occur in three different varieties. Imps speak Demon and also have their own language consisting of chittering, high-pitched barks, chirps, and yelps. They are very fast moving and are totally fearless. Imps delight in causing suffering and tormenting anything living. Imps are of marginal intelligence and especially hate humans and other <ldquo/>smarter<rdquo/> races. Imps live in clans consisting of 5x <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> red imps, 2x <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> black imps, and <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> Darklings.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Imp (black)">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Imp (black)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>-2 to strike an imp (Fast moving)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 10 DEX: 12 BLD: 7 INT: 12 WIS: 9 WIL: 9 CHA: 6 HP: 30 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 6/6/6 Size: 2' high Dice: Strike 3, block: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>S</kind></roll> ; Bite <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Black imps are stronger versions of their red brethren. They use hit-and-run tactics, as well as simple ambushes, traps, etc. Occur in groups of 3X <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> , usually lead by some other from of demon or possibly a Darkling.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Imp (darkling)">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Imp (darkling)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>-2 to strike an imp (Fast moving) Can raise red or black imps for 1 action each. Can summon <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> red imps or 1 black imp at will for 2 actions.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 12 DEX: 14 BLD: 8 INT: 13 WIS: 10 WIL: 10 CHA: 7 HP: 50 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: 9/9/9 Size: 2' high Dice: Strike: 4 Dodge: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>S</kind></roll> ; Bite <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Darklings are the most powerful type of imp. They oversee the weaker imps, and direct their evil deeds. Ususally solitary, in groups of <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> , or sometimes commanding groups of lesser imps.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Imp (red)">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Imp (red)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>-2 to strike an imp (Fast moving)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 9 DEX: 10 BLD: 6 INT: 10 WIS: 9 WIL: 8 CHA: 6 HP: 20 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 3/3/3 Size: 2' high Dice: Strike: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll> ; Bite <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Imps are among the weakest demons. Small, fast moving, reletless and fearless. They delight in causing suffering. Ususally occur in groups of 5X <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> , lead by a higher type of imp or a greater imp.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Iron Maiden">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Iron Maiden</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Knorath (minor fire demon)">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Knorath (minor fire demon)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can raise minor and normal zombies/skeleton for one action each.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 18 DEX: 16 BLD: 16 INT: 14 WIS: 13 WIL: 13 CHA: 12 HP: 250 Actions:: 5 P/S/C: 12/14/13 Size: 8' tall humanoid Dice: Strike: 5; Block: 5; Dodge: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Morning star <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> ; Kick <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>4</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> ; Breathe Fire <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A minor demon<ndash/>red-skinned, muscular humanoid. Knows magic: Fire1..3; Black 1,2; Time 1,2; Flame Shroud, Counter 1,2,3; Bio 1,2; Quake 1,2. 700 MP. Has infravision, can see invisible. Immune to posion <and/> sleep. Regenerates <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> HP per turn</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Kobold">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Kobold</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Kobolds can leap up to 15 feet.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 10 DEX: 15 BLD: 10 INT: 8 WIS: 8 WIL: 8 CHA: 8 HP: 24 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: Leather if anything Size: 3'-4' tall Dice: Strike: 3; Parry: 3; Dodge: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Will usually use a short spear or short bow.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Kobolds travel in packs of <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll>. They are sadistic creatures that enjoy the eating of intelligent creatures. They are not cowardly like goblins, so are much more dangerous.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Kraken">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Kraken</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Each tentacle can make 2 &quot;free&quot; slaps or constricions per turn. The other actions are for moving. Immune to water and ice/cold attacks. A kraken's eye is susceptable to damage.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 30 DEX: 15 BLD: 40 INT: 5 WIS: 5 WIL: 10 CHA: 4 HP: 4000 Actions:: 2 P/S/C: 10/10/20 Size: Main body is 80' long, with 100' tentacles Dice: Strike: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Tentacle slap <and/> grab <roll><num>10</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll>. Tentacle Constriction: <roll><num>6</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>C</kind></roll> , doubles each consecutive action. Full body constriction: ( <roll><num>8</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> )x4 C as above</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Krakens are gargantuan creatures of the deep oceans. Rarely seen, but when they are, they instill panic and will often attack nearby sailing vessels thinking they are their favorite prey (whales). Not a vicious animal naturally.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Kuan-Ya">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Kuan-Ya</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Minor Teleport (3/day) Snort Smoke (As spell Create Smoke, 1/turn) Breathe Fire (As spell Ashen Cloud) 1/day immune to poisons and life-affecting spells elemental resistance Charge Flies Spirit (immune to non-magical weapons) A Kuan Ya that sees it's reflection in a mirror looses half it's HP. (only works once per day) Striking a Kuan-Ya with a mirror deals damage directly to HP equal to twice its normal fire damge ( <roll><num>6</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> )</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Immune to fire and poison. Take 1/4 damage from other elemental sources, except water which deals 1/2 damage instead. 200 HP Size: 2 (15' long, but diminished size due to narrow body) Actions: 3 plus 3 moves Attack: 6-6 (bite) Dodge: none Natural Armor: 0/0/0 Base Armor: 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>10</raw><kind>S</kind></roll> and <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> Fire Tail Whip <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>3</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> and <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> Fire Charge-bite deals double the normal S damage; fire damage is unchanged.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Apperance: The Kuan-Ya is an agressive beast whose body is made entirely of fire. It's head resembles that of a dragon or some great lizard or serpent. It glows bright orange and red, and appears to made of flames compressed together in an invisible shell, showing detail including teeth, eyes, and ridges on the forehead. The center of its eyes are two white-hot glowing spots. The remainder of its body is long and serpentine, and is far less detailed. The end of it's tail is nothing other than wild flame. The beast is about fifteen feet long and the body is two feet in diameter at the head, tapering down to the end of the tail. Habits: Kuan-Ya are tempramental, agressive, and mean. Fortunately, their temper is also mercurial and while they are easily provoked, they are also likely to forget about past acts of agression if a new threat presents itself. Kuan-Ya are spirit beings, and therefore they do not need to eat. They are not particularly intelligent. Combat: Kuan-Ya are fearless and charge forward in battle. They use no subterfuge and attack the most convenient opponent directly, biting with their red-hot mouth.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Maw larva">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Maw larva</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Excellent climbers. They have a strong grip when holding onto something. Can jump up to 6', but slow and ungainly on the ground.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 10 DEX: 10 BLD: 4 INT: 6 WIS: 6 WIL: 10 CHA: 4 HP: 10 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 1/3/0 Size: 8-10&quot; long Dice: Strike: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>-</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> ; Bite <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A rat-sized pink creature with soft, wrinkly skin and four small limbs each of which end in a 3-clawed hand. It has a massive head and mouth<ndash/>the size of a man's fist<ndash/>with prominent teeth. They eat anything they can catch.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Metal Babble">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Metal Babble</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>(standard) Regenerate 10 HP/turn Babble: Affects all within 15' radius who can hear it. Deals <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> and <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> WIL (huge) Regenerate 20 HP/turn Babble: Affects all within 20' radius who can hear it. Deals <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> , <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> WIL, and -1 action next turn. Immune to weapons of +3 quality or lesser.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>(standard) Vulerable to electricity (1.5x damage) 150 HP Size: 2 Actions: 3 plus 2 moves Attack/Parry: 6-8 with pseudopod, 5-8 with blade cyclone Natural Armor: 70/50/35 Base Armor: 1 (huge) Vulerable to electricity (1.5x damage) 400 HP Size: 2 Actions: 3 plus 2 moves Attack/Parry: 7-8 with pseudopod, 6-8 with blade cyclone Natural Armor: 80/60/45 Base Armor: 1</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>(standard) Spike Pseudopod: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>5</raw><kind>P</kind></roll> , 30 AP Blade Cyclone <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><rOff>+</rOff><raw>15</raw><kind>S</kind></roll> , affects all surrounding squares. (huge) Spike Pseudopod: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>15</raw><kind>P</kind></roll> , 30 AP, or half damage at a 10' range. Blade Cyclone <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><rOff>+</rOff><raw>25</raw><kind>S</kind></roll> , affects all surrounding squares.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Appearance: The metal babble is a strange creature whose body looks like an amorphous blob of silvery liquid metal. The creature has a &quot;mound shaped&quot; body about four feet in diameter and two feet thick in the center. Its body is constantly moving and squirming like some sort of huge metal amoeba. The creature makes a noise not ulike a simmering stew as the metal that makes up its body flows about and bubbles. Metal babbles move about like a slug, but they are capable of moving quite rapidly. Habits: Metal Babbles are of very low intelligence. They like dark areas such as old cellars, caves, and underground crypts. They slide about the floor, searching for material to eat. Metal Babbles are capable of eating nearly anything, including stone, dirt, and organic matter. They care little for the taste of meat, though they will eat it in preferance to stone. The Metal Babble's favorite food is metal objects, including coins, weapons, tools and the like. Metal Babbles eat by engulfing their food like an amoeba. Combat: Metal Babbles do not hunt live prey, and they do not persue hostilities of their own accord. However, if disturbed they attack ferociously. Metal Babbles attack by forming their body into living weapons. Their most common attack is to form a spear-like blade and thrust it towards a target. When surrounded by multiple threats, they can form their body into a huge mass of spinning blades, threatening everyone around them. Finally, the creature is able to spew forth a sonic attack of mind-numbing gibberish. All creatures who are within range (and who can hear) are affected by this ability.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Minotaur">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Minotaur</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Charge: Takes up all actions for the turn, and has a 5D+14 for successes (because it is so fast) and will deal <roll><num>6</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 23 DEX: 14 BLD: 24 INT: 10 WIS: 10 WIL: 12 CHA: 8 HP: 60 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 9/9/9 Size: 7'-8' humanoid Dice: Strike: 3; Parry: 3; Block: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>8</raw><kind>S</kind></roll> ; Horns: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>8</raw><kind>P</kind></roll> ; Hooves: <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>8</raw><kind>C</kind></roll>. Some may use a blunt weapon and maybe a shield.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Minotaurs are massive humanoid creatures covered with corse hair. It has the head and legs of a bull. They are typically passive unless attacked.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Mummy">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Mummy</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Undead. Immune to poison, cold, and electricity attacks. Healing spells cast on a mummy will do 1/2 &quot;healed&quot; damage direct to HP.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 20 DEX: 10 BLD: 12 INT: 4 WIS: 4 WIL: 6 CHA: 4 HP: 40 Actions:: 2 P/S/C: 4/4/4 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Punch: <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Stupid, mindless creature brought back to life. A decaying corpse wrapped in cloth that stinks to high-heaven. Will attack any non-undead on sight.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Necrolisk">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Necrolisk</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>low-light vision Heat sense</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Beast 400 HP Size: 3 Actions: 3 Attack: 4-10 Bite 4-12 Tail slap 4-12 Grab with small arms 3-11 Claws Move: 4 Natural Armor: 12/16/8 Base Armor: 9</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><raw>5</raw><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> Tail Slap: <roll><raw>10</raw><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll> Claws: <roll><raw>5</raw><num>3</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll> Impale on Spike: <roll><raw>5</raw><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>P</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Apperance: This foul beast resembles a gigantic ignuana. It's body is fifteen feet long, with a tail of similar length. It stands on four heavily muscled legs, ending in sharp claws. The creature's back is bristling with slender, bony spikes that are the size of two-handed swords. An additional four slender arms protrude from the creature's midsection: two on each side. These arms are long and slender and end in clawed hands. Habits: The Necrolisk is a powerful carnivore<ndash/>it spends its time hunting in order to feed its ravenous appetite. Its only other pastime is sleeping off past meals. Any creature encountered by a Necrolisk is either ignored (in the case of tiny vermin) or categorized as food or as a potential threat<ndash/>in both cases, it is attacked and eaten. The necrolisk is fond of impaling dead prey on its back spikes to store it for later as it relishes the taste of partially-decayed meat. Combat: The Necrolisk is an unsubtle combatant. It charges foes and attacks them with claws, bite, its tail slap. Incapacitated targets are impaled on its back spikes. It us unlikley to back down from a fight unless it is obvious loosing or if it's opponents are particularly flashy and/or larger than it is.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Net-lath (minor earth demon)">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Net-lath (minor earth demon)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can raise minor and normal zombies/skeleton for one action each, can summon zombies at will for 1,2,3 actions respectivley</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 12 DEX: 16 BLD: 14 INT: 15 WIS: 15 WIL: 16 CHA: 10 HP: 400 Actions:: 5 P/S/C: 16/16/16 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 3; Dodge: 5;</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Death touch <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> ; Poisionous breath weapon <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> area affect</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A minor demon<ndash/>Guant, grey-skinned humanoid. Knows magic: Fire1..3; Black 1,2,3; Time 1,2; Counter 1,2,3; Bio 1,2; Quake 1,2,3; Geo Transport, Heal 1,2,3. 1200 MP. Can see invisible. Immune to posion <and/> sleep. Regenerates <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> HP per turn</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Nightmare">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Nightmare</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can carry a rider who weighs no more than 1 ton (and is small enough). All melee attacks have fire effect. Cannot be hurt my non-magical attacks. Walks on air. Speed: 50 mph. Immune to fire</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 18 DEX: 13 BLD: 18 INT: 10 WIS: 12 WIL: 14 CHA: 10 HP: 200 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 16/16/16; 10 base armor Size: Large War-Horse Sized Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 5</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> ; Front Kick: <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> ; Back Kick: <roll><num>5</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> ; Fire Breath: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> Fire</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Trainable - Ebony black horses with manes and hoves of fire. Solitary creatures, tend to be cruel to other creatures out of spite. A trained nightmare will have the same disposition of its trainer, and will not listen to anyone besides the trainer.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Ogre">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Ogre</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>None</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 24 DEX: 12 BLD: 22 INT: 8 WIS: 6 WIL: 10 CHA: 4 HP: 100 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 9/9/9 Natural; Will often wear leather Size: 10' tall, 6' wide Dice: Strike: 4; Parry: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>9</raw><kind>P</kind></roll> ; Claws: <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><rOff>+</rOff><raw>9</raw><kind>S</kind></roll> ; Often will use a very large blunt weapon</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Dumb humanoid creatures with brownish yellow skin. Band together like goblins, and attack in large numbers ( <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> ). Afraid of magic users (must make a WIL check or flee), otherwise, they are not fearfull of anything.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Quickening Demon">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Quickening Demon</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Rabbat">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Rabbat</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Flies Doom, as the spell except timer is <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>-</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> instead, and affects up to 4 targets at once. Only 1/day Fireball, <roll><num>10</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> 30' radius Fire effect Magma Dart, <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> Explosive + Fire Energy Shield <roll><raw>3</raw><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> turns, 1/2 damage incoming only.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>Immune to fire and cold 200 HP Size: 2 Actions: 3 plus 2 moves Attack/Parry: 4-11 (bite) Dodge: none Natural Armor: 10/15/5 Base Armor: 7</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bns/><rOff>+</rOff><raw>10</raw><kind>S</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Apperance: The Rabbat is frightening beast to behold. It consists of a bulbous central body which is dominated by a single giant eyeball and a huge mouth filled with vicious looking teeth<ndash/>leaving no doubt that this beast is a meat eater. Two bat-like wings extend from the central body. It has no other limbs. Habits: Rabbats are aggressive meat eaters. In the wild, they persue and attack anything they think they can kill, which is most creatures. Rabbats are only afraid of very large, powerful, beasts such as Dragons. They may be found in nearly any enviornment, but they tend to lair in caves. Rabbats are much more powerful than they are intelligent, and thus they are sometimes subjugated by powerful wizards for use as minions. Combat: Rabbats are unsubtle and make no use of trickery or deciet. They do, however, know the tactical advantage of staying away from a fight and utilize their ranged spell-like abilities, closing in to bite only when they are clearly winning the fight. They are unlikely to flee except in the most exceptional of circumstances.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Shadow Walker">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Shadow Walker</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Skeleton-greater mage">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Skeleton-greater mage</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>can touch and drain <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> HP</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 9 DEX: 10 BLD: 10 INT: 16 WIS: 13 WIL: 13 CHA: 8 HP: 50 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: varies, typ: 8/8/8 Size: Human Sized Dice: Strike: 3; Dodge: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Punch <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> , Cold blast <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> D</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Skeletal mage appears as an animated human skeleton, has clothing and carries a staff or wand-like object. Likes to wear crowns and jewlery. Has 350 MP, knows spells: Fire 1,2,3; Cold 1; Bio 1,2; Quake 1,2; Magic Missile.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Skeleton-greater warrior">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Skeleton-greater warrior</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>can touch and drain <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> HP</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 15 DEX: 14 BLD: 12 INT: 12 WIS: 9 WIL: 9 CHA: 8 HP: 70 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: varies, typ: 8/8/8 Size: Human Sized Dice: Strike: 5; Parry: 5; Dodge:3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Attacks with archaic weapon (varies)</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Animated skeleton, typically has some archaic armor. Wields an archaic weapon in combat, favoring large swords, axes, or blunt weapons like flails/ball-and-chain.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Skeleton-mage">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Skeleton-mage</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>none</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 8 DEX: 9 BLD: 8 INT: 14 WIS: 11 WIL: 11 CHA: 8 HP: 40 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: varies, typ: 4/4/4 Size: Human Sized Dice: Strike:3, Dodge: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Punch <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> , Cold blast <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> D</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Skeletal mage appears as an animated human skeleton, often has some clothing and carries a staff or wand-like object. Has 250 MP, knows spells: Fire 1,2; Cold 1; Bio 1.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Skeleton-minor">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Skeleton-minor</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>none</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 8 DEX: 8 BLD: 8 INT: 8 WIS: 8 WIL: 8 CHA: 8 HP: 25 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: none Size: Human Sized Dice: Strike: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Punch <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Appears as an animated, somewhat damaged humanoid skeleton.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Skeleton-warrior">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Skeleton-warrior</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>none</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 13 DEX: 12 BLD: 10 INT: 10 WIS: 8 WIL: 8 CHA: 8 HP: 50 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: varies, typ: 4/4/4 Size: Human Sized Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Attacks with archaic weapon (varies)</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Animated skeleton, typically has some poor quality archaic armor (chain, hard leather, etc.). Wields an archaic weapon in combat, usually a sword, knife, or blunt</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Snakeman - Greater - Harn Dal&apos;aar">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Snakeman - Greater - Harn Dal'aar</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can spit acidic venom once per turn. Deals <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> if it strikes bare skin.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 18 DEX: 16 BLD: 14 INT: 12 WIS: 12 WIL: 12 CHA: 10 HP: 170 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: 10/12/11 base: 5 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 5; Dodge: 3; Parry: 5; Block: 5;</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Oversized Long sword <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>S</kind></roll> ; Sheild Bash <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> ; Throw Fire <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> ; bite <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> + <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> posion</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A demonic warrior created from a human sacrifice and a venomous snake in a magical ritual. Wields a serrated long sword in one hand. Appears much like a human, with scaly skin and a forked tongue. Their skin has a distinct greenish hue.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Snakeman - Greater - Ku&apos;toxx">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Snakeman - Greater - Ku'toxx</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can spit acidic venom once per turn. Deals <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> if it strikes bare skin.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 19 DEX: 16 BLD: 18 INT: 14 WIS: 12 WIL: 13 CHA: 11 HP: 220 Actions:: 5 P/S/C: 14/16/12 base: 5 Size: Human Sized Dice: Strike: 5; Dodge: 3; Parry: 5; Block: 5;</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Oversized Long sword <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>S</kind></roll> (+6 raw); Sheild Bash <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> ; Throw Fire <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> ; bite <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> + <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> posion</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A demonic warrior created from a human sacrifice and a venomous snake in a magical ritual. Wields a serrated long sword in one hand. Appears much like a human, with scaly skin and a forked tongue. Their skin has a distinct gray hue. Has no body hair.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Snakeman - Gukn">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Snakeman - Gukn</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Can spit acidic venom once per turn. Deals <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> if it strikes bare skin.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 16 DEX: 15 BLD: 12 INT: 10 WIS: 10 WIL: 10 CHA: 8 HP: 100 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 8/10/8 base: 4 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 2; Parry: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Oversized Long sword <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll> ; Throw fire <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> ; bite <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>P</kind></roll> + <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> posion</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A demonic warrior created from a human sacrifice and a venomous snake in a magical ritual. Wields a serrated long sword in one hand. Appears much like a human, with a somewhat scaly skin pattern and a forked tongue.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Stygian Fly">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Stygian Fly</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Has only one attack<ndash/>biting. If bitten, the target will suffer <roll><num>2</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns><kind>S</kind></roll>. If flesh is contacted, target suffers tremendous pain. Wound will grow, consuming target's body, at a rate of <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> D per SECOND.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 2 DEX: 16 BLD: 1 INT: 1 WIS: 1 WIL: 10 CHA: 1 HP: 10 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 3/3/3 -9 to strike due to size and movement. Size: about 3&quot; long Dice: Strike: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite<ndash/>see special.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A horrible demonic insect from the depths of the underworld. Stupid, lives only to feast upon the flesh and souls of the living. Even if the wound is cured, the wounded portion of the SOUL remains lost.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Stygian Mofish">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Stygian Mofish</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Cannot be harmed by nonmagical weapons. Immune to cold and fire.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 14 DEX: 10 BLD: 12 INT: 6 WIS: 14 WIL: 14 CHA: 5 HP: 100 Actions:: P/S/C: young: 3/3/3; average 6/6/6; old: 9/9/10 Size: young: 2'; average: 5'; old: 8' long Dice: Strike: 3 Dodge: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>4</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>S</kind></roll> (-1 die for young, +1 for old)</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Demonic creatures that inhabit the waters of the underworld. Very fast swimmers. Will attack anything living that approaches their territory.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Stygian Toad">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Stygian Toad</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Wounds caused by an attack from a Stygian Toad cannot heal by normal means. They can be healed by magic at 1/10th normal rates.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 12 DEX: 12 BLD: 6 INT: 6 WIS: 10 WIL: 10 CHA: 4 HP: 60 Actions:: 2 P/S/C: 8/14/8 Size: About 2' long Dice: Strike: 6</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>C</kind></roll> ; Tongue spear: <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>P</kind></roll> , range of 6'</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A large, wart-covered toad that lives in bogs, marshes, and stagnant water. Lies in wait for it's prey, and then strikes. Camo: level 5. Likes to wound target and then wait for it to die, returning to eat the entire body of the victim.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Tevish-Tzat">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Tevish-Tzat</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Regenerates <roll><num>3</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> HP on each of it's turns.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 24 DEX: 14 BLD: 22 INT: 8 WIS: 8 WIL: 12 CHA: 6 HP: 300 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: 12/12/6 Size: 14' tall Dice: Strike: 4; Block: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Claws: <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/></roll> ; Bite: <roll><num>4</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>P</kind></roll>. Any contact poisons target for <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> per turn for <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> turns.</text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A tall, lanky demon with rotten yellow skin. Hunched over, with long spindly arms. Will persue (and attempt to eat) weaker opponents first. Ususally solitary.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Titan">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Titan</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities"><text/></field>
        <field name="Statistics"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description"><text/></field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Troll">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Troll</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Trolls regenerate <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> HP on each of their turns. They suffer half damage from poisons.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 10 DEX: 8 BLD: 12 INT: 8 WIS: 8 WIL: 8 CHA: 6 HP: 24 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: none or light armor Size: Human sized Dice: Varies. They use human skills and weapons.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Trolls are an ancient race, usually despised by the higher races (men, elves, dwarves). They are primitive and considered savage and dirty. Trolls speak their own native tongue</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Troll, Rock">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Troll, Rock</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Rock Trolls regenerate <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> HP on each of their turns. They have a natural Camo skill of 3 and natural armor of 4/4/4.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 16 DEX: 12 BLD: 20 INT: 8 WIS: 10 WIL: 12 CHA: 7 HP: 50 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: Heavy human armor Size: 8' tall humanoid Dice: Varies. They use human skills and weapons; favor axes, hammers.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Rock Trolls are a distant offshoot of the Troll race. Rock Trolls are much larger. They are a proud, honorable, warrior race that defend their territory fiercely. They rarely venture out of their lands so they are not frequently encountered.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Wolf, Dire">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Wolf, Dire</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>Howl: takes 1 action. Summons <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> wolves loyal to the Dire Wolf.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 18 DEX: 16 BLD: 18 INT: 4 WIS: 4 WIL: 12 CHA: 5 HP: 200 Actions:: 4 P/S/C: 3/6/0 Size: 6' long, 4' high Dice: Strike: 3 Dodge: 4</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Bite <roll><num>3</num><face>6</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll> ; Claws <roll><num>2</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>S</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>A huge, supernatural version of a normal wolf. They are sometimes solitary but ususally found with a pack of normal wolves which they lead.</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Zombie">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Zombie</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>If struck in melee, 30<percent/>chance to deal <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> damage to attacker</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 13 DEX: 10 BLD: 16 INT: 9 WIS: 9 WIL: 10 CHA: 6 HP: 50 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 8/8/8 base 5 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Punch <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> + <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Undead, rotting corpse. Suffers double damage from fire based attacks. Regenerates <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> HP per turn</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Zombie - Greater">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Zombie - Greater</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>If struck in melee, 30<percent/>chance to deal <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> D damage to attacker</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 14 DEX: 12 BLD: 18 INT: 9 WIS: 10 WIL: 12 CHA: 6 HP: 70 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 9/9/9 base 6 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 4; Dodge: 2</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Punch <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>2</bns></roll> + <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns><kind>U</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Undead, rotting corpse. Regenerates <roll><num>1</num><face>6</face><bOff>+</bOff><bns>1</bns></roll> HP per turn</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
      <datum name="Zombie - Minor">
        <field name="Name" title="yes">
          <text>Zombie - Minor</text>
        </field>
        <field name="MetaTag"><text>No value</text></field>
        <field name="Special Abilities">
          <text>If struck in melee, 30<percent/>chance to deal <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> damage to attacker</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Statistics">
          <text>STR: 12 DEX: 8 BLD: 14 INT: 8 WIS: 8 WIL: 8 CHA: 6 HP: 35 Actions:: 3 P/S/C: 6/6/6; base 4 Size: Human sized Dice: Strike: 3</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Attacks">
          <text>Punch <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/></roll> + <roll><num>1</num><face>4</face><bns/><kind>U</kind></roll> </text>
        </field>
        <field description="yes" name="Description">
          <text>Undead, rotting corpse. Suffers double damage from fire based attacks. Regenerates <roll><num>1</num><face>2</face><bns/></roll> HP per turn (no rollover!)</text>
        </field>
        <field name="Level"><text>No value</text></field>
      </datum>
    </category>
