<chapter>
    <title>Core Rules</title>
    <section><!-- Intro -->
        <title>Introduction</title>

  <text><Apathy /> is a paper &amp; pencil role-playing game.  <Apathy
  />'s authors have played a great many RPGs including D&amp;D, Heroes
  Unlimited, GURPS, Shadowrun, TMMNT, various White Wolf games
  (Vampire, etc.), Deadlands, and a few others.  While these games are
  all fun, we felt that each game had various shortcomings that could
  be improved upon.  Enter <Apathy />.  <Apathy /> is designed to be a
  very flexible role-playing system.  <Apathy /> can handle classic
  games with knights and dragons, as well as modern-day, Cyberpunk,
  superhero, or futuristic scenarios.  It excels at fantasy games that
  blend all genres.</text>

  <text><Apathy /> is recommended for advanced role-players (or at
  least for experienced DM/GM/Storytellers).  This is because the
  <Apathy /> system is designed for a unique mix of speed and realism
  rather than carefully <dquo>balanced</dquo> rules.  The <Apathy />
  rules make it very easy to make unbalanced (<dquo>min-maxed</dquo>)
  or tweaked characters.  <Apathy /> is likewise not appropriate for
  <dquo>rules lawyers</dquo> or excessively anal GMs and
  players.</text>

  <text><Apathy /> was created around several core features.  These
  are what make <Apathy /> a unique game system:</text>

  <description-list>

    <item><Apathy /> has no fixed character classes, such as
    <dquo>fighter</dquo> or <dquo>wizard</dquo>, etc.  Players can
    pick and choose every detail of their character, rather than being
    forced into set classes.</item>

    <item><Apathy /> contains rules for all manner of technological
    and supernatural powers, weapons, items, and skills for characters
    to use.  These range from archaic concepts like martial arts and
    swords, through ultra-modern concepts such as cybernetics and
    mecha---and the supernatural abilities of magic and psionics.
    These different elements can be used simultaneously without any
    one being excessively powerful.</item>

    <item>There are no discrete <dquo>levels</dquo> for character
    advancement.  Characters develop and grow constantly, rather than
    infrequent, sudden, increases common to level-based games.  There
    is a distinct and obvious increase in <dquo>power</dquo> as
    characters grow.  This gives players the feeling that their
    characters are constantly improving as the game continues.</item>

    <item>The game rules are purposely devoid of <dquo>fluff</dquo>
    rules.  Time-consuming (and therefore not fun) look-up tables and
    thick books of rules are nowhere to be found.  <Apathy /> is
    designed to be fast to play.  Most of the <dquo>tables</dquo> in
    the <Apathy /> manuals are just to explain things to the players
    and aren't used during play.</item>

    <item>While <Apathy /> is devoid of many <dquo>clutter
    rules</dquo>, it does have an emphasis on realism.  <Apathy />'s
    combat system is an excellent compromise between speed and
    realism.</item>

    <item>In any game of <Apathy />, the CHARACTERS are the heroes!</item>
  </description-list>
    </section><!-- /Intro -->
    <section><!-- Basic Terms -->
        <title>Basic Terms</title>
        
          <description-list>
   <item description="Action">An action is the most basic unit of time during combat.
  It is roughly equal to one second of time.  Most characters will
  have three actions per turn, though certain things can increase or
  decrease this number.  Note that as long as a character is
  unconscious, he or she <bold>always</bold> has at least one action per turn.</item>

   <item description="Base armor"> A character's natural resistance to bodily harm of
  unusual varieties.  You can think of this as <dquo>toughness</dquo> (not to
  be confused with the skill of the same name).  A character's base
  armor reduces the damage they suffer from U (undefined) damage.
  Base armor \emph{does not} protect against any other form of damage,
  such as P, S, C, or D. Note, that if a character suffers any U
  damage, no matter how high their base armor might be, they
  \emph{always} loose at least 1 HP.</item>

   <item description="C"> An abbreviation for \emph{crushing}.  When used in
  conjunction with a weapon, it indicates that the weapon in question
  deals crushing type damage.  When used in conjunction with armor, it
  indicates how much crushing damage the armor will defend against.</item>

   <item description="CP"> \emph{Character Points}.  These are points you use to
  <dquo>purchase</dquo> skills, equipment, etc. for your character.  CP can
  also be used to increase attributes according to a special table.
  See the section on character creation.</item>

   <item description="Character"> A persona within the game world that is adopted by a
  player.  The player sees through the character's eyes, controls the
  character's actions, and speaks through the character's mouth.</item>

   <item description="D"> An abbreviation for Direct Damage.  D damage is applied
  directly against the target's HP.  Armor, including base armor,
  \emph{cannot} protect against D damage.  Fortunately, D damage
  sources are few and far between.</item>

   <item description="Gamemaster"> A person who is in the game that is not a player.
  The gamemaster controls the game world that the players inhabit.
  He/she controls everything that is not the players.  This includes
  other people (sometimes called non-player characters), monsters,
  natural events, etc.  This is usually abbreviated as <dquo>GM</dquo>.</item>

   <item description="HP"> Abbreviation for Hit Points.  Hit Points are used to
  represent a character's health.  If a character gets injured, their
  HP decreases.  If a character reaches 0 HP, they fall unconscious.
  If a character reaches -X HP, where X is equal to their maximum HP,
  they are dead.  Note that if a character is below 0 HP, they will
  loose 1 HP per turn (1 HP per 3 seconds when not in combat) due to
  bleeding, unless they are given medical attention.</item>

  <item description="HTH">
see Hand-to-Hand </item>

  <item description="Hand-to-Hand"> Hand-to-hand is a special type of combat.  It
  takes place when the combatants use no weapons of any kind.  Thus,
  in hand-to-hand combat, only punches, kicks, and similar attacks
  will take place.</item>

  <item description="Luck"> Usually, this is short for Luck Points.  Luck points are
  accumulated during gameplay, and players redeem them for combat
  bonuses, or for saving their character's butt if things get rough.
  This is used to help unlucky die rolls from screwing over players.
  All major character in the game, including significant NPCs,
  villains, etc. will have luck points.  The GM is responsible for
  distributing luck points.</item>

  <item description="MA"> Abbreviation for Martial Arts.  It is sometimes used to
  refer to the Martial Arts skill.  See the Martial Arts section for
  more information.</item>

  <item description="MP"> Magic Points, also called Mana.  Magic points measure how
  much magic a character can use in a certain amount of time.  Each
  time magic is used (a spell is cast, or the character makes a rune)
  MP are consumed.  If a character has no MP, they cannot use any
  magic until the MP replenish.  MP replenish naturally over time.
  See the Magic section for details.</item>

  <item description="Melee"> Melee is a special type of combat.  Melee combat takes
  place when there are \emph{no} projectile (launched, thrown, shot,
  etc.) weapons or attacks of any kind.  Melee combat includes things
  like hand-to-hand fighting, or using weapons like swords, clubs,
  etc.</item>

  <item description="Missile"> A missile weapon is one that flies through the air in
  some manner.  Throwing knives, slings, thrown stones, spears, and
  arrows are examples of missile weapons.</item>

  <item description="Non-Player Character"> A person controlled by the gamemaster who
  interacts with the players.  A non-player character is anyone in the
  game world not controlled by a player.</item>

  <item description="NPC"> See Non Player Character.</item>

  <item description="P"> An abbreviation for Piercing.  When used in conjunction with
  a weapon, it indicates that the weapon in question deals piercing
  type damage.  When used in conjunction with armor, it indicates how
  much piercing damage the armor will defend against.</item>

  <item description="PC"> Power Cells.  This is a measurement of energy or power for
  things like mecha, vehicles, robots, and power armor.  Power,
  measured in PC, is produced by things like engines and is consumed
  by movement systems and weapons, etc.  PC can also mean <dquo>player
  character</dquo>.</item>

  <item description="Player"> An actual person, like the authors of this manual--or
  you--who controls a character in the game world.</item>

  <item description="Round"> A <dquo>round</dquo> is the most general unit of time during
  combat.  Any sequence of combat is broken down into one or more
  rounds.  During each round, each combatant gets to take one turn.  A
  round is over whenever all combatants have taken a turn (or are
  unable to for some reason).</item>

  <item description="S"> An abbreviation for Slashing.  When used in conjunction with
  a weapon, it indicates that the weapon in question deals slashing
  type damage.  When used in conjunction with armor, it indicates how
  much slashing damage the armor will defend against.</item>

  <item description="Size"> A representation of the approximate size of objects such
  as people, mecha, etc.  Humans are size level 2.  Each size level is
  approximately double the height and weight of the size below it.
  So, size 2 covers things up to about 7<squo /> tall.  Size 3, therefore, is
  about 14<squo /> tall.</item>

  <item description="Turn"> A turn is a unit of time during combat.  Each round of
  combat is broken down into one turn per combatant.  During each
  player's turn, they get to do whatever they want.  A turn is roughly
  equal to three seconds of time.  Each turn is subdivided into
  actions.</item>

  <item description="U"> An abbreviation for undefined damage.  Undefined damage is a
  special type of damage that cannot be prevented by normal armor.  It
  is usually caused by supernatural powers, magic, high tech weapons,
  and similar unusual sources.  Normal (P/S/C) armor \emph{cannot}
  protect against U damage.  With very few exceptions, the ONLY thing
  that can protect a character from U damage is his or her base armor.
  Note, that if a character suffers any U damage, no matter how high
  their base armor might be, they ALWAYS loose 1 HP.</item>
 </description-list>

    </section><!-- /Basic Terms -->
    <section><!-- Game World -->
        <title>Game World</title>
         <text><Apathy />, like most role-playing games, can be thought of like a play
or a movie.  The players are like the actors; their characters are the
heroes and heroines of the story.  Like a movie, a game can take place
in any number of settings.  The GM is like the director, and decides
the intricacies of the game world.</text>

<text>The GM should talk with the players and decide upon what kind of game
world they would like to use.  The GM can then finalize the details of
that world, and should tell the players about it before the players
make their characters and the game starts.</text>

<text>Some things to think about when creating the game world are the following:</text>

<numbered-list>
<item>Time Period:  Medieval?  Modern-day?  Futuristic?</item>
<item> Location:  on Earth?  A different planet?  A particular city, perhaps?</item>
<item> Level of technology</item>
<item> Allowed game subsections: Magic?  Psionics?  Supernatural Powers? etc.</item>
</numbered-list>

<text>The <Apathy /> system contains sections for many different types of
games and many different historical settings.  The GM should decide
which ones to allow for each game.</text>
    </section><!-- /Game World -->
    <section><!-- Character -->
        <title>Creating a Character</title>

<text>The first step in playing <Apathy /> is determining your character
concept.  Talk to the GM and your fellow players for ideas about the
game setting and what kind of character you might want to play.  Your
imagination is the only real limit as to what your character can be.
Perhaps you want to play a heroic knight that fights for honor and
puts monsters to the sword?  Or maybe you'd rather play a cunning and
seductive thief with a hidden agenda.  You could be a young mecha
pilot---inexperienced, but eager to fight for his cause.  Your
character is a hero in the game.  You should take this opportunity to
have fun and do things you can't do in real life.</text>

<img src="/Monsters/Buer.png" />

<text>If you are having trouble thinking up a character concept, you might
want to look to books, movies, or even historical precedent as to what
kind of character you want to play.  You could be a space mercenary
like Han Solo from Star Wars, or maybe a secret agent like James
Bond---or perhaps an old-west gunslinger.</text>

<text>Once you have an idea so to what kind of character you want to play,
it's time to develop that idea.  Think about what your character looks
like.  How old are they?  How do they dress?  What kinds of
possessions do they have?  What do they do for a living?  What was
their past?  How would they react in a fight?  What would they do if
they were suddenly given a lot of money?  What are their fears?  Their
hopes?  Their goals?</text>

<text>Now you should have a good understanding of your character's
appearance, personality, skills, etc.  What you need to do next is
represent that idea in the <Apathy /> system rules.  Grab a character
sheet, and follow along.</text>
        <section><!-- Character Basics -->
            <title>Character Basics</title>
            <text>The first part of describing your character is very simple.  Decide
what your character's basic description is like.  Are they male or
female?  How tall?  What do they weigh?  Fill in age, sex, height,
weight, eyes color, and hair color/style on the upper right portion of
your character sheet.  Decide on your character's name, and fill that
in too.  There is also a spot on the character sheet for \emph{your}
name.  Now you can move on to the details of your character.</text>
        </section><!-- /Character Basics -->
        <section><!-- Attributes -->
                <title>Attributes</title>

<text><Apathy /> models characters by means of a core attribute system.
These attributes are numbers that describe the most basic
characteristics of any given character.  They are:</text>

\begin{table}[!htb]
\begin{center}
\begin{tabular}{p{.5in}p{1in}p{2.5in}}
<figure>
    <table>
    <head>
        <cell width=".5in">Abbr.</cell>
        <cell width="1in">Name</cell>
        <cell width="2.5in">Definition</cell>
    </head>
    <row>
        <cell>STR</cell>
        <cell>Strength</cell>
        <cell>raw physical strength,  muscle power</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>DEX</cell>
        <cell>Dexterity</cell>
        <cell>quickness, coordination, fine motor control, balance</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>BLD</cell>
        <cell>Build</cell>
        <cell>the toughness and durability of your body, stamina, <dquo>guts</dquo></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>INT</cell>
        <cell>Intelligence</cell>
        <cell>computational power of the mind, ability to grasp complex problems</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>KNO</cell>
        <cell>Knowledge</cell>
        <cell>experience and background knowledge, common sense, etc.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>WIL</cell>
        <cell>Willpower</cell>
        <cell>strength of the mind, ability to `stick it out' when things get tough</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>CHA</cell>
        <cell>Charisma</cell>
        <cell>friendliness, dealing with people, etc.</cell>
    </row>
</table>
<caption>Basic Terms</caption>
</figure>

<text><emph>Throughout this document the attributes will usually be
  mentioned using the three-letter abbreviation instead of the full
  name.</emph></text>

<text>The first three attributes (STR, DEX, and BLD) are considered Physical
Attributes.  The second three attributes (INT, WIS, and WIL) are
Mental Attributes.  The seventh, CHA, is a little of both, but is
generally considered to be a Mental Attribute.</text>

<text>Attributes are rated on a scale.  1 is the lowest possible attribute
score.  There is no top end on the scale, though an attribute of 20 is
the peak of human ability.  A human character can never have an
attribute higher than 20 without some supernatural effect (super
power, magic, cybernetics, etc).</text>

<text>When creating a character, the GM allows you a certain number of
attribute points.  Attribute Points are used to purchase the attribute
values you want your character to have. <bold>A normal human has
  about 40 attribute points.  An above average human would have about
  105--140 attribute points.  We recommend that 120 Attribute Points
  be assigned to starting characters---after all, player characters
  are supposed to be heroic---though the GM has the final word.</bold></text>

<text>The cost of an attribute is computed like a skill with Rank 1 (see the
skill section later on). However, the final value for the attribute
(for a Human) is increased by 8; that is, if you buy 5 levels of STR
(for 15 AP), then the final value of the STR is <math>5 + 8 = 13</math>.</text>

<text><bold>In most cases no player may have an attribute below 8.
  Attributes below 8 are considered handicapped and/or disabled, and
  such a character would probably not be adventuring!</bold>  <emph>If the
  GM deems it OK, then you may reduce an attribute below 8, but you
  get NO benefits (you wouldn't get points in another attribute for
  example).  Why would you do this?  Simple, it's in your character
  concept.  Would a 6-year-old child have an 8 STR?  Not likely.</emph></text>

<text>When recording your attributes on the character sheet, record the number of
Attribute Points you spent on that attribute, this will help you when you wish
to increase them later.</text>

<text><bold>No attribute can be above a 20 for a natural human.  A 20 is
  considered the peak of human ability.  11 or so is average.  Below 8
  is considered handicapped for an adult human.  Note that certain
  things can increase attributes above 20, such as supernatural
  powers, magic, cybernetics, etc.</bold></text>

<text>Character Points (see next section) can be used to purchase Attribute Points
for increasing your attributes later on.</text>

        </section><!-- /Attributes -->
        <section><!-- SubAttr -->
            <title>Sub-Attributes</title>
<text>There are a number of <dquo>sub-attributes</dquo> that rely on your attributes to
determine their value.  The names, description, and method for determining
their value are listed below.</text>

<figure>
    <table>
        <head>
            <cell width="1in">Abbr.</cell>
            <cell width="3in">Definition</cell>
            <cell width="1.5in">Computation</cell>
        </head>
        <row>
            <cell><bold>Lift</bold></cell>
            <cell>This determines how much weight the character can lift in pounds, in a <dquo>good</dquo> situation, such as a weighted barbell or a trunk with handles.</cell>
            <cell><math>{STR*STR*BLD}\over{10}+STR</math></cell>
            <cell><bold>Carry</bold></cell>
            <cell>This is the amount of weight the character can carry about his/her person for a reasonable length of time.</cell>
            <cell><math>Lift \over 2</math></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><bold>Encumbrance</bold>
            </cell>
            <cell>This represents how much gear the character can wear before encountering adverse effects due to the weight and impaired mobility.</cell>
            <cell><math>{BLD+DEX+STR}\over 6</math></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><bold>Base Armor</bold></cell>
            <cell>Determines how resilient the character is to <dquo>odd</dquo> damage, such as lightning and fire.</cell>
            <cell><math>{BLD+WIL}\over 6</math></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><bold>Movement</bold></cell>
            <cell>How fast the character is in <dquo>squares per move-equivalent action.</dquo></cell>
            <cell><math>{2*STR+DEX}\over 15</math></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>\textbf{Perception}</cell>
            <cell>How well the character can notice things around him.  Used just like an attribute check.</cell>
            <cell><math>{DEX+2*KNO+INT}\over 4</math></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>\textbf{Interaction}</cell>
            <cell>The basic ability of a character to interact with other people.</cell>
            <cell><math>{CHA+KNO+INT}\over 3</math></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>\textbf{Hit Points}</cell>
            <cell>The amount of damage you can receive before dying.</cell>
            <cell><math>BLD+WIL</math></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell>\textbf{Magic Points}</cell>
            <cell>The number of Magic Points you can draw on to cast magic spells or perform supernatural feats</cell>
            <cell>$(WIL+BLD)*10$</cell>
        </row>
    </table>
    <caption>Sub-Attributes</caption>
</figure>

<text>Encumbrance, Base Armor, HP, and MP will be discussed in more detail in later
sections.  Keep this in mind as you may need to update them later.</text>
        </section><!-- /SubAttr -->
        <section><!-- CP -->
            <title>Character Points</title>
<text>The remainder of the character creation process is done through the expenditure
of Character Points, otherwise known as CP.  Talk with your GM about how many
CP you should use to create your character with.  We have found that for a
group of 3-4 players 125 CP is about right.  Typically the more players, the
fewer CP characters should have.  This will keep the group from becoming too
powerful---unless this is the GM's intent.</text>

<text>You will use your CP to <dquo>purchase</dquo> the remainder of your character.  The rest
of your character is broken into three categories where you will spend these
points:</text>

<itemized-list>
    <item>Mundane
        <description-list>
            <item description="Attributes"> increasing starting attributes</item>
            <item description="Skills" > normal skills, proficiency and knowledge of various topics</item>
            <item description="Combat Skills" > techniques for fighting and defense.</item>
        </description-list>
    </item>
    <item>Arcane / Magic
        <description-list>
            <item description="Spellcasting" />
            <item description="Psionics" />
            <item description="Witchcraft or Ritual Magic" />
            <item description="Supernatural abilities (super powers)" />
        </description-list>
    </item>
    <item>Technology
        <description-list>
            <item description="Mecha and Robotics" >Robotic bodies, limbs, powered armor, and robotic suits</item>
            <item description="Augmentations" >Cybernetics, genetic mutations, and chemical augmentations</item>
            <item description="Weapons" />
            <item description="Armor" />
            <item description="Equipment" > &amp; other material possessions</item>
        </description-list>
    </item>
</itemized-list>

<text><bold>IMPORTANT NOTE!</bold> <Apathy /> does not have <dquo>character classes</dquo> that are
common to many role-playing systems.  The <Apathy /> system allows the player
to decide every detail pertaining to his character, rather than being stuck
with a <dquo>default</dquo> set of abilities and skills.  It is up to the player to use
his CP to develop a well-rounded character.  Note that there are NO skills
that come <dquo>free.</dquo>  If your character is literate, then that skill needs
to be purchased.  Know how to drive a car?  Buy the skill.</text>

        </section><!-- /CP -->
        <section><!-- Inc Attr -->
        <title>Increasing Attributes (optional)</title>

<text>If your attributes aren't quite where you desire, you will need to get more
Attribute Points so you can purchase a better attribute.  Each Attribute Point
costs 1 Character Point.  Once you purchase the number of Attribute Points you
want, just look at the table found in the Attributes section above to see
how many total Attribute Points you must spend to get that attribute.</text>

<text>You must pay a number of Attribute Points equal to the difference between what
you want, and what you already have.  For example: if you currently have an 11
STR (6 Attribute Points) and wish to increase it to a 14 (21 Attribute Points)
that will cost you 15 Attribute Points ($9 - 4 = 5$).  Since Attribute Points
cost 1 Character Point each, going from an 11 in an attribute to a 14 will cost
15 CP.</text>

<text>Remember to keep track of how many Attribute Points you have spent on your
attributes so you can easily increase them at a later date.</text>
        </section><!-- /Inc Attr -->
    </section><!-- /Character -->
    <section><!-- Skills -->
        <title>Skills</title>
<text>All characters have skills.  Skills represent what your character has learned
and what they know how to do.  Other than being useful in game, skills help to
distinguish your character from everyone else in the world.  Are you going to
play a diplomat?  You better have diplomacy, law, and similar skills.  A
warrior?  Better have that shield and/or weapon skills handy!</text>

<text>Skills have a number of pieces of information associated with them.  They have
a \textbf{Rank}, \textbf{Associated Attribute}, \textbf{Description},
and \textbf{Level}.</text>

<text>The \textbf{rank} determines how hard a skill is to learn.  Higher the rank, the more
time and CP it will take to get better at it.  Rank 1 skills are the simplest
and easiest to learn.  Skills that are more difficult have higher ranks.  Rank
can also be thought of as the <dquo>cost</dquo> or <dquo>price</dquo> of a skill.</text>

<text>An \textbf{associated} attribute tells you what attribute is used in the skill roll.
This is the attribute that is used along with any particular skill.  This is
discussed in more detail below.</text>

<text>The \textbf{description} will let you know the scope of actions that a skill
encompasses.  The things listed are not the only things available under that
skill, but just some of the more common applications of the skill.  If you have
a question, ask your GM about his take on a particular skill.</text>

<text>\textbf{Level} is how good your particular character is at the skill. You will use CP
to purchase levels in a skill, which is discussed below.  If you don't know a
skill at all, you have Level 0 in that skill---meaning you don't know anything
about it.  The more you know about the skill, the higher your level.
This is often abbreviated as <dquo>Lvl</dquo> (alt. <dquo>LVL</dquo>).  You must purchase your
skill levels with CP.  Below is a simple chart indicating what different levels
correspond to:</text>

<figure>
    <table>
        <head>
            <cell align="center">\textbf{Level}</cell>
            <cell align="left">\textbf{What it means}</cell>
        </head>
            <row>
                <cell>0</cell>
                <cell>No knowledge of the skill.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>1</cell>
                <cell>Amateur.  You know something about it.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>2</cell>
                <cell>Had some training or experience</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>3</cell>
                <cell>Beginning professional or serious hobbyist</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>4</cell>
                <cell>Professional</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>5</cell>
                <cell>Experienced professional</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>6</cell>
                <cell>Exceptionally good.  Among the best in the country.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>7</cell>
                <cell>Among the best in the world.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>8+</cell>
                <cell>Among the best ever</cell>
            </row>
    </table>
        <caption>Skill Level and Descriptive Equivalents</caption>
</figure>

<text>Like most of character creation, skills are purchased using CP.  The higher
the rank, the more expensive it will be.  The higher the level you want in the
skill, the more expensive it will be.</text>

<text>For those that are mathematically inclined, here is the formula for determining
CP of a particular skill level and rank:</text>

<math>
\sum_{i=1}^{Desired Level = n} \left(Rank * i\right) = Rank * {{n^{2}+n}\over{2}}
</math>

<text>For the rest of us, use this nifty table, and multiply the value listed by the
rank.</text>

<figure>
    <table>
        <head>
            <cell align="left" border-right="1px black" />
            <cell align="center" /><cell align="center" /><cell align="center" />
            <cell align="center" /><cell align="center" /><cell align="center" />
            <cell align="center" /><cell align="center" /><cell align="center" />
            <cell align="center" />
        </head>
        <row>
            <cell><bold>Desired Level</bold></cell>
            <cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell>
            <cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell>
            <cell>7</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell>
            <cell>10</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><bold>CP Cost for Rank 1</bold></cell>
            <cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell>
            <cell>10</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>21</cell>
            <cell>28</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>45</cell>
            <cell>55</cell>
        </row>
    </table>
    <caption>CP cost of Desired Level, precomputed</caption>
</figure>

<text>See the trend?</text>

<text>If not, here's yet another way to look at purchasing skills.</text>

<text>To get level 1 of a skill, you must spend the Rank in CP.  To get to the next
level, add the rank of the skill to the amount of CP you spent the last time you
increase the skill (and just that last increase, not the total amount you've spent
on the skill) and that is the amount that you need to spend.</text>

    <example>
        <title>Computing Skill Cost</title>
        <text>I want to purchase the shield skill
(rank 2).  To get Lvl 1
I would need to spend
2 CP.  Now, if I want to go from Lvl 1, to Lvl 2, I would add the rank (2) to
the amount I spent on the last level increase (2 CP), to get the new cost, in
this case I would need to spend a total of 4 CP (rank of 2 + 2 CP from last
purchase).  So now the total amount I have spent on this skill is 6 CP.  Lets say
I'm not happy with my Lvl 2 shield skill, and wish to upgrade it to level 3.
I would again take the rank (2) and add it to the amount I spent on the last
increase (4) to get the number of CP I must spend to upgrade the skill.  In this
case, I must spend an additional 6 CP.  Therefore, to get a level 3 shield skill
(or any skill or rank 2), I must spend a total of 12 CP.</text>
    </example>

<text>If you take a look at the little chart above, you will see that at the desired
skill level (3) the CP cost is a 6, which I then multiply by the rank (2) to get
12 CP, the same thing I got when I did it out by hand.</text>

<text>Note that the chart will only tell you how many total Character Points.  To get
the number of CP needed to increase to the next level, just subtract the upper
number from the lower one.  A more complete version of the above table can be
found at the end of this manual.</text>

<text>Once you are in game and earning experience, you can increase the level of a
skill you currently have at least one level in by paying the appropriate CP
cost.  If you wish to learn the first level of a skill you don't have yet, it
takes a number of weeks of intense studying equal to the rank of the skill.</text>
        <section><!-- Skill Spec -->
            <title>Skill Specialization (optional)</title>
            <section><!-- Spec Most -->
                <title>Specialization in most Skills</title>
<text>It is possible to specialize in many skills.  When specialized, a character
knows more about a certain aspect of the skill than other parts of the skill.
In game terms, you are +1 LVL when performing a check in the area of your
specialization, but are -4 to your roll when you are performing a check outside
of your specialization.  Specializing does NOT cost any extra CP.</text>

    <example>
        <title>History$\rightarrow$Spanish</title>
        <text>Ralf Gr\"osse-Kunstleve is a historian.
Specifically, he is knowledgeable
about Spanish history. He has a LVL 3 History skill with a specialization in
Spanish History.  This means that if Juan had to make a skill check related to
Spanish history, he would roll 4 dice.  (3 from his LVL, +1 from the specialty.)
However, if he had to make a History roll about another kind of history, he
would only roll 3 dice, and be at a -4 to his roll.</text>
    </example>

<text>Note that you can choose to buy a particular skill more than once with different
specialties, if you feel like it.  When this happens the roll for <dquo>outside
of specialty</dquo> skill checks is the highest of the skill levels -4 +1 for each
skill beyond the first.</text>

    <example>
        <title>Chemistry$\rightarrow$WMD</title>
        <text>Dr. Klo\t{tz}enstein is a scientist.
He has LVL 3 Chemistry with a specialty in
Chemical weapons and poisons.  As well, he has LVL 4 Chemistry with a
specialization in the chemistry of explosives.  Dr. Klotzenstein's rolls are
as follows:

\noindent For Weapons/poisons: 4 dice \\
\noindent For Explosives: 5 dice \\
\noindent For Non-specialty rolls, 5 dice -3.}</text>
    </example>

<text>It is possible to specialize in most skills.  Talk to your GM about specializing
to see which skills you think are appropriate and which ones are not.</text>

<text><bold>Specializing in skills is purely optional.</bold></text>
            </section><!-- /Spec Most -->
            <section><!-- Spec Wpn -->
                <title>Specialization applied to Weapon skills</title>
<text>It is also possible to specialize in weapon skills.  If a character has a
specialized weapon skill that means that he is especially proficient with a
very specific type of weapon.  When wielding a weapon that matches a character's
specialty, that character receives +1 LVL to the skill.  This bonus applies to
attack (strike) rolls, and defensive rolls (parry), if applicable.  When using
a weapon that is outside the character's specialty, the character is at -1 LVL.
Note that Weapon skill specialization does NOT affect damage rolls.</text>

<text>\textbf{Specializing in a weapons skill costs 3 CP in addition to the normal cost of the
skill. Specializing can be applied to all weapon proficiency type skills and
the shield skill.}</text>

    <example>
        <title>Axes$\rightarrow$Nordic War Axe</title>
        <text>Bj\o{}rgen
is a warrior with a liking for the Nordic War Axe.
He has the skill
<dquo>Archaic Weapons: Axes</dquo> at level 3.  As well, he is specialized in the Nordic
War Axe.  The total skill cost is 9 CP.  That is 6 CP for Level 3 in a Rank 1
skill, Plus 3 CP from the specialization.  When welding a Genuine Nordic War
Axe~\texttrademark in combat, Gunnar has 4 dice.  However, when using any other
kind of axe Gunnar only has 2 dice.</text>
    </example>

<text>Note that some unusual or esoteric weapons \emph{require} specialization.
This is because those weapons are different enough from common weapons that
they require special knowledge and experience in order to use them properly.</text>

<text>Most characters that specialize in weapons are very particular about their
weapons.  For the character it is almost an obsessive-compulsive issue to
wield a particular weapon.  Generally the weapon must be very specific in order
to satisfy the specialty.  In medieval campaigns, a weapon specialty might
require a sword forged by a particular smith, or arrows made from a certain
type of wood.  In a modern campaign, a weapon specialty might entail a particular
make and model of rifle.</text>

<text>\textbf{Specializing in skills is purely optional.}</text>

            </section><!-- /Spec Wpn -->
        </section><!-- /Skill Spec -->

    </section><!-- /Skills -->
    <section><!-- Rolls -->
        <title>Rules (Rolls)</title>
<text>What would an RPG be without rules?  <Apathy /> has a set of rules that allow
for just about any occurrence that an imaginative GM can put the players through.</text>

<text>Lets start with the basics (some of this will be review):</text>

<text>In <Apathy />, there are \emph{three} different types of die rolls.  Every time
you roll a die when playing <Apathy />, you will use one of these sets of rules.</text>

        <section><!-- Attr Chks -->
    <title>Attribute Checks</title>

<text>Attribute checks are required anytime the GM wants to see if you did something
solely based on an attribute.  They are used whenever a player wants their 
character to do something tricky.  Attribute checks are purely based on a 
character's core attributes.  They are completely separate from skills.  If a 
player needs to do something based on a particular skill, then see the skill 
roll section below.</text>

    <example>
        <title>Catch a Pack</title>
        <text>Barnacleez is trying
to catch a pack that was thrown at him.  The GM 
requires him to make a DEX check to see if he successfully caught the pack.</text>
    </example>

    <example>
        <title>Swim a Long Distance</title>
        <text>Thomas is trying to
swim a long distance while carrying a heavy load.
He has to roll a BLD check to see if he has enough stamina to make the swim.</text>
    </example>

    <example>
        <title>Decipher Symbols</title>
        <text>Wendy is trying to
decipher the meaning of some strange symbols written 
on a wall.  Since she has no applicable skills, the GM determines that she needs 
to make an INT check in order to figure out what they mean.</text>

<text>Attribute checks are always rolled the same.  Roll ONE twenty-sided die, add 
the attribute to the die, and add any bonuses or negatives.  If the total (die 
roll + attribute + bonuses + negatives) is 25 or higher, then the check 
succeeded.  If you roll a 1, you fail automatically, no matter what your bonuses 
or attributes are.  If you roll a 20, you succeed automatically, no matter what 
the negatives might be.  \textbf{For an attribute check, you always roll just one 
20-sided die.</text>
    </example>
        </section><!-- /Attr Chks -->
        <section><!-- Contest of Attr -->
        <title>Contest of Attributes</title>
<text><bold>Contests of Attributes</bold> occur whenever two characters are competing at 
something that is largely dependent on an attribute and nothing else.  Arm 
wrestling is a contest of strength.   Racing to complete a puzzle is a contest 
of intelligence.  A trivia game would be a contest of wisdom, etc.</text>

<text>A contest of attributes occurs \emph{only} when there are multiple competitors 
(generally two) and \emph{only} when there is no particular skill involved.  For 
example, arm wrestling is a contest of strength but a game of 1-on-1 basketball 
is generally \emph{not}, because basketball is a complex game.</text>

<text>When a contest of attributes occurs, all competitors roll 1D4 and add the
result to their attribute.  The highest score wins, and like scores tie.
The GM may wish to impose negatives and/or bonuses depending on the exact
circumstances of the contest.</text>

<example>
    <title>Dougles vs. Enemy Soldier</title>
    <text>Douglas (STR 13) is fighting with an 
enemy solider (STR 12) over the possession of a single rifle.  The GM 
declares that a contest of strength will resolve who manages to gain 
possession of the rifle.  The GM rolls for the solider (a three) and 
Douglas rolls a 1.  The enemy soldier has a total of 15, and Douglas 
has 14.  Therefore, the enemy soldier wrestles the rifle out of
Douglas's hands.</text></example>
        </section><!-- /Contest of Attr -->
        <section><!-- Skill Rolls -->
            <title>Skill Rolls</title>
<text><bold>Skill rolls</bold>are used whenever a player wants to use one of his
character's skills.  They are also used whenever two characters are competing
at something (Contest of skills) related to a skill. \textbf{Skill rolls are also used
<dquo>to strike</dquo> or <dquo>to defend</dquo> in combat.}</text>

<text>To determine if you are successful in performing a skill, roll a number of D20s 
equal to the Level you have purchased the skill in.  To \emph{each} die, add 
your 
current attribute referenced by the associated attribute value of the skill.  
Each time a die with this value added to it reaches 25 or above, this is called 
a success.  If you have at least one success, you successfully performed the 
skill.  Rolling a <dquo>20</dquo> on a die will give you +1 successes to however many 
you rolled normally.  Note that this makes it possible to have more successes 
than you have levels in a given skill.  Likewise, a roll of <dquo>1</dquo> is -1 
successes to your total.  If you have negative successes (caused by rolling 
more 1s than successes) then you have a critical failure!  In the case of a 
critical failure the GM will determine what (negative) outcome happens!</text>

<!-- CONTINUE HERE -->

<figure>
    <table>
        <head>
            <cell align="center">Roll</cell>
            <cell align="left">Sample Outcome</cell>
        </head>
            <row>
                <cell>Strike (sword)</cell>
                <cell>Sword breaks or is dropped</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>Strike (gun)</cell>
                <cell>gun jams or misfires</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>Parry</cell>
                <cell>you drop your weapon and are struck by the incoming blow</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>Diplomacy</cell>
                <cell>you make a faux pas that offends the parties involved</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>Deception</cell>
                <cell>you are caught <dquo>red handed</dquo> in a blatant lie</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>Medicine</cell>
                <cell>you make an outright mistake, harming the patient.</cell>
            </row>
        </table>
    <caption>Sample outcome for Skill Rolls</caption>
</figure>

<text>The GM will give penalties and/or bonuses to your skill roll based on the 
difficulty of the action you are performing and what circumstances may be 
surrounding it.  When such a negative or bonus is given, this is subtracted 
from the associated attribute value, not the number of dice rolled for a skill.</text>

<text>Basically stated, skill rolls work like this:  Roll 1D20 for each level you 
have in the skill.  To each die, add your associated attribute and any 
negatives 
or bonuses the GM gives you.  If the total on each die is 25 or greater that is 
a success.  If the die rolls a 20, regardless of bonuses, attributes, etc. you 
get +1 successes.  If a die rolls a 1, regardless of bonuses, etc. you get -1 
success.</text>

<text>Note that the \textsc{Maximum} you can ever add to your die roll---no 
matter how high 
your attribute or bonuses to succeed might be---is 20.</text>

<text>Also, if you are doing something simple with respect to your skill level 
then you don't have to roll dice at all.  It's assumed that you succeed 
examples.</text>

    <example>
        <title>Lookup Internt Address</title>
        <text>Amy has the Computer
Use skill at level 3.  She wants to look up an 
Internet address on the computer that she thinks might give the players some 
needed information.  Since this is a simple task and she has a significant 
level in the associated skill (Computer Use), then the GM rules that she does 
so automatically, with no roll needed.</text>
    </example>

    <example>
        <title>Investigate Mysterious Person</title>
        <text>Amy is still on the Internet.
Now she is attempting to dig up some 
information about a mysterious person.  The GM determines that Amy needs to 
use her Level 2 Investigation skill.  Amy has a 13 WIS, the associated 
attribute 
for Investigation.  The GM tells her that this is a normal difficulty skill, 
and there is no bonus or negative.  So Amy rolls 2D20 for the skill and rolls a 
6 and a 13.  After adding her WIS to each roll, she has a 19 and a 26.
Only the 
26 is a success since it is 25 or above.  Since she has at least one success,
Amy 
is able to find the information she was looking for.</text>
    </example>

    <example>
        <title>Fix a Beater</title>
        <text>Chris is trying
to fix an old car so he and his fellow characters can use 
it.  The GM determines that this falls under the Mechanic: General skill.  Chris
has a level 2 in that skill.  Furthermore, the GM determines that since the car 
is in really bad shape, that Chris has a -3 to his roll.  Chris has a 12 DEX.  
Chris rolls his dice and gets a 1 and a 16. (Chris is rolling two dice because 
he has a level 2 skill)  Adding his DEX to those rolls, Chris now has a 13 and 
a 28.  The 13 isn't 25 or above, so it fails, but the 28 succeeds.  So far, 
Chris has 1 success.  However, the <dquo>1</dquo> Chris rolled is -1 success.  So, this 
gives Chris a total of 0 successes---meaning the car didn't get fixed.</text>
    </example>

    <example>
        <title>Shoot a Large Robot</title>
        <text>Billy is
a cybernetic gunfighter with a 22 DEX.  He is trying to shoot an 
enemy robot.  The GM determines that Billy gets a bonus of +3 to shoot the 
robot because it's so large.  Normally, Billy would roll his dice and add +25 
to each one:  +22 from his DEX and +3 from the size bonus.  However, this gets 
capped at +20.  Thus, Billy only gets to add +20 to each of his dice.</text>
    </example>

    <example>
        <title>Called Shot to Arm</title>
        <text>Billy is still fighting the same
giant robot.  This time, he's trying to 
make a called shot and shoot the robot in the arm.  The GM determines that 
Billy gets a +3 bonus due to the robot's size, but also a -4 to strike because 
of the called shot to the arm.  Thus, Billy adds up his bonuses:  +22 from DEX 
+3 from size and -4 for the called shot.  This adds up to +21, but the bonus 
is capped at +20.  Again, Billy adds +20 to his dice.  Notice that the <dquo>+20 
cap</dquo> is applied AFTER all the bonuses and negatives are added up.</text>
    </example>
        </section><!-- /Skill Rolls -->
        <section><!-- Contest of Skills -->
            <title>Contest of Skills</title>
<text><bold>A contest of skills occurs when two people are trying 
to defeat each other in some manner with their skills.</bold>
If two characters were competing to see who could sing better, the 
character with the largest number of successes of the singing skill 
would win.  The most common example of this is combat.  In order to 
be successful in a combat situation---such as attempting to hit an 
opponent with a sword while he is blocking with a shield, the 
initiator (or attacker) of the action must make more successes 
than the defender.</text>

<example>
    <title>Tom and the Shopkeeper in a Contest</title>
    <text>Tom is attempting 
to purchase an expensive suit of armor, and doesn't want to pay 
full price.  So he is attempting to bring the price down by using 
the Bargaining skill.  The shopkeeper also has the Bargaining skill, 
so a contest of skills ensues.  Tom has a skill level of 3, and a 
WIS of 13 (the associated attribute for Bargaining); the shopkeeper 
has a level 4 Bargaining (he's been at it longer than Tom has), 
and a WIS of 10.

Tom rolls 3 dice and gets a <dquo>14</dquo>, <dquo>20</dquo>, and a <dquo>3</dquo>.  Tom now 
adds his wisdom (13) to each of these.  The GM didn't give any 
negatives or bonuses, so that is all that gets added.  After adding, 
the totals are 27, 33, and 16.  Two of these are 25 or higher, so Tom 
has two successes so far.  Note that Tom rolled one 20---which gives him 
an additional success.  Tom has a total of three successes.
 
The shopkeeper rolls four dice (remember, he has a level 4 Bargaining), 
and gets a <dquo>1</dquo>, <dquo>12</dquo>, <dquo>15'</dquo>, and an <dquo>18</dquo>.  After adding the 
shopkeeper's WIS of 10, we get the following rolls: <dquo>11</dquo>, <dquo>22</dquo>, 
<dquo>25</dquo>, and <dquo>28</dquo>.  The 25 and 28 are both successes, but the 
<dquo>1</dquo> is a -1 success, so the shopkeeper has 1 total success.

Tom has 3 successes, and the shopkeeper has 1.  Since Tom initiated 
the bargaining, and has more successes than the <dquo>defender</dquo>, he is 
successful in his attempt to reduce the price of the armor.  How
much is determined by the GM, but it should be commensurate with 
the number of successes that Tom beat the shopkeeper by.</text>
</example>

<text>The winner of a contest of skills is whomever rolled the highest 
number of successes.  The margin of success is based on the difference 
between the two rolls.  For example, if the <dquo>winner</dquo> had only 1 more 
success than the <dquo>loser</dquo>, then the contest was close.  However, if 
the <dquo>winner</dquo> had three more successes than the loser, then it was a 
decisive victory!</text>

<text>Ties are left up to the GM to resolve.  The suggested protocol is as follows:</text>

<text>If the tie occurred on a contest that entails a single past event or 
is something that is <dquo>judged</dquo> by outsiders, then the winner is the 
character with the higher associated attribute.  (Example: who can 
paint a better picture, etc.)</text>

<text>If the contest entails an ongoing event (such as the haggling over a 
suit of armor detailed above) then it is assumed that the competitors 
<dquo>keep at it</dquo> and a second roll is in order.</text>

<text>The rules for combat are slightly more complicated; see below.</text>

        </section><!-- /Contest of Skills -->
        <section><!-- Skills Rolls and Related -->
            <title>Skill Rolls and Related Skills</title>
<text>If a character needs to make a skill roll and that character knows 
other skills that are somehow related to (or are similar to) the 
skill to be rolled, that character is generally entitled to a bonus 
to his or her roll.  The exact terms of the bonus, including what 
skills qualify as <dquo>related</dquo>, is determined by the GM on a case-by-case 
basis.  The general rule is that each level of a related skill conveys 
a +1 to the roll.  The maximum possible bonus from related skills is 
+5, regardless of the circumstances.</text>

<example>
    <title>Paul repairing a device</title>
    <text>Paul is attempting to repair an 
electronic device.  The GM asks Paul to roll his Electronics skill, 
which Paul has at lvl 4.  Paul mentions that he also knows the 
skills Electrical Engineering: 2, Electrician: 3, Mechanic: General: 3, 
and Communications/Telco: 3.  The GM determines that since this device 
is purely electronic, Paul's Mechanic skill is of no use.  As well, the 
GM decides that since this device is unrelated to communications, 
Paul's Communications skill does not apply either.  However, the GM 
decides that Paul's Electrical Engineering and Electrician skills 
are relevant.  The GM assigns Paul a bonus of +5 to his roll from his 
levels in those related skills.</text>
</example>

<text><bold>Related Skill bonuses NEVER apply to 
combat skills or any skill used in a combat situation.</bold></text>

        </section><!-- /Skills Rolls and Related -->
        <section><!-- All Other Rolls -->
            <title>All Other Rolls</title>
<text>This type of die rolling is used for just about everything else in 
the game: rolling damage from combat, the duration of magical spells, 
or the number of monsters appearing in a group.</text>

<text>Rolling dice is represented in the XDY+Z format; for example 
3D4+1.  This means that you roll three individual 4-sided dice, 
and add 1 to each die.</text>

<text>If any die roll with its bonus added in equals or betters the maximum 
value on a die, then you get a \textbf{rollover}.  When a 
rollover happens, re-roll that die, without any bonus, and add its 
value to the total.  If the roll again has the highest value on the 
die, then another rollover happens.  This keeps going until the 
highest value on the die is not rolled.  \textbf{Remember, after 
the first roll, the bonus is not applied; it's just the 
raw die roll.}</text>

<text>This may sound confusing, so we'll work with the example from above.
Let's say you have to roll 3D4+1.  You get some four-sided dice and 
roll three of them.  Suppose the results are: 1, 3, and a 4.  After 
adding the +1 (from the die bonus), we now have: 2, 4, and 5.  We add 
all the totals up and get 11.  Now we have to deal with the rollovers.
Because the highest value on a four-sided dice is a 4, we have two 
rollovers: the 4 and 5.  So we roll each of these again, 
\textbf{without the original bonus}, and get a 2 and 4.  We add 
these to the total yielding 17.  But wait, we have yet another 
rollover (the 4).  So we roll that die again, and get a 3.  We now 
have a total of a 20 for our 3D4+1 die roll.</text>

<text>The same rules apply for any die.  Lets say you are rolling six-sided 
dice.  If any die (after bonuses) has a 6 or higher, then you get a 
rollover.  On an eight-sided die?  You guessed it; a roll of 8 or higher 
will yield a rollover.</text>

<text>If you have bonuses or negatives to a roll, add them up first, 
then perform the final roll.</text>

<text>Note that if there is a minus to the die roll once all the 
bonuses/penalties are added up, then no rollover is possible.  An 
example is 1D4-1.  Even if you roll a 4 on the die it will be reduced 
to a 3, which does not yield a rollover.  \textbf{No die (even 
after negatives) can give a value less than 1}.  So, if you 
have a 1D6-4, and roll a 2 (which would theoretically total -2), 
then the actual total would be 1.</text>

<text>Along with what is given above, die rolls might have a 
\textbf{raw bonus}.  This is represented by a bonus in brackets 
such as this: 3D4+1 [+4] (alt. 4+3D4+1).  Raw Bonuses are 
added to the resultant total of a die roll, NOT to each die; thus 
they do not affect rollovers at all.  This bonus is added in after 
all the rollovers are done with.  Consider the prior example of 
3D4+1 but with the [+4] added.  That would be written 3D4+1 [+4].
The total using the above numbers would be 24. </text>

<text>Unless otherwise stated, \emph{all non-skill die rolls use this system}.</text>
        </section><!-- /All Other Rolls -->
    </section><!-- /Rolls -->
    <section><!-- Combat Sequence and Initiative -->
        <title>Combat Sequence &amp; Initiative</title>

<text>Combat is based on a system of \textit{Rounds}, \textit{Turns}, and
\textit{Actions}.  A <dquo>round</dquo> lasts about five seconds.  It is the
length of time in which all combatants have done something.  Each
round is broken down into actions.  An action lasts about 1 second.
Each combatant gets one or more actions during each round.  When all
combatants have used up their actions, the current round is over and a
new one starts.</text>

<text>During your turn, you determine what you wish to do with your
available actions.  Almost everything that you do of significance
during your turn consumes an action.  Simple examples of what can be
done in an action are shooting a gun, swing a sword, moving, or using
a mystical ability.  Keep in mind that a lot of <dquo>boring</dquo> combat
stuff also takes up actions: reloading your weapon, moving around,
ducking behind cover, or taking an item out of your pack.  Some things
that you will want to do will consume multiple actions per turn.</text>

<img src="/MartialArts/Cpg359-49v.jpg" />

<text>All characters, by default, have \emph{three} actions per round.
Certain skills or in-game effects might change this.  When combat is
going to start, all players need to figure out how many actions they
get.  (typically, this will be 3 each).</text>

<text>At the beginning of combat, all characters must roll initiative.  This
determines who attacks first in the turn.  When combat starts,
participants must roll a 1D20 for their initiative. If any characters
have more than 3 actions per turn (due to a skill or magical effect or
somesuch), then those characters must roll initiative twice.</text>

<text>Various bonuses or penalties apply to initiative rolls.  Certain
skills and magical effects can alter initiative.  As well, the GM may
apply initiative bonuses or penalties depending on game situations,
such as surprise attacks or ambushes.</text>

<text>\textbf{Most characters will have 3 actions per turn.  All 
three actions are 
taken at the same time, on that character's initiative.}</text>

<example>
    <title>Tom's Turn in Combat</title>
    <text>Tom is in combat.
Tom has three actions and he rolled an 11 as his 
initiative.  When it's Tom's turn in combat (11), he takes all three actions at 
that time.</text>
</example>

<text>The character that has the highest initiative goes first, and then the 
character with the next highest initiative takes their turn, and so 
forth down the line until all combatants have taken a turn.</text>

<text>Once all turns are over, the current round of combat is over.  It then 
restarts with everyone's initiative being the same as it was in the previous 
round.  This progression continues until combat is over.  If the combatants 
change significantly during combat---for example, if new characters show up on 
the scene---the GM might want to make everyone re-roll their initiative.  If 
something happens during combat that changes how many actions the combatants 
have, the GM should ask that initiative be re-rolled.</text>

<text>Some things that you might want to do will take up multiple actions.  A common 
example of this is spell casting, where many spells take several actions to 
cast.  If you do this, you may need to drag this type of action across multiple 
actions or even multiple turns.  For example, let's say that you want to cast 
a spell that takes 3 actions.  You can use your first action to start casting, 
and then use your second and third actions to finish casting the spell.   At 
any time you may cancel (stop casting) the spell or ability with no penalty.  
When an ability or activity requires multiple actions, it always takes place 
on the final action that completes that activity.  Also, it is possible to be 
disturbed or disrupted if you are attacked while performing a multiple-action 
activity.  The GM should take note of this and might impose skill checks or 
other chances of failure if you get knocked around too much.</text>

<text>\textbf{Note that everything you may wish to do in combat 
requires one or more actions.  
This includes moving around, drawing a weapon, 
using items, etc.  Undoubtedly, 
many of your actions will be used for things 
other than attacking.}</text>

<text>When in combat, some characters may want to delay their action until 
later.  A character can always choose to <dquo>act later</dquo> in combat.  
When doing so the player states what new initiative number he 
wishes to act on.  The new initiative must be lower than his 
current initiative number.  Once a character's initiative is 
delayed it remains delayed (though it could be delayed even further).  
That characters initiative remains at the new, lower, number for the 
remainder of combat, unless the GM asks all players to re-roll 
initiative.  Actions cannot be split between different initiative 
numbers.  So, a character must either take all his actions at his 
normal initiative, or he must delay all his actions to a later initiative.</text>

<example>
    <title>Tom's initiative</title>
    <text>Tom's initiative roll is an 18.  He 
and his fellow players were cornered by ogres for whom the GM has 
secretly rolled initiative.  Tom has the highest initiative roll, so 
he goes first.  Tom isn't exactly sure what to do, so he delays 
his initiative until <dquo>10</dquo>.  The GM then resumes combat as normal, 
with the next highest initiative going first.  Tom has initiative 10 
for the remainder of combat.</text>
</example>


<text>Some game effects last a certain number of turns, or have a certain 
effect each turn.  These effects are counted and take place on 
the affected character's turn.  They only are counted and occur 
if the character begins that turn with the effect in place.  
These effects occur at the beginning of that character's turn 
in a given round.  These effects are automatic and do not consume 
any time from the character.  Resolve all effects before that 
character takes any actions. </text>

<example>
    <title>Lucy's turn in combat</title>
    <text>It is Lucy's turn in 
combat and she casts Regeneration on herself.  The effect of the 
spell is that each turn she gains 1D4+1 hit points.  Now the spell 
has taken effect, but she does not gain any HP yet, nor does this 
turn count against the duration of the spell.  Now all other 
combatants take their turns.  When it is again Lucy's 
turn (next round) she gains her 1D4+1 HP, just before 
her first action.  This is also considered one turn out of the 
spell's duration.</text>
</example>

<text>It is possible to <dquo>hold an action</dquo> for later.  Holding an 
action means that the character is maintaining his current 
initiative number, but is saving an action for a specific 
situation.  A character may only hold one action at a time.  
Furthermore, you must declare what your held action will be, and 
under what circumstances.  Held actions are resolved as soon 
as their conditions are met.  Held actions <dquo>expire</dquo> if their 
declared conditions never occur at the beginning of your next turn.</text>

<example>
    <title>Tom holds an action</title>
    <text>Tom's initiative is 10.  During 
his turn he spends one action to move behind some cover and another 
to ready his longbow.  Tom declares that he is going to hold his 
final action:  <dquo>I am going to cover the hallway with my 
bow.  If I see a goblin come out of the hallway, I'm going to 
shoot at it</dquo>.  If a goblin does indeed come out of the hallway (and 
Tom can see this), then Tom may immediately take his held action to 
fire an arrow at it.  However, if no goblin comes down the 
hallway before Tom's next turn, then the held action is wasted.</text>
</example>

<text>Notes for held actions:</text>
<numbered-list>
    <item> You may only hold one action at a time</item>
    <item> You must state specifically what the conditions for 
your held action must be, and what your action will be once 
those conditions are met.</item>
    <item> Your held action can be any activity you could do 
in one action (including attacking, moving, using a magical ability, etc.)</item>
    <item> Held actions are lost if their triggering conditions never occur.</item>
</numbered-list>
        <section><!-- Weapons and Equipment -->
            <title>Weapons &amp; Equipment</title>
<text>Most characters will carry equipment in combat.  This usually includes
weapons and armor.  There are no <dquo>class</dquo> restrictions for weapons or
armor.  Any character can wear any armor and wield any weapon,
provided that the character has the appropriate attributes and skills.</text>

<text>Weapons have a \emph{minimum strength requirement} (MSR).  The MSR
indicates what strength is required of the character to properly wield
a given weapon.  If the character's strength is \textit{less} than the
MSR, then the character has -1 to strike and [-1] damage for each
point of strength difference.</text>

<text>The \emph{raw damage bonus} (RDB) is calculated by subtracting 8 from
the wielder's \textscbf{Str}. The RDB is added as \emph{raw} damage to
total of the weapon's damage. However, all weapons have a
\emph{maximum strength bonus} (MSB); if the RDB is greater than the
MSB, then the MSB is used as the RDB instead.</text>

<example>
    <title>MSR for Bosk</title>
    <text>Bosk has a STR of 17 and is brandishing a
  Hercules Club (3D6C, MSR: 12, MSB: 13).  Because Bosk's
  \textscbf{Str} is higher than the minimum strength requirement of
  the Hercules Club (12), he is entitled to a damage bonus.  Subtract
  8 from Bosk's \textscbf{Str} score to calculate his bonus: $17 - 8 =
  9$. So this means that Bosk deals 9+3D6 C damage.</text>
</example>


<example>
    <title>Bosk with Knife</title>
    <text>Suppose Bosk pulls out a long knife
  (1D6+1 S, MSR: 8; MSB: 4).  Bosk's \textscbf{Str} is significantly
  higher than the minimum required for the weapon.  Calculating his
  theoretical bonus, we can write: 17 - 8 = 9.  At first glance, it
  appears that Bosk is entitled to a [+9] bonus.  However, the maximum
  strength bonus for the long knife is 4. Therefore, Bosk's damage
  roll would be 4+1D6+1.</text>
</example>


<text>Bows never grant a damage bonus to characters with higher than 
required STR.  However, it is possible to purchase stiffer (stronger) 
bows that can take advantage of a character's higher STR score.  
High-draw bows cost 20\% more for every 1 STR point added to the 
MSR.  For each point, add [+1] damage.  This can be stacked.  So, a 
+1 bow costs 20\% extra, a +2 bow costs 40\% extra, etc.  Note 
that the maximum STR requirement that can be added to a bow of a 
given type is equal to half of its original MSR.  Note that the 
damage and strike penalty for having a lower-than-required STR does 
apply to bows.  Modern compound bows are adjustable and can be set 
to a higher than normal strength value without incurring additional cost.</text>

<img src="/Magic/Lion-faced_deity.jpg" />

<text>Characters will have two hands that they may use to wield weapons.
All weapons are either one-hand or two-handed.  Two-handed weapons, of
course, require both hands to properly wield.  One-handed weapons
require only one hand.  Therefore a player could wield one single-hand
weapon, one two-handed weapon, two single-hand weapons, or one
single-hand weapon and a shield or other item. However, when wielding
two weapons the character can have penalties. Also, wielding two
weapons does not grant the ability to the character to strike with
both weapons in one action. In general, wielding two weapons gives the
user -3 and -6 to strike with the primary and off -hand
(respectively), and requires an additional action. These penalties can
be mitigated with skills from \emph{Martial Arts}.</text>

<text>Characters that use magic, aside from Martial Magic, must have at 
least one hand free when casting spells. 
Characters that use Faith magic must have a holy symbol in their 
grasp when casting magic; this requires a free hand to hold.  
Spellcasters are free to use two-handed weapons so long as they 
aren't wielding the weapon at the same time as they are 
casting spells.  (Spellcasters can put away a weapon, cast magic 
freely, and then draw their weapon again, though this takes time)</text>

<text>All firearms are assumed to be 2-handed by default.  However, pistols 
and submachine guns may be fired with one hand.  (See rules for using 
2-handed weapons with one hand below).  Larger firearms including 
rifles, shotguns, and heavy weapons (rocket launchers, etc.) must always 
be used 2-handed.  It always requires two hands to reload a firearm, 
no matter what kind it is.</text>

<text>Bows are always two-handed weapons.  Hand (small) crossbows can be 
aimed and fired with one hand.  However, cocking and re-loading 
a crossbow always requires two hands.  Larger crossbows always 
require two hands to fire as well as load.  Siege weapons, cannons, 
heavy weapons, etc, always require both hands to be free in order 
to load, aim, and fire.</text>

<text>It is possible to use two hands to fight with a one-handed weapon.  
In this case, the wielder has -1 to strike and effectively adds +3 
to his strength.</text>

<text>It is possible to use some two-handed weapons with one hand.  To do 
so, add 4 to the minimum strength requirement of the weapon.  Note 
that many two-handed weapons always require two hands, period.  These 
are large firearms (rifles, shotguns), staves, pole arms, chains, and bows.  </text>

        </section><!-- /Weapons and Equipment -->
        <section><!-- Dual-wielding Weapons or Weapon and Shield -->
            <title>Dual-wielding Weapons or Weapon &amp; Shield</title>
<text>As noted above, it is possible for characters to wield two weapons in
combat, or a weapon and a shield. A character \emph{cannot} attack
with both weapons during the same action unless he takes the
\emph{Multi-weapon style} skill in \emph{Martial Arts}.  A character
using a weapon and a shield \emph{may not} attack with his weapon and
shield bash in the same action, for the same reason.  When attacking
with both weapons the character makes two separate attack rolls, one
for each weapon; each attack is resolved separately. This takes two
separate actions.</text>

<description-list>
    <item description="Two normal weapons"> When wielding two weapons the weapon in the
  character's <dquo>good</dquo> hand receives a -3 to strike and the weapon in
  the character's <dquo>off</dquo> hand receives a -6. Some characters can have
  <dquo>even-more-offhand</dquo> weapons, such as a kick (or two), or literally
  having extra limbs. To calculate the negative to strike for wielding
  multiple weapons, first find the number of weapons being used, then
  order them (the strike order). The first weapon is at -3 to strike,
  the second at -6, the third ad -9, and so on, i.e. the k$^{th}$
  weapon is at -3*k to strike.</item>

    <item description="Paired weapons">, or one normal weapon and one backup weapon:
  Some weapons are well suited to, or even designed for, use in the
  <dquo>off</dquo> hand.  When using these weapons the penalty for the offhand
  weapon is -3 as opposed to -6.  The penalty for the primary weapon
  remains -3.  Specifically, these combinations are:

        <numbered-list>
            <item>Any type of knife may be used in the off-hand in combination
    with any standard (non exotic) one-handed weapon in the main hand.</item>
            <item>Two Kris, or one Kris Datoh (main hand) and one Kris (off
    hand).</item>
            <item>One Katana (main hand) and one Wakizashi (off hand), but only
    if the wielder is specialized in both weapons and takes the
    appropriate penalty for using the Katana one-handed.</item>
            <item>Any weapon that is normally used in pairs, such as Sai, Kama,
    tonfa, nunchaku, or Iron Claws.</item>
            <item>Two identical handguns, but only with the appropriate penalty
    for using them one-handed.</item>
        </numbered-list>
    </item>

    <item description="One normal weapon and a shield or item"> If the character is
  wielding a 1-handed weapon in his <dquo>good</dquo> hand, and his other hand
  is carrying a shield, a non-weapon holy symbol, or a utility item
  then there is NO strike penalty at all.  For the purposes of this
  rule a utility item is something such as a torch, walking stick,
  magical totem, leash, or bag.  Utility items are not weapons and
  must not require particular attention to carry.</item>
 
</description-list>

<text>If a character is wielding two weapons, he may always choose to attack
with the main weapon only at no penalty.  In this case the weapon in
his off hand is considered merely carried, and is not <dquo>ready</dquo> for
combat. An attack with the off-hand weapon is always made with the
full penalty, regardless of what the <dquo>main hand</dquo> is doing.</text>

<text>Note that the \emph{Ambidexterity} skill from Martial Arts can reduce
the dual-weapon penalty; and that the \emph{Multi-weapon Style} skill
allows the character to strike more than once during a single
action. A different approach is the use of the \emph{Multitarget}
skill which allows the martial artist to strike multiple times with a
single weapon in a single action.</text>
        </section><!-- /Dual-wielding Weapons or Weapon and Shield -->
        <section><!-- Combat Overview -->
            <title>Combat Overview</title>
<text>Resolving an attack is a three-step process:</text>

<numbered-list>
    <item>The attacker makes a strike roll.  A strike roll is an attempt
  to hit an opponent using a weapon or ability.</item>
    <item>The defender may attempt a defensive maneuver.  A defensive
  maneuver is a special skill that is used to avoid or reduce the
  damage from an incoming attack.</item>
    <item>If the attack was successful, damage is rolled, calculated, and
  applied to the target.</item>
</numbered-list>

<text>This process is explained in detail below.</text>
        </section><!-- /Combat Overview -->
        <section><!-- Attacking -->
            <title>Attacking</title>
<text>An attack is nearly anything that you try to do to an opponent during
your turn.  Typically an attack is a physical strike against your
opponent with a weapon (such as your fist or a sword), but it could
also be the use of a supernatural ability, magic spell, or a modern
device such as a gun.</text>

<text>When you attack, you use one of your skills in an attempt to damage
your opponent.  Normally, this will be a <dquo>basic attack</dquo> skill from
Martial Arts.  Any time you make an attack like this, you roll a
\textbf{Strike Roll}.  \emph{Strike roll} is just a special name for a
skill roll in combat---they work just like normal skill rolls.  To
recap, roll a number of D20s equal to your level of the skill you are
using to attack with (i.e. use the Large Sword skill to strike with
your bastard sword), add your attribute and any bonuses or negatives.
For each die that hits 25 or better, you have a success.  \textbf{If
  you have at least one success, you strike the target.}  Otherwise
you miss your target.</text>

<text>Some attacks don't require a skill roll.  This includes special
attacks that automatically hit your opponent (such as certain
abilities from Martial Arts) as well as magical spells or supernatural
powers that are auto-targeting.  For example, the magic spell
\emph{Ray of Heat} automatically hits your opponent, with no strike
roll needed.</text>
        </section><!-- /Attacking -->
        <section><!-- Defending -->
            <title>Defending</title>
<text>The target of an attack usually receives an attempt to defend himself.
\textbf{Defending is using your skills to avoid getting hit by an
  incoming attack.}  There are many different skills that are
available for defense.  They are called defensive maneuvers. A
defensive maneuver is a special skill or ability that you use
specifically in response to being attacked; otherwise they work like
normal skills.  A target of an attack may attempt to use any
\emph{one} defensive maneuver in order to protect himself from the
attack. The most common are parrying, blocking, and the \emph{Dodge}
skill.  These are described below.  Other defensive maneuvers may be
found in the Martial Arts section.</text>

<description-list>
    <item description="Parry" > Parrying is using your weapon to deflect a blow from
  another weapon.  Parrying may only be performed with melee weapons,
  against either a melee or hand to hand attack.  Parrying is
  ineffective versus other attacks, such as explosives, bullets,
  chemical splashes, magical energy, etc.  Parry is not a skill
  itself, rather the skill roll for parrying is based on the weapon
  skill you are trying to parry with.  For example, you would use your
  \emph{Knife} skill to parry using your dagger.  You must have your
  weapon drawn and ready in order to use it to parry.  Note, that this
  is the same skill that is used for attacking with your weapon, so
  most characters will have a good chance at parrying.  \textbf{A
    weapon or similar combat skill is used for parrying.  Also note
    that parrying is always subject to GM approval.  The GM determines
    the outcome of a successful parry, though it usually means that
    the defender avoids all damage.  However, if you are parrying an
    attack from a heavy or large weapon with a small weapon, the GM
    might want to impose a different outcome.}</item>
    <item description="Block"> Blocking is putting a shield between you and an incoming
  attack.  \textbf{Upon a successful block, a shield's armor values
    are added to any armor that you are currently wearing} (see
  below).  You can attempt to block any incoming attack that you are
  aware of.  Blocking can be used against melee attacks, missile
  weapons, arrows, gunshots, and unusual attacks such as a fireball or
  an acid splash.  Larger shields will make it easier to block, more
  info can be found in the shields section.  \textbf{The \emph{Shield}
    skill is used for blocking.  Blocking means that the blow hits,
    but the defender gets to add the armor of the shield to his own
    armor value.}  In the case of a non-standard attack, such as a
  splash of acid, the shield simply stops a certain percentage of the
  damage outright.</item>
    <item description="Dodge" >one of the best types of defense.  \emph{Dodge} is an
  (expensive) skill; dodging is moving your body out of the way of an
  incoming attack.  By sidestepping, ducking, throwing yourself to the
  ground or similar action you can avoid any attack completely and
  take no damage.  The \emph{Dodge} skill is used for dodging.  On a
  successful dodge the blow doesn't hit, period.  However, dodge is a
  high rank skill, so most characters will not be very good at it.</item>
</description-list>

<text>Now that you know what the types of defenses are, we are going to lump
them together and call them <dquo>defense</dquo> for the sake of simplicity for
what is to follow.</text>

<text>To defend against an attack, you must succeed at your defending skill
roll.  And you must have MORE successes at the attacker had in his
attack roll.  For example, if an attacker has 3 successes to strike
you, then you would need at least 4 successes at your defensive skill
to protect yourself.  If you have fewer successes than the attacker,
you are struck by the attack.  You can only attempt to defend against
an attack with one type of defense.  You can only try to block, dodge,
or parry once per attack but not multiple of these at a time (i.e. you
cannot attempt to block and dodge the same attack).  You can attempt
to parry one attack and then dodge the next attack, however.</text>

<text>If you are struck you will likely take damage from the attack.  Also
note that you cannot defend (parry, block, or dodge) an attack that
you did not know about!</text>

<text>Note that there are other defensive maneuvers aside from Dodge, Parry,
and Block.  These include certain magic spells (Blink, for example),
martial arts abilities (such as Preemptive Dodge), or supernatural
powers.  Regardless of what defense a character chooses to use, only
ONE defense maneuver may be used against any one incoming
attack\footnote{Some magical spells or super powers of a defensive
  nature are active for a set duration---usually several rounds.  Such
  spells, such as full barrier, are not defensive maneuvers.  These
  spells are independent of defense.  A character using such a spell
  may still use a defensive maneuver if she chooses to.  Magical
  spells, martial arts techniques, and supernatural abilities are
  considered defense maneuvers whenever they are single-use effects
  that are used against only one specific attack (such as
  Blink).}\footnote{Some attacks, such as automatically targeting
  magical spells, will strike your opponent regardless of defense.
  Defensive maneuvers are ineffective against these spells.  For
  example, Ray of Heat as discussed above will always strike its
  target.  Call Lightning will always strike its target, if the caster
  succeeds on his magical control roll to cast the spell.  For these
  abilities, defensive maneuvers have no effect.}.</text>
        </section><!-- /Defending -->
        <section><!-- Damage -->
            <title>Damage</title>
<text>When an attack hits its target, it will inflict damage upon it.  Every
weapon has a damage rating associated with it as well as a damage type
(for example: a dagger is a 1D6 P weapon).  The damage rating is the
amount of damage it will do, and the damage type reflects how the
weapon deals its damage.</text>

<text>Here's a key of the different damage types with abbreviations in
parenthesis and what they are typically associated with:</text>

<description-list>
    <item description="Piercing (P)"> using a sharp tip to penetrate the target creating
  a hole or deep cut within the target.  Some melee weapons, most
  bullets, and other penetrating weapons deal piercing damage.  Armor
  can protect against this type of damage.</item>
    <item description="Slashing (S)"> using a cutting edge to slice the target creating
  a fairly shallow long cut within the target.  Most melee weapons
  such as knives and swords, as well as lasers deal slashing damage.
  Armor can protect against this type of damage.</item>
    <item description="Crushing (C)"> using a heavy blunt edge in an attempt to fracture
  or break the target.  This is typically the hardest damage to
  protect against, and as such, is a favorite type of damage for melee
  combat.  Punches, clubs, staves, and explosions deal crushing
  damage.  Armor can protect against this type of damage.</item>
    <item description="Undefined (U)"> using energy to cause damage within the target.
  This can include electricity, heat, magic, sickness and other
  <dquo>odd</dquo> types of damage.  Normal armor cannot protect against this
  type of damage.  Only your character's Base Armor (BA) can protect
  you from undefined damage.  Any time someone takes undefined damage
  he or she will always take at least one point of damage, regardless
  of the base armor.</item>
    <item description="Direct (D)"> extremely damaging attacks deal D damage.  There is
  no way to protect yourself from direct damage, as it will bypass all
  armor and other protections that you have on.  Damage from D attacks
  is subtracted directly from hit points (HP).</item>
</description-list>

<text>Consider the dagger again: 1D6 P</text>

<text>This tells us that a strike from a Dagger deals 1D6 damage.  Also, we
know that it deals piercing damage.</text>

<text>Ok, so now we've got our weapon's damage rating and it's damage type.
Roll the given damage as described in the dice rolling section at the
beginning of the rules section.  The higher the damage roll, the more
severe the attack was upon the target.</text>

<text>After the damage roll is determined, subtract that damage from the
target's Hit Points (HP).  Armor can reduce the damage taken, which
brings us to$\ldots$</text>
        </section><!-- /Damage -->
        <section><!-- Armor -->
            <title>Armor</title>
<text>Armor is any covering that you are wearing or behind that will absorb
some of the damage applied to you.  All armor is given three numerical
ratings for piercing, slashing, and crushing protection.  The higher
any one number is, the better it will protect you from that type of
damage.  Typically this value sequence is represented as P/S/C
(Piercing/Slashing/Crushing).  An example would be 3/2/3, which
provides 3 points of piercing protection, two points of slashing
protection, and 3 points of crushing protection.</text>

<text>When taking damage subtract the armor value, which matches the damage
type of the weapon, from the damage amount.</text>

<text>Here are a few examples:</text>

<example>
    <title>Carlos vs. the Bandit</title>
    <text>Carlos was attacked by a bandit
  with a short sword.  The bandit made his skill roll to attack and
  had three successes.  Carlos attempts to parry and had only one
  success.  Since Carlos has fewer successes than the attacker, he
  fails to parry and takes full damage.  The GM rolls damage for the
  bandit and determines that the bandit's sword blow deals 8 damage.
  Carlos is wearing soft leather armor, which has a P/S/C rating of
  2/3/0. We know the short sword dealt 8 damage.  But it is a slashing
  weapon (denoted by the S in the weapon damage), so the armor
  provides 3 points of protection against this attack.  So we take the
  damage of the weapon (8) and the amount of protection the armor
  gives (3), and subtract the armor value from the weapon damage.  So,
  Carlos just took 5 damage (8-3=5).</text>
</example>

<example>
    <title>Lira the Gladiator</title>
    <text>Lira is fighting a gladiator-style
  duel.  Her opponent attacks with a spear and has two successes to
  hit.  Lira wants to block and rolls her shield skill.  She has four
  successes on her skill roll.  This means that she successfully
  blocked the incoming attack with her shield.  The GM rolls damage
  for the attack and gets 14 P.  (that's a strong blow!)  Lira is
  using a Splint Shield (P/S/C of 9/9/9) and is wearing Hard Leather
  armor (3/4/1).  First, apply the damage against Lira's shield.  Her
  shield has an armor of 9 versus P.  This means that her shield stops
  9 points of the incoming damage.  However, since the spear blow
  dealt more damage than her shield has armor, the weapon continues
  through her shield---which now has a hole in it.  Lira now deals
  with the remaining 5 damage.  (14 damage was dealt, minus the 9
  taken by the shield = 5).  Her armor has a P value of 3, meaning
  that she only takes 2 points of damage to her HP total.  (14 damage
  - 9 from shield - 3 from armor = 2)</text>
</example>

<text>Now that you have that, lets introduce a few tricks.  The entire next
two paragraphs are incredibly important, so pay attention!</text>

<text>Weapons that deal undefined or direct damage (U or D damage) bypass
all armor values.  Undefined damage can be protected against by your
character's Base Armor (BA) sub-attribute.  Just subtract the BA from
the damage taken as if the BA was normal armor.  Note that Base Armor
is not used for protecting against anything but undefined damage!  A
target will always lose at least one HP when hit with an attack that
deals undefined damage.</text>

<text>Direct damage cannot be protected against.  Not by normal armor, Base
Armor, not anything.  It's harsh, so be careful when on the receiving
end of something that deals D damage.  D damage is applied directly to
your Hit Points.</text>
            <section><!-- Armor Piercing -->
                <title>Armor Piercing</title>
<text>Some weapons have a note that says <dquo>AP</dquo> followed by some number.
This kind of weapon has an unusual ability to pierce armor.  If an
armored target is struck by a weapon with <dquo>AP</dquo>, the armor is reduced
by the AP number for the purposes of damage calculation.  Note, that
this cannot go negative.  If an <dquo>AP: 10</dquo> weapon strikes someone
wearing 5 armor, then the armor is totally ignored.  It does not,
however, go to -5.</text>

<example>
    <title>Lira Strikes With Gladius</title>
    <text>Lira is wielding a gladius,
  which is a type of short sword that has AP: 5.  She successfully
  strikes her opponent, and rolls 11 damage.  Her opponent has an
  armor of 7 versus slashing damage.  First, deduct the AP from the
  armor: 7 armor - 5 AP = 2.  Then, deduct the armor from the damage
  like normal: 11 damage - 2 armor = 9 damage.  Lira's opponent takes
  9 damage.

  Consider the same situation as above, but assume that Lira's
  opponent's armor is only a 3 versus slashing.  First, deduct the AP
  form the armor: 3 armor - 5 AP = -2.  However, this cannot be
  negative, so we cap it at zero.  Now, deduct the result from the
  damage: 11 damage - 0 = 11.  Lira's opponent takes all 11 damage.</text>
</example>

<text>AP is effective against armored targets, but it does nothing against
unarmored targets.  Note, that most weapons with AP don't deal very
much damage.  It is usually a good idea to use AP weapons versus
armored targets only, and use <dquo>normal</dquo> weapons versus unarmored
targets.</text>
            </section><!-- /Armor Piercing -->
        </section><!-- /Armor -->
    <section><!-- Hit Points -->
        <title>Hit Points</title>
<text>Hit points are numbers used to represent how injured or healthy a
character is.  A character will have TWO Hit Point numbers.  Your
maximum Hit Points determines how tough your character is at full
health.  This number will rarely change.  It is determined by your BLD
and WIL attributes, and will rarely change unless your attributes
change.</text>

<text>Your \emph{current} hit points is the most important number.  It will
likely change frequently during combat.  Hit points are generally
represented as a fraction: ${Current~HP}\over{Max~HP}$.  When the game
begins, your character will be fully healthy and uninjured.  Thus,
when starting, your current HP will be equal to your maximum.</text>

<src img="/Map/Forte-marghera-02.jpg" />

<text>As you get injured, any damage you take (after applying armor, etc.)
will be applied to your current HP.  As you get injured, your current
HP drops.  Over time, your body will heal itself, and your HP will go
up.  Seeking medical attention will speed this process.  Other things,
like magic or cybernetic devices, can heal you as well.</text>

<text>Your current HP can never exceed your maximum HP.  As a general rule
for minor injuries (less than 5 HP), you gain back 1 HP per day of
average activity.  For significant HP losses, it takes (Max~HP -
Current~HP)$^{2}$ days to fully recover your HP.</text>

<text>If a character is resting and is under basic medical care, then your
healing time is cut in HALF.  If your character is under the care of a
professional Doctor or Healer, healing time is cut to one QUARTER of
normal time.</text>

<text>If your current HP falls below 0, your character falls unconscious.
It is possible to remain conscious by making a willpower check at -X,
where X is the amount below zero your HP are.  If your current HP are
below 0, your character is bleeding badly (internal bleeding is
possible too) and you will loose 1 HP per round, unless you receive
medical attention.  If your current HP ever reaches the negative of
your maximum HP, you have died.</text>
    </section><!-- /Hit Points -->
    </section><!-- /Combat Sequence and Initiative -->
</chapter>